<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "oodialog.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooDialog Reference XML file.
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2005-2024, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    # Portions Copyright (c) 2004, IBM Corporation. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<chapter id="chapResources" xreflabel="resources"><title>Resources</title>
<indexterm><primary>Resources</primary></indexterm>
<para>
  In the Windows OS, a <emphasis role="italic">resource</emphasis>, is binary data used by a
  Windows-based application.  Usually, the binary data is attached to one of the application's executable
  files (*.exe or *.dll.)  However, the binary data can also be generated dynamically in memory. (Which
  is common in ooDialog, for example the dialog template for a UserDialog is generated in memory.)
</para>
<para>
  The data in standard resources describes things familar to ooDialog programmers like, dialog boxes,
  icons, menus, cursors, bitmaps, fonts, etc. The standard resources also include accelerator tables,
  string-table entries, message-table entries, and other resources that ooDialog does not currently have
  support for, but may support in the future.
</para>
<para>
  This chapter describes ooDialog classes that provide access to Windows resources.  The classes allow
  the oodialog programmer to use and manipulate resources in their ooDialog programs.  This is an area of
  ooDialog that is slated for future improvements.
</para>


<section id="sctResourceClasses"><title>Resource Classes</title>
<para> The classes listed in the following table are documented in this chapter:
<table id="tblResourcesClasses" frame="all"> <title>ooDialog Resource Classes</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colwidth="1*" /><colspec colwidth="4*" />
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Class</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>Image <xref linkend="clsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Objects used to work with and manipulate images.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>ImageList <xref linkend="clsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Objects used to efficiently manage large sets of images.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Mouse <xref linkend="clsMouse"/></entry>
<entry>Objects used to efficiently manage large sets of images.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>ResourceImage <xref linkend="clsResourceImage"/></entry>
<entry>Objects used to represent modules that contain resources.</entry>
</row>
</tbody></tgroup>
</table>
</para>
</section>

<section id="clsImage" xreflabel="Image"><title>Image Class</title>
<indexterm><primary>Image class</primary></indexterm>
<para>
  The Image class is used to work with and manipulate images.  Currently, the image types supported include bitmaps,
  icons, cursors (cursors are a type of icon), and enhanced metafiles.  The enhanced metafile support is very limited at
  this time.
</para>
<para>
  The class supports loading images from files, from resources contained in any executable files (*.exe and *.dll,) from
  the files associated with the ooDialog program, and from the generally available system resources.
</para>
<para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> The <computeroutput>.Image</computeroutput> class is the future direction that
  ooDialog will take for working with images, including bitmaps.  This is a more flexible approach than the older bitmap
  methods used when ooDialog was first developed.  It will allow access to more of the modern features of the Windows
  user interface than the older approach does.  The older bitmap methods were designed to work with Windows 3.1 and have
  a number of limitations.  The ooDialog programmer is strongly encouraged to migrate her code towards the .Image
  class.  The older bitmap methods should be considered deprecated, to a degree.  Unfortunately, replacement methods for
  all of the older bitmap methods have not as yet been implemented.  So, the older methods may still be necessary for
  some situations.
</para>
<para id="paraClsImageRelease">
  A loaded image takes up some small part of the systems's resources. It is common to release an image
  when the programmer is done with it.  The .Image class has the
<xref linkend="mthReleaseClsImage"/> method to allow the programmer to release the image, if
  desired.  It is <emphasis role="bold">important</emphasis> to note that when the ooDialog program ends,
  that is when the ooRexx interpreter process ends, the Windows operating system cleans up all the system
  resources associated with any images used in the ooDialog program.  Not releasing images does no harm
  and the ooDialog programmer should not be unduly worried about this aspect of images.
</para>
<para>
  In addition, when images are loaded as shared, the operating system completely manages them.  Shared
  images should not be released.  The .Image class tracks which images are loaded as shared and will not
  call the underlying API to release a shared image. So, again, the ooDialog programmer does not need to
  worry about mistakenly releasing a shared image.  Once an image is released, it is no longer valid and
  the object can not be used as an argument to methods requiring a valid image.  This applies to shared
  images also, even though they are not actually released.
</para>
<para>
  Why then would the ooDialog programmer want to release images?  The main reason would be to minimize
  the memory footprint of an application.  In a normal ooDialog program, with five to ten images,
  releasing the images would have no noticeable impact on the memory footprint. However, in a long
  running Rexx program that opened and closed a lot of dialogs that used images, releasing the images as
  the dialogs were closed would make a difference in the long run.  The operating system would not clean
  up the resources used by the images until the main Rexx program ended.  If the main program ran for
  days, or maybe was never intended to be shut down, it would make sense to release images that were no
  longer needed.
</para>

<section id="sctMethodsImageClass"><title>Method Table</title>

<para>
  Instances of the <computeroutput>Image</computeroutput> class implement the methods listed in the following table:
</para>

<table id="tblImageMethods" frame="all">
<title>Methods of the <computeroutput>Image</computeroutput> Class</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colwidth="1*" /><colspec colwidth="4*" />
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Method</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Class Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthColorRef"/></entry>
<entry>Provides a way to construct a COLORREF from the red, green, and blue values of a color.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthFromFilesClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Returns an array of <computeroutput>.Image</computeroutput> objects when given an array of file names.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthFromIDsClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Uses an array of resource IDs to instantiate and return an array of <computeroutput>.Image</computeroutput> objects.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetBValue"/></entry>
<entry>Returns the blue component of a RGB color.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetGValue"/></entry>
<entry>Returns the green component of a RGB color.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetImageClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Instantiates a new <computeroutput>.Image</computeroutput> object from either an image file or from one of the system images.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetRValue"/></entry>
<entry>Returns the red component of a RGB color.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthNewClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Image objects can not be instantiated from Rexx code using the <emphasis role="italic">new</emphasis>, other class methods are used.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Used to translate a symbolic name to its integer value</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthUserIcon"/></entry>
<entry>Returns a new image object from an icon resource added to the Rexx dialog object.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Instance Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthHandleClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Returns the Windows system handle to the image this object represents.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthIsNullClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Tests if the image object is valid.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthReleaseClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Releases the operating system resources used for the image.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSystemErrorCodeClsImage"/></entry>
<entry>Reflects any system error codes that are detected while working with an image object.</entry>
</row>
</tbody></tgroup>
</table>

</section>

<section id="mthColorRef" xreflabel="colorRef"><title>colorRef (Class Method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>colorRef</primary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

>>-.Image~colorRef(--+---+--+-----+--+-----+--)-----------------><
                     +-R-+  +-,-G-+  +-,-B-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  The Windows API uses a COLORREF to specify a RGB color.  This is a 32-bit number with a
  hexadecimal format of: <computeroutput>0x00bbggrr</computeroutput>. The
  <computeroutput>colorRef</computeroutput>() method provides a way to construct a COLORREF from the red,
  green, and blue values.  Each color value (red, green, or blue) is a whole number in the range of 0 to
  255 inclusive.
</para>
<para>
  Windows also defines 2 special values for a COLORREF, CLR_NONE and CLR_DEFAULT. To get the numeric
  value for either of these values use CLR_NONE or CLR_DEFAULT for the R argument. E.g.,
  <computeroutput>ref = .Image~colorRef("CLR_NONE")</computeroutput>.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    All the arguments are optional, with 0 being the default for any omitted argument.
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>R</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The red component of the RGB color, or one of the CLR_NONE / CLR_DEFAULT keywords. Case is not
          significant for either of the two keywords.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>G</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The green component of the RGB value.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>B</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The blue component of the RGB value.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return is a valid RGB color, specified as a COLORREF.  Some method arguments related to images
      or colors require a COLORREF.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
 ref = .Image~colorRef(245, 89, 255)
 say 'A fancy purple:' ref '(0x' || ref~d2x~right(8, '0')')'
 say

::requires 'oodPlain.cls'

/* Output:

A fancy purple: 16734709 (0x00FF59F5)

*/
]]>
</programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::colorRef() [class method] -->


<section id="mthFromFilesClsImage" xreflabel="fromFiles"><title>fromFiles (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>fromFiles</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--fromFiles(--files--+--------+--+--------+--+---------+--)---><
                       +-,-type-+  +-,-size-+  +-,-flags-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Gets an array of .Image objects, using an array of file names.  This method is useful to load more
  than one image at a time, when all the images have the same specifications, type, size, and flags.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>files</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          An array of file names to use to instantiate the .Image objects.  The array can contain any
          number of file names, but it can not be sparse.  That is, each index of the array must contain
          a file name.  If an incorrect item is detected in the array, then a syntax error is raised and
          no images are returned.
        </para>
        <para>
          On the other hand, if there is an error with the Win32 API loading an image, then no syntax
          error is raised.  The index in the array for that image is left empty.  One way to check for
          this type of error is to compare the number of items in the returned array with the number of
          items in file name array.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>type</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Specifies the type of the image, bitmap, icon, or cursor. You can use
          the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric
          value for one of the following symbols:
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>IMAGE_BITMAP</member> <member>IMAGE_ICON</member>
          <member>IMAGE_CURSOR</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The default is IMAGE_BITMAP.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>size</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object that specifies the size of the image.  The default
          is a size of 0x0.  Under most circumstances this indicates that the actual size of the image
          should be used.  However, the MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation should
          be consulted for other meanings.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>flags</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The load resource flags for the LoadImage() API.  The flags are one or more of the following
          symbols. You can use the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric
          value for any of the following symbols.  The <xref linkend="mthOrClsDlgUtil"/> method of
          the <xref linkend="clsDlgUtil"/> class can be used to combine more than one of the
          symbols if needed.
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>LR_DEFAULTCOLOR</member>    <member>LR_CREATEDIBSECTION</member>
          <member>LR_DEFAULTSIZE</member>     <member>LR_LOADFROMFILE</member>
          <member>LR_LOADMAP3DCOLORS</member> <member>LR_LOADTRANSPARENT</member>
          <member>LR_MONOCHROME</member>      <member>LR_SHARED</member>
          <member>LR_VGACOLOR</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The default is LR_LOADFROMFILE.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The method returns an array of .Image objects, one object for each image that was loaded from a
      file successfully.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the Win32 API: <computeroutput>LoadImage()</computeroutput>. Use the
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation to get more information on the arguments to
      this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[


      ]]>
      </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::fromFiles() [class method] -->

<section id="mthFromIDsClsImage" xreflabel="fromIDs"><title>fromIDs (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>fromIDs</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--fromIDs(--ids,--+--------+--+--------+--+---------+--)------><
                    +-,-type-+  +-,-size-+  +-,-flags-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Uses an array of resource IDs to instantiate and return an array of .Image objects.  This method loads
  the system image resources referenced by the resource IDs in the array.  The images must all be the
  same type and size, and use the same load flags.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>ids</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          An array of resource IDs to use to instantiate the .Image objects.  The array can contain any
          number of IDs, but it can not be sparse.  That is, each index of the array must contain a
          number.  If an incorrect item is detected in the array, then a syntax error is raised and no
          images are returned.
        </para>
        <para>
          On the other hand, if there is an error with the Win32 API loading an image, then no syntax
          error is raised.  The index in the array for that image is left empty.  One way to check for
          this type of error is to compare the number of items in the returned array with the number of
          items in ID array.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>type</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Specifies the type of the image: bitmap, icon, or cursor. You can use
          the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric value for one of the
          following symbols:
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>IMAGE_BITMAP</member> <member>IMAGE_ICON</member>
          <member>IMAGE_CURSOR</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The default is IMAGE_ICON
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>size</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object that specifies the size of the image.  The default
          is a size of 0x0.  Under most circumstances this indicates that the actual size of the image
          should be used.  However, the MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation should
          be consulted for other meanings.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>flags</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The load resource flags for the LoadImage() API.  The flags are one or more of the following
          symbols. You can use the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric
          value for any of the following symbols.  The <xref linkend="mthOrClsDlgUtil"/> method of
          the <xref linkend="clsDlgUtil"/> class can be used to combine more than one of the
          symbols if needed.
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>LR_DEFAULTCOLOR</member>    <member>LR_CREATEDIBSECTION</member>
          <member>LR_DEFAULTSIZE</member>     <member>LR_LOADFROMFILE</member>
          <member>LR_LOADMAP3DCOLORS</member> <member>LR_LOADTRANSPARENT</member>
          <member>LR_MONOCHROME</member>      <member>LR_SHARED</member>
          <member>LR_VGACOLOR</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The default is LR_SHARED | LR_DEFAULTSIZE.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The method returns an array of .Image objects, one object for each system image that was loaded
      successfully.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the Win32 API: <computeroutput>LoadImage()</computeroutput>. Use the
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation to get more information on the arguments to
      this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[


    ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::fromIDs() [class method] -->

<section id="mthGetBValue" xreflabel="getBValue"><title>getBValue (Class Method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>getRValue</primary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>-.Image~getBValue(--colorRef--)----------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns the blue component of a RGB color.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
    The single argument is:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>colorRef</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A RGB color, a COLORREF. See the <xref linkend="mthColorRef"/> method for a brief discussion of these terms.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The return is the blue component of the specified RGB color.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    See the <link linkend="exampleGetRValueClsImage">example</link> for the <emphasis role="italic">getRValue</emphasis>
    method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::getBValue() [class method] -->

<section id="mthGetGValue" xreflabel="getGValue"><title>getGValue (Class Method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>getRValue</primary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>-.Image~getGValue(--colorRef--)----------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns the green component of a RGB color.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The single argument is:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>colorRef</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A RGB color, a COLORREF.  See the <xref linkend="mthColorRef"/>() method for a
            brief discussion of these terms.
          </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The return is the green component of the specified RGB color.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    See the <link linkend="exampleGetRValueClsImage">example</link> for the <emphasis role="italic">getRValue</emphasis>
    method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::getGValue() [class method] -->

<section id="mthGetImageClsImage" xreflabel="getImage"><title>getImage (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>getImage</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getImage(--id--+--------+--+--------+--+---------+--)-------><
                   +-,-type-+  +-,-size-+  +-,-flags-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Instantiates a new .Image object from either an image file or from one of the system images.  When id
  is a number then the corresponding system image is used.  Otherwise, id is taken to be the name of an
  image file.  File names can be either relative or absolute.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term>id</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        If not a number, then id must be the name of a stand-alone image file.
      </para>
      <para>
        If id is a number than it is taken to be the resource id of an image provided by the system.  The
        following are the symbolic names for all the system images. You can use
        the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric value for any of the
        following symbols:
        <simplelist type='vert' columns='4'>
        <member>IDI_APPLICATION</member> <member>IDI_HAND</member> <member>IDI_QUESTION</member>
        <member>IDI_EXCLAMATION</member> <member>IDI_ASTERISK</member> <member>IDI_WINLOGO</member>
        <member></member> <member></member> <member></member>
        <member></member> <member></member> <member></member>
        <member></member>

        <member>OCR_NORMAL</member> <member>OCR_IBEAM</member> <member>OCR_WAIT</member>
        <member>OCR_CROSS</member> <member>OCR_UP</member> <member>OCR_SIZENWSE</member>
        <member>OCR_SIZENESW</member> <member>OCR_SIZEWE</member> <member>OCR_SIZENS</member>
        <member>OCR_SIZEALL</member> <member>OCR_NO</member> <member>OCR_HAND</member>
        <member>OCR_APPSTARTING</member>

        <member>OBM_CLOSE</member> <member>OBM_UPARROW</member> <member>OBM_DNARROW</member>
        <member>OBM_RGARROW</member> <member>OBM_LFARROW</member> <member>OBM_REDUCE</member>
        <member>OBM_ZOOM</member> <member>OBM_RESTORE</member> <member>OBM_REDUCED</member>
        <member>OBM_ZOOMD</member> <member>OBM_RESTORED</member> <member>OBM_UPARROWD</member>
        <member>OBM_DNARROWD</member>

        <member>OBM_RGARROWD</member> <member>OBM_LFARROWD</member> <member>OBM_DNARROW</member>
        <member>OBM_COMBO</member> <member>OBM_UPARROWI</member> <member>OBM_DNARROWI</member>
        <member>OBM_RGARROWI</member> <member>OBM_LFARROWI</member> <member>OBM_SIZE</member>
        <member>OBM_BTSIZE</member> <member>OBM_CHECK</member> <member>OBM_CHECKBOXES</member>
        <member>OBM_BTNCORNERS</member>
        </simplelist>
      </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>type</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A number between 0 and 255 that specifies the type of the image: bitmap, icon, or cursor. You can use
        the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric value for one of the
        following symbols:
        <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
        <member>IMAGE_BITMAP</member> <member>IMAGE_ICON</member>
        <member>IMAGE_CURSOR</member>
        </simplelist>
      </para>
      <para>
        The default is IMAGE_BITMAP.
      </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>size</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object that specifies the size of the image.
      </para>
      <para>
        The default is a size of 0x0.  Under most circumstances this indicates that the actual size of
        the image should be used.  However, the MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/>
        documentation should be consulted for other meanings.
      </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>flags</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The load resource flags for the LoadImage() API.  The flags are one or more of the following
        symbols. You can use the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric
        value for any of the following symbols.  The <xref linkend="mthOrClsDlgUtil"/> method of
        the <xref linkend="clsDlgUtil"/> class can be used to combine more than one of the
        symbols if needed.
        <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
        <member>LR_DEFAULTCOLOR</member>    <member>LR_CREATEDIBSECTION</member>
        <member>LR_DEFAULTSIZE</member>     <member>LR_LOADFROMFILE</member>
        <member>LR_LOADMAP3DCOLORS</member> <member>LR_LOADTRANSPARENT</member>
        <member>LR_MONOCHROME</member>      <member>LR_SHARED</member>
        <member>LR_VGACOLOR</member>
        </simplelist>
      </para>
      <para>
        When id specifies a file name, the default flags are LR_LOADFROMFILE, othewise the default flags
        are LR_SHARED | LR_DEFAULTSIZE.  Note that the system images must be loaded as shared.
      </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      A .Image object that represents the image specified.  If an error happened, the object may not be
      valid.  Use the <xref linkend="mthIsNullClsImage"/> method to check if the image is
      valid.  If there was an error, <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/> may help
      to determine the error.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the Win32 API: <computeroutput>LoadImage()</computeroutput>. Use the
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation to get more information on the arguments to
      this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
    flags = .DlgUtil~or(.Image~toID(LR_DEFAULTSIZE), .Image~toID(LR_SHARED), -
                        .Image~toID(LR_LOADMAP3DCOLORS))

    questionIcon = .Image~getImage(.Image~toID(IDI_QUESTION),              -
                                   .Image~toID(IMAGE_ICON),                -
                                   .Size~new(0, 0), flags)
    if questionIcon~isNull then do
      say 'Error getting the question icon.  Error code:' .systemErrorCode
    end

    /* Note that you can always use the raw numeric value for the args.
     * This works just as well:
     */
    questionIcon = .Image~getImage(32514, 1, .Size~new(0, 0), 36928)
    if questionIcon~isNull then do
      say 'Error getting the question icon.  Error code:' .systemErrorCode
    end

    ]]>
    </programlisting>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::getImage() [class method] -->


<section id="mthGetRValue" xreflabel="getRValue"><title>getRValue (Class Method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>getRValue</primary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>-.Image~getRValue(--colorRef--)----------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns the red component of a RGB color.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The single argument is:
      <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>colorRef</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A RGB color, a COLORREF.  See the <xref linkend="mthColorRef"/>() method for a
          brief discussion of these terms.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return is the red component of the specified RGB color.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <programlisting id="exampleGetRValueClsImage">
    <![CDATA[
      progressBar = self~newProgressBar("IDC_PB_FILES")
      if progressBar <> .nil then do
        purple = .Image~colorRef(245, 89, 255)

        say 'Going to set the background color for the progress bar'
        oldColor = progressBar~backgroundColor(purple)

        say 'Old background color was:' oldColor '(0x'oldColor~d2x')'
        say '  Red:  ' .Image~getRValue(oldColor)
        say '  Green:' .Image~getGValue(oldColor)
        say '  Blue: ' .IMage~getBValue(oldColor)
        say
      end

      /* Output might be:

      Going to set the background color for the progress bar
      Old background color was: 11460781 (0xAEE0AD)
        Red:   173
        Green: 224
        Blue:  174

      */
    ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::getRValue() [class method] -->

<section id="mthNewClsImage" xreflabel="new"><title>new (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>new</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>

<para>
  The Image class does not allow new Image objects to be instantiated from Rexx code using the new()
  method.  New Image objects are obtained through one of the other Image class methods, or they are
  returned from methods of other classes.
</para>
<para>
  These methods are used to create new Image object(s).
  <simplelist type='horiz' columns='1'>
  <member>Image (class) method:<xref linkend="mthGetImageClsImage"/></member>
  <member>Image (class) method:<xref linkend="mthFromFilesClsImage"/></member>
  <member>Image (class) method:<xref linkend="mthFromIDsClsImage"/></member>
  <member>Image (class) method:<xref linkend="mthUserIcon"/></member>
  <member>ResourceImage (instance) method:<xref linkend="mthGetImageClsResourceImage"/></member>
  <member>ResourceImage (instance) method:<xref linkend="mthGetImagesClsResourceImage"/></member>
  </simplelist>
</para>
</section>  <!-- End Image::new() [class method] -->

<section id="mthToIDClsImage" xreflabel="toID"><title>toID (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>id</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--toID(--symbolicName--)-----------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  The <emphasis role="italic">toID</emphasis> method is used to translate a symbolic name to its
  integer value.  In general the symbolic name is related to images or color.  Many of the arguments to
  the methods of classes related to images use the integer value of a symbolic ID in the Windows API.
  This method allows the programmer to use the symbolic ID without knowing what the actual integer value
  is.
</para>
<para>
  Take for example the task of retrieving the 'Question' icon resource from the system using the
<xref linkend="mthGetImageClsImage"/> method.  The ooDialog programmer could
  either use the numerical value of 32514 or use the <emphasis role="italic">toID</emphasis> method as
  follows.  Note that the two invocations of getImage() are equivalent:
</para>
  <programlisting>
  <![CDATA[
    qIcon = .Image~getImage(.Image~toID(IDI_QUESTION))

    qIcon = .Image~getImage(32514)
  ]]>
  </programlisting>
<para>
  The symbolic ID keywords are spelled exactly as Microsoft spells them in the
  MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> which allows the ooDialog to easily look up the meaning
  of any single ID while at the same time reducing the documentation task for the ooDialog
  developers.  The keywords are case sensitive and must be all in upper-case.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The single required argument is:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>symbolicName</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The symbolic name whose numeric value is desired.  There any number of symbolic names
            and they are not listed here.  Rather the symbolic names are listed in the documentation
            for the methods they are applicable to.
          </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return value is the numeric value of the symbol.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
    say 'The numeric value of the IDI_WINLOGO symbol is:' .Image~toID(IDI_WINLOGO)
    /*
      Output on the console would be:

      The numeric value of the IDI_WINLOGO symbol is: 32517
    */
    ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::id() [class method] -->

<section id="mthUserIcon" xreflabel="userIcon"><title>userIcon (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>userIcon</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>userIcon</primary><secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--userIcon(--dlg--,--id--+---------+--+---------+--)----------><
                           +-,-size--+  +-,-opts--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns a new <computeroutput>Image</computeroutput> object from an icon resource added to the dialog through the
 <xref linkend="mthAddIconResource"/>() method.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term>dlg [required]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      The Rexx dialog object to which the user icon was added.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>id [required]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
       The resource ID of the icon. Can be numeric or <xref linkend="defSymbolicId"/>.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>size [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      A <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object that specifies the size of the image.
    </para>
    <para>
      If this argument is omitted, a size of 0 is used. Under most circumstances this indicates that the actual size of
      the icon should be used.  However, if LR_DEFAULTSIZE is used as one of the flags in the <emphasis
      role="italic">opts</emphasis> argument, then the width and height specified by the system metric values for icons
      is used.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>opts [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      A whole number that specifies the flags that control how the operating system loads the icon. The flags are one or
      more of the following symbols. You can use the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct
      numeric value for any of the following symbols. The <xref linkend="mthOrClsDlgUtil"/> method of the
<xref linkend="clsDlgUtil"/> class can be used to combine more than one of the symbols if needed.
      <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
      <member>LR_DEFAULTCOLOR</member>    <member>LR_CREATEDIBSECTION</member>
      <member>LR_DEFAULTSIZE</member>     <member>LR_LOADFROMFILE</member>
      <member>LR_LOADMAP3DCOLORS</member> <member>LR_LOADTRANSPARENT</member>
      <member>LR_MONOCHROME</member>      <member>LR_SHARED</member>
      <member>LR_VGACOLOR</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The default value is LR_LOADFROMFILE. The flags for this method, must include LR_LOADFROMFILE and can not contain
      LR_SHARED. If this argument is specified by the programmer, the value is checked, and corrected if necessary. See
      the remarks section for some additional comments.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    An image object, which may be a <xref linkend="mthIsNullClsImage"/> image on error.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    For most usage, the Rexx programmer would do one of the following things:
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Omit the <emphasis role="italic">size</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">flags</emphasis> arguments. This
      would load the icon using the actual size of the icon. If multiple icon images are included in the file, then the
      first image found would be used.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Omit the <emphasis role="italic">size</emphasis> and include the LR_DEFAULTSIZE flag in the <emphasis
      role="italic">flags</emphasis>. This would load the using the system metric values for icons.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Specify the size for the loaded image and omit the <emphasis role="italic">flags</emphasis> argument.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    This method uses the LoadImage() Windows API to actually load the icon image. For more advanced uses of this method,
    consult the MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected. This includes an invalid symbolic ID.
  </para>
  <para>
    Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example adds an icon resource to the dialog through the
 <xref linkend="mthAddIconResource"/> method and then uses that icon for the image in a
 <xref linkend="clsStatic"/> image control.
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  dlg = .SimpleDialog~new("Simple.rc", IDD_DIALOG1, , 'Simple.h')
  if dlg~initCode = 0 then do
    dlg~addIconResource(IDI_ENHANCED_QUESTION_MARK, 'fancyQuestion.ico')
    dlg~execute("SHOWTOP", IDI_CORPORATE_IMAGE)
  end

::method initDialog
  expose iconControl

  iconControl = self~newStatic(IDC_ICON_QUESTION)
  if iconControl <> .nil then do
    questionMark = .Image~userIcon(self, IDI_ENHANCED_QUESTION_MARK, .Size~new(64, 64) )
    if \ questionMark~isNull then iconControl~setIcon(questionMark)
  end

  self~connectButtonEvent(IDC_PB_YES, "CLICKED", onYes)
  self~connectButtonEvent(IDC_PB_NO, "CLICKED", onNo)

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::userIcon() [class method] -->


<section id="mthHandleClsImage" xreflabel="handle"><title>handle</title>
<indexterm><primary>handle</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--handle---------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns the Windows system handle to the image this object represents.  It is an error to invoke this
  method if the image is null, or after the image has been released.
</para>
<para>
   Currently, the handle is only useful for display.  In the ooDialog framework, methods that use images
   for arguments, use the .Image object, not the image handle.  Older methods that use a bitmap handle
   for a argument will not work with this handle.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The method does not have an argument.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return is the handle to the image.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
    hIcon = .Image~getImage(.Image~toID(IDI_QUESTION), .Image~toID(IMAGE_ICON))
    say 'hIcon:  ' hIcon
    say ' handle:' hIcon~handle

    /* Output to the console might be (on a 64-bit Windows system)

       hIcon:  an Image
       handle: 0x000000000001002B
    */
    ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::handle() -->


<section id="mthReleaseClsImage" xreflabel="release"><title>release</title>
<indexterm><primary>release</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--release--------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Releases the image.  This will free up operating system resources used for the image.  See the
  introduction to the <link linkend="paraClsImageRelease">Image</link> class for some discussion on releasing an image.
</para>
<para>
  Once an image object has been released, it is an error to use the object.  However, the
<xref linkend="mthIsNullClsImage"/> and
<xref linkend="mthSystemErrorCodeClsImage"/> methods can always be used.  The isNull()
  method will return <computeroutput>.true</computeroutput> after an image object has been released.
  Shared images should not be released, the operating system manages them.  To prevent the programmer
  from accidentally releasing a shared image, the .Image object tracks which images are loaded as shared
  and does not release a shared image if the programmer requests it.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The possible return values are:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>0</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            No error detected.
          </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>non-zero</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The operating system error code.
          </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      In this example, when the user presses the Test button, the current image for the static control is
      replaced by the system question mark image. The old image is no longer needed and it is released.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method onTest

        iconControl = self~newStatic(IDC_ICON_QUESTION)
        if iconControl <> .nil then do
          hQuestion = .Image~getImage(.Image~toID(IDI_QUESTION), .Image~toID(IMAGE_ICON))
          say 'Question icon:' hQuestion~handle
          if hQuestion~isNull then do
            say 'errror code:' .systemErrorCode
          end
          else do
            image = iconControl~setImage(hQuestion)
            say 'Swapped images:'
            say '  new icon:' hQuestion~handle
            say '  old icon:' image~handle

            -- The old image is no longer needed.
            ret = image~release
            say 'Released old image return:' ret '.SystemErrorCode:' .systemErrorCode
          end
        end

        /* Output on the screen, on a 64-bit system, might be:

         Question icon: 0x000000000001002B
         Swapped images:
           new icon: 0x000000000001002B
           old icon: 0x0000000001120639
         Released old image return: 0 .SystemErrorCode: 0

        */
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::release() -->


<section id="mthIsNullClsImage" xreflabel="isNull"><title>isNull</title>
<indexterm><primary>isNull</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--isNull---------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  The isNull() method tests if the image object is valid.  The image will be null if an error occurred
  when it was loaded, or if the image has been released.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The method returns <computeroutput>.true</computeroutput> if the image is not valid, is null, and
      <computeroutput>.false</computeroutput> if the image is not null.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      In this example the programmer wanted to load the system question mark icon, but used the wrong
      image type.  (He uses IMAGE_BITMAP instead of IMAGE_ICON.)  The system will refuse to load the
      image.  To test if the image was loaded okay, use the isNull() method.  Note that the getImage()
      method set the .SystemErrorCode.  As in all software, the error codes are not always that
      informative.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      hQuestion = .Image~getImage(.Image~toID(IDI_QUESTION), .Image~toID(IMAGE_BITMAP))
      if hQuestion~isNull then do
        say 'System Errror code:' .systemErrorCode
        say '  System message:  ' SysGetErrorText(.systemErrorCode)
      end

      /* Output would be:

      System Errror code: 1814
        System message:   The specified resource name cannot be found in the image file.

      */
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::isNull() -->


<section id="mthSystemErrorCodeClsImage" xreflabel="systemErrorCode"><title>systemErrorCode</title>
<indexterm><primary>systemErrorCode</primary>
<secondary>Image class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--systemErrorCode------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  The systemErrorCode attribute of the image object will reflect any system error codes that are detected
  while working with an image object.  This is the same error code as the
  <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/> is set to.  This can be useful if the programmer
  wants to check for an error code at some point when it is possible that .systemErrorCode has been
  reset.  (See the example below.)
</para>
<para>
   Like the <xref linkend="mthIsNullClsImage"/> method this method can be invoked even when
   the image is not valid.  However, it should not be used to check if the image is valid because it is
   possible for the value to be 0 and the image to be null.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments to this method
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The value is usually 0, but may be a system error code if one was detected.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      In this example the system error code attribute for an image is checked at a point in the
      life-cycle of the application when checking the <computeroutput>.systemErrorCode</computeroutput>
      would be meaningless:
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method onYes
        expose hIcon

        -- Need to release the icon image, but it is not always valid.
        if \ hIcon~isNull then hIcon~release
        else do
          say 'The icon image is not valid.'
          say '  Error when it was loaded:' hIcon~systemErrorCode
          say '  System message:          ' SysGetErrorText(hIcon~systemErrorCode)
        end
        return self~ok:super

      /* Output might be:

      The icon image is not valid.
        Error when it was loaded: 2
        System message:           The system cannot find the file specified.

      */

      /* Note that the below was the error that caused the above.  The file name
       * is actually 'shaveIce.ico' not shavedIce.ico.
       */

        if iconControl <> .nil then do
          hIcon = .Image~getImage("shavedIce.ico", .Image~toID(IMAGE_ICON))
          ...
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Image::systemErrorCode() -->

</section>  <!--   End Image class -->

<section id="clsImageList" xreflabel="ImageList"><title>ImageList Class</title>
<indexterm><primary>ImageList class</primary></indexterm>
<para>
  An image list is a object used to efficiently manage large sets of images.  Either icons or bitmaps.
  In an image list, all images are the same size and are accessed by a zero-based index. The images are
  in screen device format. Optionally, each image in the list can have a matching monochrome bitmap that
  is used as a mask to draw the image transparently.
</para>
<para>
  The .ImageList object acts as an interface to the underlying operating system Image List, which
  Microsoft calls a control. Although Microsoft calls the Image List a control and  documents it with the
  other dialog controls, it is not a control in the same sense as button, edit, or list-view controls. It
  is not a window, all dialog controls are windows.  It does not send or receive window messages. Use the
  MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation to get more information on exactly how
  Image Lists work.
</para>
<para>
  When an image list is no longer needed, it can be released.  This frees up the system resources used
  for the images and the image list.  The programmer releases an image list by using the
<xref linkend="mthReleaseClsImageList"/> method.  Once an image list is released it can no
  longer be used.  It is an error to invoke any method on the released object, except for the
<xref linkend="mthIsNullClsImageList"/> method.  The isNull() method can be invoked any time to
  test if an image list is valid or not. It should go without saying that a programmer should not release
  an image list that is in use.
</para>
<para>
  Future versions of the .ImageList are intended to provide a complete interface to the underlying Image
  List control.  At this time not all functionality is implemented.
</para>

<section id="sctMethodsImageListClass"><title>Method Table</title>

<para>
  Instances of the ImageList class implement the methods listed in the following table:
</para>

<table id="tblImageListMethods" frame="all">
<title>Image Instance Methods</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colwidth="1*" /><colspec colwidth="4*" />
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Method</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Class Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthCreateClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Creates a new empty image list of the type specified.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthNewClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Currently it is not intended for the ooDialog programmer to instantiate an image list object directly using the new method.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Instance Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthAddClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Adds one or more bitmap images to the image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthAddIcon"/></entry>
<entry>Adds an icon or cursor image to the image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthAddImagesClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Adds a number of images to the image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthAddMaskedClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Adds one or more bitmap images, along with a mask to the image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthDuplicateClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Creates a duplicate image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetCountClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Determines the number of images in the image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetIconClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Creates and returns an icon image from an image and mask in this image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetImageSizeClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Determines the size of the images in the image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthHandleClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Returns the Windows system handle to the image list this object represents.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthIsNullClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Used to check if an image list is valid.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthRemoveClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Removes the image at the specified index from the image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthRemoveAllClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Removes all images from the image list.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthReleaseClsImageList"/></entry>
<entry>Releases the resource module so that the operating system can reclaim the system resources used by the image list.</entry>
</row>
</tbody></tgroup>
</table>

</section>

<section id="mthCreateClsImageList" xreflabel="create"><title>create (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>create</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--create(--+--------+-+---------+-+---------+-+--------+--)---><
             +--size--+ +-,-flags-+ +-,-count-+ +-,-grow-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Creates a new empty image list of the type specified.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>The arguments are:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>size [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object that specifies the size of a single image in the
          image list.  All images in an image list have the same size. The size is specified in pixels.
        </para>
        <para>
          If this argument is omitted the system default size for an icon is used.  This size can vary
          depending on which version of Windows is running and whether the user has selected to use large
          icons or not.  A typical size is 32 x 32 (in pixels.)
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>flags [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The flags that specify the type of image list to create. The flags are one or more of the following
          symbols, but can include only one ILC_COLOR* value. You can use
          the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric value for any of the
          following symbols.  The <xref linkend="mthOrClsDlgUtil"/> method of the
<xref linkend="clsDlgUtil"/> class can be used to combine the symbols.
        </para>
        <para>
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>ILC_MASK</member>     <member>ILC_COLOR24</member>
          <member>ILC_COLOR</member>    <member>ILC_COLOR32</member>
          <member>ILC_COLORDDB</member> <member>ILC_PALETTE</member>
          <member>ILC_COLOR4</member>   <member>ILC_MIRROR</member>
          <member>ILC_COLOR8</member>   <member>ILC_PERITEMMIRROR</member>
          <member>ILC_COLOR16</member>
          </simplelist>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_MASK</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              The image list contains two bitmaps, one of which is used as a mask. The mask is a monochrome bitmap. If
              this value is omitted, the image list contains only one bitmap.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_COLOR</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              Indicates to use the default image list type when none of the other ILC_COLOR* flags are used. Usually the
              default is ILC_COLOR4. However, with older display drivers the default may be ILC_COLORDDB.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_COLORDDB</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              The image list uses a device-dependent bitmap.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_COLOR4</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              The image list uses a 4-bit, 16-color, device-independent bitmap, DIB, section for the bitmap
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_COLOR8</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              The image list uses an 8-bit DIB section. The color table use the same colors as the halftone palette.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_COLOR16</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              Use a 16-bit (32/64k-color) DIB section.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_COLOR24</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              Use a 24-bit DIB section.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_COLOR32</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              Use a 32-bit DIB section.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_PALETTE</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              Microsoft has this flag but it is not implemented. ooDialog accepts the flag in case it is implemented in
              future versions of Windows.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_MIRROR</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              Languages such as Hebrew or Arabic that read right-to-left can be mirrored by Windows. When an image list
              is created on a mirrored version of Windows, the images are mirrored. I.e.,, they are flipped to display
              from right to left. This flag on mirrored versions of Windows instructs to OS to not automatically mirror
              the images.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>ILC_PERITEMMIRROR</term>
            <listitem>
            <para>
              This flag is ignored unless ILC_MIRROR is also used. It should be used when the image list contains a
              strip of images.
            </para>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>count [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The initial size for the image list. The size is the number of images the image list contains. When this
          argument is omitted the default is 6.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>grow [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The amount by which the image list can grow if the operating system needs to resize the image list to make
          room for more images. The default value when omitted is 0.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      A new, empty, image list is returned.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> It is theoretical possible for this method to fail and the returned image
      list to be null. However, in practice, it is virtually impossible to cause a failure.  Using a size of 0 x 0 seems
      about the only way.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_Create()</computeroutput> API. Use the
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation to get more information on the arguments to
      this method.
    </para>
    <para>
      The ILC_MIRROR and ILC_PERITEMMIRROR flags require
      Common Control <xref linkend="ovvComctl32"/> version 6.0 or later. If necessary use the
 <xref linkend="mthComCtl32Version"/>() method to determine the current version of
      the library.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <programlisting>
  <![CDATA[
  -- We set the flags to create a 24 bit color, masked image list.
  flags = .DlgUtil~or(.Image~toID(ILC_COLOR24), .Image~toID(ILC_MASK))

  -- Create an empty .ImageList object:
  imageList = .ImageList~create(.Size~new(61, 46), flags, 10, 10);
  ]]>
  </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::create() [class method] -->


<section id="mthNewClsImageList" xreflabel="new"><title>new (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>new</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
  Currently it is not intended for the ooDialog programmer to instantiate an image list object directly
  using the new method.  This may change in the future and will be documented at that time, if the
  intention changes.  .ImageList objects are instantiated using the
<xref linkend="mthCreateClsImageList"/> method.
</para>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::new() [class method] -->

<section id="mthAddClsImageList" xreflabel="add"><title>add</title>
<indexterm><primary>add</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--add(--image-+---------+--)-------------------><
                +-,-mask--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Adds a bitmap image or images to the image list.  The number of images is inferred from the width of
  the added bitmap.  Optionally adds the mask for the bitmap(s).  If the image list does not use a mask,
  the mask argument is ignored, even if it is present.
</para>
<para>
  Internally the image list makes a copy of the bitmap.  After the method returns, the original image can
  be released if it is not needed anymore.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>The arguments are:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>image</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The .Image object that represents the image to add.  This must be a bitmap image.  The width of
          the image determines the number of images added.  (Remember all images in a image list are the
          same size.)
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>mask</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The mask(s) to use with the image(s).  This must be a bitmap image.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      On success, the index of the first image added is returned, otherwise -1 is returned.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected or if the image list is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_Add()</computeroutput> API. The
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation can provide more information on this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example sets the image list for a list-view control.  The images are loaded from psdemolv.bmp
      which is a bitmap 16 pixels high by 64 pixels wide, containing 4 individual images.  Since the
      image list is created with a size of 16 x 16, when the add() method is used, the image list infers
      that the bitmap is 4 images.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      -- Set the images for the items in the list-view.
      image = .Image~getImage("bmp\psdemolv.bmp")
      imageList = .ImageList~create(.Size~new(16, 16), .Image~toID(ILC_COLOR8), 4, 0)
      if \image~isNull,  \imageList~isNull then do
         imageList~add(image)
         lc~setImageList(imageList, .Image~toID(LVSIL_SMALL))

         -- The image list makes a copy of the bitmap, so we can release it now.
         image~release
      end
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::add() -->


<section id="mthAddIcon" xreflabel="addIcon"><title>addIcon</title>
<indexterm><primary>addIcon</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--addIcon(--image--)---------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Adds an icon or cursor image to the image list.  If the image list is masked, then both the image and
  mask bitmaps of the icon or cursor are  copied. If it is not masked, then only the image bitmap is
  copied.
</para>
<para>
  Internally the image list makes a copy of the bitmap.  After the method returns, the original image can
  be released if it is not needed anymore.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>The only argument is:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>image</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The .Image object that represents the image to add.  This must be an icon or cursor image.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This method returns the index of the added icon or cursor on success, otherwise -1 is returned.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected or if the image list is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_AddIcon()</computeroutput> API. The
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation can provide more information on this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Here the system icon images are loaded and then displayed in a list-view. Each icon will show in
      the list-view with the text for the icon being its numeric resource ID. Since the system icons are
      shared, the icon images are not released after they are added to the image list.

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
  ids = .array~new()
  ids[ 1] = .Image~toID(IDI_APPLICATION)
  ids[ 2] = .Image~toID(IDI_HAND)
  ids[ 3] = .Image~toID(IDI_QUESTION)
  ids[ 4] = .Image~toID(IDI_EXCLAMATION)
  ids[ 5] = .Image~toID(IDI_ASTERISK)
  ids[ 6] = .Image~toID(IDI_WINLOGO)

  flags = .DlgUtil~or(.Image~toID(ILC_COLOR8), .Image~toID(ILC_MASK))

  imageList = .ImageList~create(.Size~new(32, 32), flags, 20, 10)

  do i = 1 to ids~items
    image = .Image~getImage(ids[i], .Image~toID(IMAGE_ICON))
    imageList~addIcon(image)
  end

  list~setImageList(imageList, .Image~toID(LVSIL_NORMAL))

  do i = 1 to ids~items
    list~add(ids[i], i - 1)
  end

]]>
</programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::addIcon() -->


<section id="mthAddImagesClsImageList" xreflabel="addImages"><title>addImages</title>
<indexterm><primary>addImages</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--addImages(--images--+---------+--)-----------><
                        +-,-cRef--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Adds a number of images to the image list.  The images are supplied in a non-sparse array and must all
  be of the same type.
</para>
<para>
  The images are added to the image list in the same order as they exist in the array.  If an error
  occurs in the middle of processing the images, the method returns at that point.  This means that
  images prior to the error will exist in the image list, but no images in the array after the error will
  be placed in the image list.  Which images were placed in the image list can be determined by the
  return value of this method.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected or if the image list is null.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>The arguments are:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>images</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          An array of non-null .Image objects.  The array must not be sparse, that is each index in the
          array must contain an .Image object.  The images can be bitmaps, icons, or cursors, but each
          image in the array must be the same type. (Remember that cursors are icons, so that the array
          can contain a mixture of icons and cursors.) Bitmaps can not be mixed with icons or cursors.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>cRef</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A <xref linkend="mthColorRef"/> that is used to generate the mask if the image
          list is a masked image list.  See the
<xref linkend="mthAddMaskedClsImageList"/> method for more details on this argument.
          This argument is ignored if the images are not bitmaps, or if the image list is not masked.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This method returns the image list index of the last successfully added image, or -1 if no images
      were added.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example creates an image list from a number icons and then displays them in a list-view
      control in a dialog.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      list  = self~newListView(IDC_LV_IMAGES)

      files1 = .array~new()
      files1[ 1] = "Bee.ico"
      files1[ 2] = "Camera.ico"
      files1[ 3] = "Camera1.ico"
      files1[ 4] = "Default.ico"
      files1[ 5] = "Disabled.ico"
      files1[ 6] = "Hot.ico"
      files1[ 7] = "Lamp.ico"
      files1[ 8] = "Mountain.ico"
      files1[ 9] = "Normal.ico"
      files1[10] = "Penguin.ico"
      files1[11] = "Picture.ico"
      files1[12] = "Pushed.ico"
      files1[13] = "Question32.ico"
      files1[14] = "Search32.ico"
      files1[15] = "Skull.ico"
      files1[16] = "Stolen.ico"
      files1[17] = "Window.ico"

      size = .Size~new(32, 32)

      images = .Image~fromFiles(files1, .Image~toID(IMAGE_ICON), size)
      if images~items <> files1~items then do
        say 'Error loading images.'
        say '  System error:' .systemErrorCode
        say '  Message:     ' SysGetErrorText(.systemErrorCode)
        return
      end

      count = images~items
      flags = .DlgUtil~or(.Image~toID(ILC_COLOR24), .Image~toID(ILC_MASK))

      imageList = .ImageList~create(size, flags, 20, 10);

      lastAdded = imageList~addImages(images)
      if lastAdded <> (count - 1) then do
        -- Not all images were added.  We just ignore this and display
        -- in the list-view what was added.
      end

      -- Set the image list for the list-view's normal icons.
      list~setImageList(imageList, .Image~toID(LVSIL_NORMAL))

      -- Add an item to the list-view for each image.  The
      -- text for each item will be the icon file name and
      -- the icon will be the image we loaded.
      do i = 0 to lastAdded
        list~add(files1[i + 1], i)
      end
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::addImages() -->


<section id="mthAddMaskedClsImageList" xreflabel="addMasked"><title>addMasked</title>
<indexterm><primary>addMasked</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--addMasked(--image-,-cRef--)------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Adds a bitmap image, or images, to the image list.  The COLORREF cRef is used to generate the mask.
</para>
<para>
  Internally the image list makes a copy of the bitmap.  After the method returns, the original image can
  be released if it is not needed anymore.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>The arguments are:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>image</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The .Image object that represents the image to add.  This must be a bitmap image.  The width of
          the image determines the number of images added.  (Remember all images in a image list are the
          same size.)
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>cRef</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <xref linkend="mthColorRef"/> to use to generate the mask. In the added image,
          each pixel that matches this color is changed to black, and the corresponding bit in the mask
          is set to 1.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      On success, the index of the first added image is returned, otherwise -1 is returned.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected or if the image list is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_AddMasked()</computeroutput> API. The
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation can provide more information on this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example comes from a dialog with a Tab control.  An image list is used to set an icon for each
      tab.  Each icon is a colored letter on a white background.  Using a white color to generate the
      mask causes the image to be drawn transparently.  The colored letter itself shows, and the rest of
      the image lets the underlying color show through.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      -- Add all the tabs, including the index into the image list for an icon for
      -- each tab.
      tc~addFullSeq("Red", 0, ,"Green", 1, , "Moss", 2, , "Blue", 3, ,   -
                    "Purple", 4, ,  "Cyan", 5, , "Gray", 6)

      -- Create a COLORREF (pure white) and load our bitmap.
      cRef = .Image~colorRef(255, 255, 255)
      image = .Image~getImage("bmp\psdemoTab.bmp")

      -- Create our image list, as a masked image list.
      imageList = .ImageList~create(.Size~new(16, 16),                   -
                                    .DlgUtil~or(.Image~toID(ILC_COLOR24),  -
                                    .Image~toID(ILC_MASK)),                -
                                     10, 0)

      if \image~isNull,  \imageList~isNull then do
         imageList~addMasked(image, cRef)
         tc~setImageList(imageList)

         image~release
      end

      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::addMasked() -->


<section id="mthDuplicateClsImageList" xreflabel="duplicate"><title>duplicate</title>
<indexterm><primary>duplicate</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--duplicate------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Creates a duplicate image list.  All information in the original image list is copied to the new image
  list.  (Overlay images are not copied, but ooDialog does not have support for image list overlay images
  at this time.)  The two image lists are independent.  Adding, or removing, images from one image list
  has no effect on the other.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return is a copy of the image list.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises a syntax error if the image list is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_Duplicate()</computeroutput> API. The
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation can provide more information on this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This fictious example is from a point-of-sale application for a restaurant.  The customer is
      presented with a list-view of menu items, each list-view item has a colorful icon depicting the
      selection.  The customers place their orders through the application and wait-people then bring
      them their meal when it is ready.  The dinner menu has all the items that the lunch menu does, plus
      some more.  The customer can choose whether to order from the lunch menu or the dinner menu, so the
      lunch menu image list has to remain unchanged.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method getDinnerImageList private
        use strict arg lunchImageList

        dinnerList = lunchImageList~duplicate
        fileArray = self~getDinnerImageFiles
        dinnerList~addImages(fileArray)

      return dinnerList
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::duplicate() -->


<section id="mthGetCountClsImageList" xreflabel="getCount"><title>getCount</title>
<indexterm><primary>getCount</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getCount-------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Determines the number of images in the image list.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Returns the number of images currently in the image list.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises a syntax error if the image list is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_ImageCount()</computeroutput> API. The
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation can provide more information on this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
    ::method displayImageListCount private
      use strict arg imageList
      say 'Image list:' imageList~handle 'has' imagelist~getCount 'images.'

      /*
        Possible output on a Windows 64-bit system:

        Image list: 0x00000000000ED420 has 17 images.
      */
    ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::getCount() -->


<section id="mthGetIconClsImageList" xreflabel="getIcon"><title>getIcon</title>
<indexterm><primary>getIcon</primary><secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ImageList class</primary><secondary>getIcon</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getIcon(--index--+--------------+--+-----------+--)------------------------><
                     +-,-drawStyle--+  +-,-ovrLay--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Creates and returns an icon image from an image and mask in this image list.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term>index [required]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      The one-based index of the image in this list.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>drawStyle [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      A list of 0 or more of the following keywords separated by spaces. These keywords specify the drawing style that the
      returned icon is created with. Case is not significant. The default if this argument is omitted is NORMAL. Note that
      several of the keywords have the exact same meaning. This is intentional on Microsoft's part:
    </para>
    <para>
      <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
        <member>BLEND       </member>
        <member>BLEND25     </member>
        <member>BLEND50     </member>
        <member>FOCUS       </member>
        <member>MASK        </member>
        <member>NORMAL      </member>
        <member>SELECTED    </member>
        <member>TRANSPARENT </member>
      </simplelist>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>BLEND</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Draws the image, blending 50 percent with the system highlight color. This value has no effect if the image list
          does not contain a mask.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>BLEND25</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Draws the image, blending 25 percent with the system highlight color. This value has no effect if the image list
          does not contain a mask.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>BLEND50</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Draws the image, blending 50 percent with the system highlight color. This value has no effect if the image list
          does not contain a mask.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>FOCUS</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Draws the image, blending 25 percent with the system highlight color. This value has no effect if the image list
          does not contain a mask.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>MASK</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Draws the mask.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>NORMAL</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Draws the image using the background color for the image list. If the background color is the CLR_NONE value, the
          image is drawn transparently using the mask.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>SELECTED</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Draws the image, blending 50 percent with the system highlight color. This value has no effect if the image list
          does not contain a mask.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>TRANSPARENT</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Draws the image transparently using the mask, regardless of the background color. This value has no effect if the
          image list does not contain a mask.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>ovrLay [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      The one-based index of the overlay image in this list. See the remarks section.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a valid icon <xref linkend="clsImage"/>, or the <computeroutput>.nil</computeroutput> object on error.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The overlay image is drawn transparently over the primary image, that is the icon, returned from this method. The
    overlay image must be added to the image list separately. ooDialog has not yet implemented a method for adding overlay
    images to the image list. That is intended for a future enhancement. Therefore, at this time, the <emphasis
    role="italic">ovrlay</emphasis> argument has no meaning.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  <para>
    Sets the <link linkend="dotSystemErrorCode">.SystemErrorCode</link> variable.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example comes from an application that uses a resource only DLL. The DLL contains the dialog template for the
    application and a bitmap of images. The bitmap contains a series of 20 images side by side. Each image is 16 by 16
    pixels. The bitmap is used to create an image list, then an icon can be retrieved from the image list for any of the
    images in the bitmap file using the <emphasis role="italic">getIcon</emphasis> method and the index of the image in the
    bitmap:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
  ri = .ResourceImage~new(self)
  imageBMP = ri~getImage(IDI_ICONS_IL)

  imageList = .ImageList~create(.Size~new(16, 16), 'COLOR32', 20, 0)
  imageList~add(imageBMP)
  imageBMP~release

  icon = imageList~getIcon(1)
  statusBar~setIcon(icon, 1)
]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::getIcon() -->


<section id="mthGetImageSizeClsImageList" xreflabel="getImageSize"><title>getImageSize</title>
<indexterm><primary>getImageSize</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getImageSize---------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Determines the size of the images in the image list.  All images in any single image list have the same
  size.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>There are no arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The size of the images in the image list is returned in a <xref linkend="clsSize"/>
      object.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises a syntax error if the image list is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_IconSize()</computeroutput> API. The
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation can provide more information on this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
    ::method displayImageListSize private
      use strict arg imageList
      s = imageList~getImageSize
      h = s~height 'pixels high'
      w = s~width 'pixels wide'
      say 'Image list:' imageList~handle 'contains images' h 'by' w

      /*
        Possible output on a Windows 64-bit system:

        Image list: 0x00000000000DCB20 contains images 32 pixels high by 32 pixels wide
      */

    ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::getImageSize() -->


<section id="mthHandleClsImageList" xreflabel="handle"><title>handle</title>
<indexterm><primary>handle</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--handle---------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns the Windows system handle to the image list this object represents.  It is an error to invoke
  this method if the image list is null, or after the image has been released.
</para>
<para>
   At this time, the handle is only useful for display.  In the ooDialog framework, methods that use
   image lists for arguments, use the .ImageList object, not the image list handle.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There is no argument to this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return is the image list handle.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
    ::method displayImageList private
      use strict arg imageList
      say 'Currently using this image list:' imageList~handle

      /*
        Possible output on a Windows 64-bit system:

        Currently using this image list: 0x00000000000DCB20
      */
    ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::handle() -->


<section id="mthIsNullClsImageList" xreflabel="isNull"><title>isNull</title>
<indexterm><primary>isNull</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--isNull---------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Used to check if an image list is valid. This method can be invoked on any image list, even after it
  has been released.  An image list will always be null after it has been released.  It is conceivable
  that, if an error occurs during an image list creation, the returned image list might be null.
  However, this is extremely unlikely.  Therefore, for all practical purposes, an image list will only be
  null after it has been released.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments to this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This method returns true if the image list is null, otherwise false.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example comes from some test code.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      -- See if we can create an image list with no size.
      imageList = .ImageList~create(.Size~new(0, 0), .Image~toID(ILC_COLOR24),  20, 10)
      if imageList~isNull then do
        say 'Can not create a 0 x 0 image list.'
        return .false
      end

      return .true

      /*
        Output will be:

        Can not create a 0 x 0 image list.

      */
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::isNull() -->


<section id="mthReleaseClsImageList" xreflabel="release"><title>release</title>
<indexterm><primary>release</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--release--------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Releases the image list allowing the operating system to reclaim the resources used by the image list.
  Once the image list has been released, it can no longer be used.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments to this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This method always returns 0.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example comes from a program that runs continuously.  During the life-cycle of the application
      it displays and then closes a dialog that creates some image lists.  The image lists are always
      different depending on the state of things.  Each time the dialog closes, it releases the image
      lists it created to free up the operating system resources.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method ok
        self~cleanUp
        return self~ok:super

      ::method cancel
        self~cleanUp
        return self~cancel:super

      ::method cleanUp private
        expose coolTempImages warningImages buildingStatusImages

        if coolTempImages \== .nil then coolTempImages~release
        if warningImages \== .nil then warningImages~release
        if buildingStatusImages \== .nil then buildingStatusImages~release

      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::release() -->


<section id="mthRemoveClsImageList" xreflabel="remove"><title>remove</title>
<indexterm><primary>remove</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--remove(--index--)----------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Removes the image at <emphasis role="italic">index</emphasis> from the image list.  When the image is
  removed, all the indexes in the list are adjusted.  I.e., if the image at index 2 is removed, the image
  at index 3 becomes index 2, the image at index 4 becomes index 3, etc..
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>The single argument is:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>index</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The one-based index of the image to remove.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This method returns true on success, otherwise false.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected or if the image list is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_Remove()</computeroutput> API. The
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation can provide more information on this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example comes from the fictious point-of-sale application for a restaurant.  Sometimes the
      chef runs out of a menu item and the item is then removed from the list-view so that the customers
      can no longer order it.  (Rigorous error checking is not done because the application was written
      by one of the waiters.)
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method removeFromMenu private
        use strict arg index

        menu = self~newListView(IDC_LV_MENU)

        bigIcons = menu~getImageList(.Image~toID(LVSIL_NORMAL))
        bigIcons~remove(index)

        smallIcons = menu~getImageList(.Image~toID(LVSIL_SMALL))
        smallIcons~remove(index)

        stateIcons = menu~getImageList(.Image~toID(LVSIL_STATE))
        stateIcons~remove(index)

        menu~delete(index)

      return 0
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::remove() -->


<section id="mthRemoveAllClsImageList" xreflabel="removeAll"><title>removeAll</title>
<indexterm><primary>removeAll</primary>
<secondary>ImageList class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--removeAll------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Removes all images from the image list.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments to this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The method returns true on success, false otherwise.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises a syntax error if the image list is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the <computeroutput>ImageList_RemoveAll()</computeroutput> API. The
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation can provide more information on this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example is a continuation of the fictious restaurant point-of-sale application.  The waiter
      that wrote the application did not like to work past the normal closing time.  The application has
      a feature that removes all the menu items as it gets near closing time to prevent customers from
      ordering something they do not have time to finish eating.  (However, the waiter noticed that he
      often got huge tips from customers that had drinks after their meal.)
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method stopOrders private

        menu = self~newListView(IDC_LV_MENU)

        bigIcons = menu~getImageList(.Image~toID(LVSIL_NORMAL))
        bigIcons~removeAll

        smallIcons = menu~getImageList(.Image~toID(LVSIL_SMALL))
        smallIcons~removeAll

        stateIcons = menu~getImageList(.Image~toID(LVSIL_STATE))
        stateIcons~removeAll

        menu~deleteAll

        self~addAfterDinnerDrinks(menu)

      return 0

      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ImageList::removeAll() -->


</section>  <!--   End ImageList class -->


<section id="clsResourceImage" xreflabel="ResourceImage"><title>ResourceImage Class</title>
<indexterm><primary>ResourceImage class</primary></indexterm>
<para>
  Resource Images represent modules that contain resources.  These modules are binary executable files,
  which on Windows are for all practical purposes .exe and .dll files. Before an application can use a
  resource in a module, the resource must be loaded from the module into memory. Once in memory, the
  application needs a handle to the specific resource in order to work with it.
</para>
<para>
  The ResourceImage class contains methods and function to assist in the loading of resources into memory
  and obtaining handles to the desired resources.  ooDialog has always had, limited, access to resources
  in modules through the <xref linkend="clsResDialog"/> class.  The ResourceImage class
  expands that access, both improving it and making the access available in any ooDialog program, with or
  without ResDialog objects. The class supports the loading of, and obtaining handles to, resources from
  any binary executable file.
</para>
<para>
  The class provides the <xref linkend="mthReleaseClsResourceImage"/> method to free up
  system resources if a module containing the resources is no longer needed.  The
  general <link linkend="paraClsImageRelease">remarks</link> concerning freeing the
  <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class are applicable here.  The release() method will ignore requests
  to release the module when it is known absolutely that the module should not be released, such as in
  the case the module is the <computeroutput>oodialog.dll</computeroutput>. In other cases only the
  programmer can know if the module should or shouldn't be released.  In those cases, the ResourceImage
  class will do as requested.  As with the images that the .Image class represents, the system resources
  used by the module the ResourceImage class represents will be automatically cleaned up when the
  interpreter process ends.  The <link linkend="paraClsImageRelease">comments</link> about why would a programmer want to
  release resources in the <computeroutput>Image</computeroutput> class remarks are equally apropos here.
</para>
<para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> The <computeroutput>ResourceImage</computeroutput> class is new in ooDialog as of
  ooRexx version 4.0.0. Its first implementation supports image resources and provides the basic framework upon which to
  expand in the future.
</para>

<section id="sctMethodsResourceImageClass"><title>Method Table</title>

<para>
  Instances of the ResourceImage class implement the methods listed in the following table:
</para>

<table id="tblResourceImageMethods" frame="all">
<title>ResourceImage Instance Methods</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Method</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Class Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthNewClsResourceImage"/></entry>
<entry>Instantiates a new resource image that represents the executable module specified by the <emphasis role="italic">fileOrDlg</emphasis> argument.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Instance Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetImageClsResourceImage"/></entry>
<entry>Loads the specified image resource in the module and returns a new <computeroutput>.Image</computeroutput> object.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetImagesClsResourceImage"/></entry>
<entry>Loads a number of image resources from the module.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthHandleClsResourceImage"/></entry>
<entry>Returns the Windows system handle for the resource module.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthIsNullClsResourceImage"/></entry>
<entry>Determines if the resource image is valid.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthReleaseClsResourceImage"/></entry>
<entry>Releases the resource module so that the operating system can reclaim the system resources.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSystemErrorCodeClsResourceImage"/></entry>
<entry>Reflects any system error codes that are detected while working with an image object.</entry>
</row>
</tbody></tgroup>
</table>

</section>


<section id="mthNewClsResourceImage" xreflabel="new"><title>new (Class method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>new</primary><secondary>ResourceImage class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--new(--fileOrDlg--)---------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Instantiates a new resource image that represents the executable module specified by <emphasis
  role="italic">fileOrDlg</emphasis>.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>The single arguments is:
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term>fileOrDlg [required]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      This argument must be either a string file name or a dialog object. If <emphasis role="italic">fileOrDlg</emphasis> is
      a string, it specifies the file name of an executable module containing resources that the ooDialog program
      wants to access. If it is a dialog object in the current program, then it specifies that the module containing the
      resources is one of the modules already available to the program.  That is, either the
      <computeroutput>oodialog.dll</computeroutput> module, or the module used for instantiating a <xref
      linkend="mthNewClsResDialog"/> <computeroutput>ResDialog</computeroutput> object.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the dialog object is a <xref linkend="clsResDialog"/> it specifies the module used to instantiate the dialog object.
      If the dialog object is not a <emphasis role="italic">ResDialog</emphasis> then it specifies the oodialog.dll module,
      which is always loaded in any ooDialog program.
    </para>
    <para>
      If <emphasis role="italic">fileOrDlg</emphasis> is a string file name, then the file name alone is sufficient. The
      operating system will search the path for the file as it normally does when a program is executed.  If the module is
      not in the path then a full, or relative, file name is required.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a new <emphasis role="italic">ResourceImage</emphasis> object. This object may be null if an error occurred.  Use
    the <xref linkend="mthIsNullClsResourceImage"/> method to check for this.  Both the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>
    or the <xref linkend="mthSystemErrorCodeClsResourceImage"/> method should contain an error code if the object is null.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example instantiates a resource image using the oodialog.dll module and uses it to load
    the generally available icon resources from that module.  The icons are then displayed in a
    list-view control.
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
::method initDialog
  expose list

  list  = self~newListView(IDC_LV_IMAGES)

  ids = .array~new()
  ids[1] = self~constDir[IDI_DLG_OODIALOG]
  ids[2] = self~constDir[IDI_DLG_APPICON]
  ids[3] = self~constDir[IDI_DLG_APPICON2]
  ids[4] = self~constDir[IDI_DLG_OOREXX]

  size = .Size~new(.SM~cxIcon, .SM~cyIcon)

  oodModule = .ResourceImage~new(self)
  icons = oodModule~getImages(ids, 'ICON', size)

  imageList = .ImageList~create(size, 'COLOR24 MASK', 4, 0)
  imageList~addImages(icons)

  list~setImageList(imageList, 'NORMAL'

  names = .array~new()
  names[1] = "IDI_DLG_OODIALOG"
  names[2] = "IDI_DLG_APPICON"
  names[3] = "IDI_DLG_APPICON2"
  names[4] = "IDI_DLG_OOREXX"

  do i = 1 to ids~items
    list~add(names[i] '('ids[i]')', i - 1)
  end

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End Resource::new() [class method] -->

<section id="mthGetImageClsResourceImage" xreflabel="getImage"><title>getImage</title>
<indexterm><primary>getImage</primary>
<secondary>ResourceImage class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getImage(--id--+--------+--+--------+--+---------+--)-------><
                   +-,-type-+  +-,-size-+  +-,-flags-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Loads the specified image resource in the module and returns a new
<xref linkend="clsImage"/> object.
</para>
<para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> <computeroutput>LoadImage()</computeroutput> is the underlying Windows API used
  here. This method is very similar to the <xref linkend="mthGetImageClsImage"/> method of the .Image
  class. The documentation for that method may provide additional insight.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>The arguments are:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>id</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The resource id of the image in the module.
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> At this time symbolic IDs are not supported for this argument.  That
            restriction may be lifted in a future version of ooDialog.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>type</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Specifies the type of the image: bitmap, icon, or cursor. You can use
          the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric value for one of the
          following symbols:
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>IMAGE_BITMAP</member> <member>IMAGE_ICON</member>
          <member>IMAGE_CURSOR</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The default is IMAGE_BITMAP
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>size</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object that specifies the size of the image.  The default
          is a size of 0x0.  Under most circumstances this indicates that the actual size of the image
          should be used.  However, the MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation for
          <computeroutput>LoadImage()</computeroutput> should be consulted for other meanings.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>flags</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The load resource flags for the LoadImage() API.  The flags are one or more of the following
          symbols. You can use the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric
          value for any of the following symbols.  The <xref linkend="mthOrClsDlgUtil"/> method of
          the <xref linkend="clsDlgUtil"/> class can be used to combine more than one of the
          symbols if needed.
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>LR_DEFAULTCOLOR</member>    <member>LR_CREATEDIBSECTION</member>
          <member>LR_DEFAULTSIZE</member>     <member>LR_LOADFROMFILE</member>
          <member>LR_LOADMAP3DCOLORS</member> <member>LR_LOADTRANSPARENT</member>
          <member>LR_MONOCHROME</member>      <member>LR_SHARED</member>
          <member>LR_VGACOLOR</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The default is LR_SHARED.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This method returns an .Image object that represents the specified image resource in the module.
      The image may be null if an error occurred, for instance if no image resource was found.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises a syntax error if the resource image is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the Win32 API: <computeroutput>LoadImage()</computeroutput>. Use the
      MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation to get more information on the arguments to
      this method.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example uses a ResDialog with a static control that displays a bitmap image.  The image for
      the static control is obtained from the resource-only DLL used by the ResDialog.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::class SimpleDialog subclass ResDialog
      ...

      ::method initDialog
        ...
        resources = .ResourceImage~new("simpleImage.dll", self)
        image = resources~getImage(self~constDir[ID_BMP_IMAGE1])
        ...
        picture = self~newStatic(IDC_BMP_PICTURE)
        oldImage = picture~setImage(image)
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ResourceImage::getImage() [class method?] -->


<section id="mthGetImagesClsResourceImage" xreflabel="getImages"><title>getImages</title>
<indexterm><primary>getImages</primary>
<secondary>ResourceImage class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getImages(--ids,--+--------+--+--------+--+---------+--)----><
                      +-,-type-+  +-,-size-+  +-,-flags-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Loads a number of image resources from the module. An array of resource IDs is used to specify which
  image resources.  All the image resources must have the same characteristics.  That is they must all be
  the same type and use the same flags.  If the type is bitmap, and the flags include LR_DEFAULTSIZE, and
  the size is 0 x 0, then the size of the image will be the actual resource size.  Otherwise, all the
  images also need to be the same size.
</para>
<para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> <computeroutput>LoadImage()</computeroutput> is the underlying Windows API
    used here.  This method is very similar to the <xref linkend="mthFromIDsClsImage"/> method of the
    .Image class. The documentation for that method can provide additional information.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>The arguments are:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>ids</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          An array of the resource IDs of the image resources in the module.  The array can contain
          any number of IDs, but it can not be sparse.  That is, each index of the array must contain a
          number.  If an incorrect item is detected in the array, then a syntax error is raised and no
          images are returned.
        </para>
        <para>
          If there is an error with an individual image resource, then the index in the array for that
          image is left empty.  One way to check for this type of error is to compare the number of items
          in the returned array with the number of items in ID array.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>type</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Specifies the type of the image: bitmap, icon, or cursor. You can use
          the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric value for one of the
          following symbols:
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>IMAGE_BITMAP</member> <member>IMAGE_ICON</member>
          <member>IMAGE_CURSOR</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The default is IMAGE_BITMAP.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>size</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object that specifies the size of the image.  The default
          is a size of 0x0.  Under most circumstances this indicates that the actual size of the image
          should be used.  However, the MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation should
          be consulted for other meanings.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>flags</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The load resource flags for the LoadImage() API.  The flags are one or more of the following
          symbols. You can use the <xref linkend="mthToIDClsImage"/> method of the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> class to get the correct numeric
          value for any of the following symbols.  The <xref linkend="mthOrClsDlgUtil"/> method of
          the <xref linkend="clsDlgUtil"/> class can be used to combine more than one of the
          symbols if needed.
          <simplelist type='horiz' columns='2'>
          <member>LR_DEFAULTCOLOR</member>    <member>LR_CREATEDIBSECTION</member>
          <member>LR_DEFAULTSIZE</member>     <member>LR_LOADFROMFILE</member>
          <member>LR_LOADMAP3DCOLORS</member> <member>LR_LOADTRANSPARENT</member>
          <member>LR_MONOCHROME</member>      <member>LR_SHARED</member>
          <member>LR_VGACOLOR</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The default is LR_SHARED.
        </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return will be an array of .Image objects, one for each resource ID specified in the
      <computeroutput>ids</computeroutput> array, if there is no error.  If there is an error loading the
      image of any specified ID, the corresponding index in the returned array will be empty.
    </para>
    <para>
      If there is an error, both the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/> and the
 <xref linkend="mthSystemErrorCodeClsResourceImage"/> attribute of this
      resource image will be set (to the same code.)  It is conceivable that an error could occur where
      the system does not set an error code, but unlikely.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises a syntax error if the resource image is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected.
    </para>
    <para>
      Provides an interface to the Win32 API: <computeroutput>LoadImage()</computeroutput>. You can use
      the MSDN <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> documentation to get more information on the
      interaction between the flags, size, and type arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The following is a complete working dialog.  Four bitmap images are used.  Each time the user
      clicks the next button, the next image is displayed.
    </para>
    <para>
      An array is constructed containing the resource IDs of the 4 images.  A new resource image object
      is instantiated from the <computeroutput>images.dll</computeroutput> module.  The getImages()
      method is then used to get an array of 4 .Image objects, using the array of resource IDs.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      /* Simple Dialog to display some images */

        dlg = .SimpleDialog~new( , 'simpleImage.h')
        if dlg~initCode = 0 then do
          dlg~createCenter(200, 247, "Simple Image Viewer", "", , "MS Shell Dlg 2", 8)
          dlg~execute("SHOWTOP", 14)
        end

      return 0
      -- End of entry point.

      ::requires "ooDialog.cls"

      ::class SimpleDialog subclass UserDialog

      ::method defineDialog

        self~createStatic(IDC_BMP_PICTURE, 10, 10, 20, 17, "BITMAP REALSIZEIMAGE")
        self~createStatic(IDC_ST_DESCRIPTION, 14, 190, 176, 20, "TEXT LEFT", "Description")
        self~createPushButton(IDC_PB_NEXT, 10, 223, 50, 14, , "Next", onNext)
        self~createPushButton(IDOK, 140, 223, 50, 14, "DEFAULT", "Ok")

      ::method initDialog
        expose picture images description descriptions nextImage

        ids = .array~new
        ids[ 1] = self~constDir[ID_BMP_IMAGE1]
        ids[ 2] = self~constDir[ID_BMP_IMAGE2]
        ids[ 3] = self~constDir[ID_BMP_IMAGE3]
        ids[ 4] = self~constDir[ID_BMP_IMAGE4]

        descriptions = .array~new
        descriptions[1] = "Conrad, King of the Hill"
        descriptions[2] = "Berk, Squint Eye"
        descriptions[3] = "Cienna, Deer in the Headlights"
        descriptions[4] = "Vail, The Flower Child"

        picture = self~newStatic(IDC_BMP_PICTURE)
        description = self~newStatic(IDC_ST_DESCRIPTION)
        self~connectButtonEvent(IDC_PB_NEXT, "CLICKED", onNext)

        nextImage = 1
        module = .ResourceImage~new("images.dll")
        images = module~getImages(ids)

        self~onNext

      ::method onNext
        expose picture description images descriptions nextImage

        if nextImage > images~items then nextImage = 1

        picture~setImage(images[nextImage])

        description~setText(descriptions[nextImage])
        nextImage += 1
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ResourceImage::getImages() -->


<section id="mthHandleClsResourceImage" xreflabel="handle"><title>handle</title>
<indexterm><primary>handle</primary>
<secondary>ResourceImage class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--handle---------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns the Windows system handle for the resource module.  It is an error to invoke this method if the
  resource image is null, or after the resource image has been released.
</para>
<para>
   At this time, the handle is only useful for display.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return is the handle for the module the resource image represents.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example ...
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method showHandles

        oodMod = .ResourceImage~new("oodialog.dll", self)
        resMod = .ResourceImage~new("simpleImage.dll", self)

        say 'The oodialog.dll module handle is:        ' oodMod~handle
        say 'The resource module for this ResDialog is:' resMod~handle


      /* The output, for a ResDialog, might be:

         The oodialog.dll module handle is:         0x009E0000
         The resource module for this ResDialog is: 0x00AF0000
      */
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ResourceImage::handle() -->


<section id="mthIsNullClsResourceImage" xreflabel="isNull"><title>isNull</title>
<indexterm><primary>isNull</primary>
<secondary>ResourceImage class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--isNull---------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Determines if the resource image is valid.  <computeroutput>isNull()</computeroutput> will always
  return <computeroutput>.true</computeroutput> after the resource image has been released.  It will also
  return <computeroutput>.true</computeroutput> if there was an error instantiating a new resource image
  object.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are no arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Returns <computeroutput>.true</computeroutput> if the object is null, otherwise
      <computeroutput>.false</computeroutput>.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      It is a good idea to check that a new resource image object is valid before using it.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method initDialog
        ...
        resourceModule = .ResourceImage~new("simpleImage.dll", self)
        if \ resourceModule~isNull the do
          image = resources~getImage(self~constDir[ID_BMP_IMAGE1])
        else do
          -- Some error handling here.
        end
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ResourceImage::isNull() -->


<section id="mthReleaseClsResourceImage" xreflabel="release"><title>release</title>
<indexterm><primary>release</primary>
<secondary>ResourceImage class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--release--------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Releases the resource module so that the operating system can reclaim the system resources.  After the
  resource image has been released it can no longer be used.  The programmer should not release the
  resource image while resources loaded from the module are still in use.
</para>
<para>
  If the resource image represents the <computeroutput>oodialog.dll</computeroutput> module, or the
  module used for a ResDialog, then the resource image should never be released.  The
  <computeroutput>release()</computeroutput> method will ignore release requests in those situations.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>There are no arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This method return the system error code, which will be zero if there is no error, and non-zero if
      there is an error. The <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/> is also set to
      this value.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Raises a syntax error if the resource image is null.
    </para>
    <para>
      Sets the <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      In this example, the images for an image list are loaded from a resource module.  The resource
      module is no longer needed after the image list is created. Since an image list makes a copy of the
      images added to it, once the image list has all the images added to it, the resource image can be
      released.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method getImages private
        use strict arg resourceIDs, size, ilFlags

        imageList = .ImageList~create(size, ilFlags, 20, 10);

        module = .ResourceImage~new("zooImages.dll")
        images = module~getImages(resourceIDs)
        imageList~addImages(images)

        do i = 1 to images~items
          images[i]~release
        end
        module~release

        return imageList
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ResourceImage::release() -->


<section id="mthSystemErrorCodeClsResourceImage" xreflabel="systemErrorCode"><title>systemErrorCode</title>
<indexterm><primary>systemErrorCode</primary>
<secondary>ResourceImage class</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--systemErrorCode------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  When a method for a resource image is invoked that sets the
  <xref linkend="dotSystemErrorCode"/>, the systemErrorCode attribute of the resource
  image object is also set. This can be useful if the programmer wants to check for an error code at some
  point when it is possible that .systemErrorCode has been reset.
</para>
<para>
  This method can always be invoked, even if the resource image is null.  It is very similar to the
<xref linkend="mthSystemErrorCodeClsImage"/> method of the .Image class and the
  documentation for that method is generally applicable here.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This method does not take any arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The return is a system error code, which will usually be 0, no error.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This example uses the <computeroutput>systemErrorCode</computeroutput> attribute to get more
      information on a possible error, rather than the <computeroutput>.systemErrorCode</computeroutput>.
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::method initDialog
        ...
        mod = .ResourceImage~new("simpleImage.dll", self)
        if mod~isNull the do
          self~writeToLog("Error with resource module simpleImage.dll")
          self~writeToLog("  RC: " mod~systemErrorCode)
          self~writeToLog("  msg:" SysGetErrorText(mod~systemErrorCode)
          return
        end

        image = resources~getImage(self~constDir[ID_BMP_IMAGE1])
        ...
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ResourceImage::systemErrorCode() -->

</section>  <!--   End ResourceImage class  -->


</chapter>
