<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "oodguide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooDialog User Guide XML file.
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2012-2022, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<!-- Appendix 06 - Direct Manipulation				  v01-00 22Aug13

     An overview of drag-drop or direct manipulation - part of the
     Model-View Framework (MVF).

     Changes:
     v01-00 22Aug13: First version.

     A6   *  Direct Manipulation                              apx6-dm
     A6.1    * The Mouse Class                              apx6-dm-ms
     A6.2    * Enabling Drag/Drop                          apx6-dm-setup
     A6.3    * Pickup and Drag                               apx6-dm-pickup
     A6.4    * Drop on Target                                 apx6-dm-drop

-->
<appendix id="apx6-dm">
  <title id="apx6-dm.title">Direct Manipulation</title>
  <indexterm><primary>Direct manipulation</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>Drag-drop</primary></indexterm>
  <para>This appendix provides an overview of the internals of the direct manipulation or
    "drag/drop" function provided from Exercise08 onwards. Drag/drop is handled by a framework that
    relieves the application developer from almost all of the necessary complexities of drag/drop.
    This framework is implemented by a cooperation between the <computeroutput>View</computeroutput>
    superclass and a new "manager" class, the Drag Manager
      (<computeroutput>DragMgr.rex</computeroutput>) both of which are located in the
      <computeroutput>Exercise08\Support</computeroutput> folder. A description of the application
    developer's view of drag/drop is provided in Chapter 8, <xref linkend="chap08-dragdrop"/>.</para>
  <para>This Appendix discusses the following aspects of the "mechanics" of drag/drop:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="apx6-dm-mouse"/></para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="apx6-dm-factoring"/></para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="apx6-dm-setup"/></para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="apx6-dm-drag"/></para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="apx6-dm-drop"/></para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <!-- Section A6.1: ??? -->
  <section id="apx6-dm-mouse" xreflabel="The Mouse Class">
    <title>The Mouse Class</title>
    <para>Drag/drop is enabled through ooDialog's <computeroutput>Mouse</computeroutput> class. When
      a window (a dialog or a control such as a List View) is to be the source of a
      drag operation, then an instance of the <computeroutput>Mouse</computeroutput> class must be
      instantiated (typically in the dialog's <computeroutput>initDialog</computeroutput> method) and
      associated with the window. For example:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[     mouse = .Mouse~new(self)]]></programlisting>
      Mouse events are
      then connected to the mouse instance. For example, here's the code for
      connecting a left-button-down (aka "start drag" or "pickup") event:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[     mouse~connectEvent('LBUTTONDOWN', dmOnLBdown)]]></programlisting>This
      defines the method <computeroutput>dmOnLBdown</computeroutput> as the event handler for a
      pickup. Other drag/drop events include mouse movement (dragging with the left
      button down) and a drop (left button up).</para>
    <para>When the user presses and holds the left mouse button then a pickup event is detected, and
      the "Left Button Down" event handler method is invoked. In this method, the mouse instance is
      "captured" as follows: <programlisting><![CDATA[     if mouse~dragDetect(...) then do
        ...
        mouse~capture()
        ...
      end]]></programlisting>The <computeroutput>dragDetect</computeroutput> method returns
        <computeroutput>.true</computeroutput> if the user has indeed started dragging. Note that
      all drag/drop events are sent to the object in which the mouse was instantiated - and each
      mouse instance is affiliated with a specific window object. For clarity, in the above code
      various statements to do with setting the drag cursor and establishing the initial state of
      the drag operation (e.g. the "we're not over a target" state) are omitted.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="apx6-dm-factoring" xreflabel="Factoring the Drag/Drop Code">
    <title>Factoring the Drag/Drop Code</title>
    <para>Drag/drop code is not particularly simple. So the question is, can the code be factored so
      that much of the detail can be delegated so that the application developer finds drag/drop
      easy to implement? To answer this, we start by defining the things that <emphasis
        role="italic"><emphasis role="bold">must</emphasis></emphasis> be done by the application
      developer; everything else can then be delegated to a superclass or other "manager" object.
      This minimum set, for simple drag/drop operations between dialogs, is as follows: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Define the dialog window (or control window within a dialog) that is to be the
            drag/drop "source" (i.e. that it can be picked up). This includes: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The area within the window from which a pickup is valid.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>The cursor icon to be used in dragging from a source window.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Define the dialog window (or a control window within a dialog) that will accept a
            drop. This includes the area within the window in which a drop is valid.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>Definition of both source and target dialogs is handled by an invocation of the
      superclass in an application dialog's <computeroutput>initDialog</computeroutput> method (as
      discussed in the next section). Everything else is handled by the
        <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> superclass (the superclass of all "view" components
      and located in the <computeroutput>Support</computeroutput> folder).</para>
      <para>Finally, <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> delegates most of the detailed
      handling of a drag/drop operation to the Drag Manager (<computeroutput>DragMgr.rex</computeroutput> - also located
      in the <computeroutput>Support</computeroutput> folder).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="apx6-dm-setup" xreflabel="Enabling Drag/Drop">
      <title id="apx6-dm-setup.title">Enabling Drag/Drop</title>
    <para>In Exercise08, all mouse events are registered in the
        <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> superclass. However, only an application-level dialog
      can define itself as a potential source for a drag operation. It does this by supering (from
      its <computeroutput>initDialog</computeroutput> method) a
        <computeroutput>dmSetAsSource</computeroutput> message (as shown at the top of <xref
        linkend="fig-apx6-01"/>). A mouse instance is created in the superclass's
        <computeroutput>dmSetAsSource</computeroutput> method and the pickup, drag, and drop events
      are connected to <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> methods. Finally,
        <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> sends a <computeroutput>setSource</computeroutput>
      message to the Drag Manager informing it that a new source dialog is present (the dialog's
      mouse instance being included as one of the arguments). The Drag Manager stores this
      information in a table. When a drag is started, it is the Drag Manager that manages the fine
      detail of the operation, finding the right mouse instance from its table of source and target
      windows.</para>
    <para>Now, if mouse events are fired during drag/drop, then what object instance receives these
      events? The answer is the object that instantiated the mouse - that is, the application-level
      view component - although handling these events is done in the
        <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> superclass, from where they're passed to the Drag
      Manager. </para>

    <para>The diagram "<xref linkend="fig-apx6-01"/>" shows how components are enabled for either
      dragging or dropping. <figure id="fig-apx6-01">
        <title>Drag/Drop Setup</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Appendix06-image1.jpg" scale="75"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>In the diagram, a component view that can be "picked up and dragged" is called a
        <emphasis role="italic">source dialog</emphasis>. <indexterm>
        <primary>Source dialog</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Direct manipulation</primary>
        <secondary>Source dialog</secondary>
      </indexterm> It defines itself as a "source" by supering to
        <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> a <computeroutput>dmSetAsSource</computeroutput>
      message (typically from its <computeroutput>initDialog</computeroutput> method). There are
      three parameters to this message: first (obligatory) is the file name of the cursor to show
      when dragging (a <computeroutput>*.cur</computeroutput> file), and second (optional) the area
      of the source dialog from which it's valid to "pick up" - i.e. to start dragging, and the
      third (optional) is a control window when the pickup is from a specific control in the dialog.
      If the second parameter is not provided, then the superclass defaults to the dialog area less
      10 on each side. If the third argum,ent is not provided, it default to the dialog window. </para>
    <para>In its <computeroutput>dmSetAsSource</computeroutput> method,
        <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> first creates an instance of the
        <computeroutput>.Mouse</computeroutput> class, and registers three event handling methods -
        <computeroutput>LBUTTONDOWN</computeroutput>), <computeroutput>MOUSEMOVE</computeroutput>
      and <computeroutput>LBUTTONUP</computeroutput>. If these events are not defined then drag/drop
      operations are ignored. It then invokes the <computeroutput>setSource</computeroutput> method
      of the Drag Manager with five arguments: the source window, the mouse instance, the cursor
      filename, the source's valid pickup area, and the source dialog. The Drag Manager then adds
      the source window to its table of sources. Note that if a
        <computeroutput>dmSetAsSource</computeroutput> message is not supered by a dialog, then no
      mouse events are handled, and so nothing happens when mouse button 1 is pressed and
      held.</para>
    <para>A view component that will accept a drop is called a <emphasis role="italic">target
        dialog</emphasis>. <indexterm>
        <primary>Target dialog</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Direct manipulation</primary>
        <secondary>Target dialog</secondary>
      </indexterm> It defines itself as a target by supering a
        <computeroutput>dmSetAsTarget</computeroutput> message (typically from its
        <computeroutput>initDialog</computeroutput> method) to its
        <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> superclass. The only argument is the area in the
      dialog in which a drop is allowed. If omitted, the default is the dialog client area less 10
      on each side. <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> then invokes the Drag Manager's
        <computeroutput>setTarget</computeroutput> method with three parameters: the dialog id, the
      dialog's window handle, and area within the dialog within which a drop is allowed. </para>
    <para>Finally, note that a view component can be both a source and a target.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="apx6-dm-drag" xreflabel="Pickup and Drag">
    <title id="apx6-dm-drag.title">Pickup and Drag</title>
    <para>The top part of the following figure shows the pickup and drag operation. The lower half
      shows a drop.</para>
  <figure id="fig-apx6-02" xreflabel="Drag/Drop Operation"><title>Drag/Drop Operation</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Appendix06-image2.jpg" scale="75" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>The operation is as follows:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>The operation starts with the user pressing and holding the "primary" button (usually the left
            button) of the mouse while over a "source" dialog. This results in the event
              <computeroutput>LBUTTONDOWN</computeroutput> being signaled to the source dialog. This
            is handled by the <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> superclass's
              <computeroutput>dmOnLBdown</computeroutput> method, which in turn invokes the Drag
            Manager's <computeroutput>dmPickup</computeroutput> method. The Drag Manager then
            "captures" the mouse instance (using the Mouse class's
              <computeroutput>capture</computeroutput> method). This results in all mouse messages
            being sent to the source dialog where they are handled by the
              <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> superclass. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>As the mouse is dragged, multiple <computeroutput>MOUSEMOVE</computeroutput> events are
            handled by the <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> superclass, which delegates them to
            the Darg Manager. For each such message, the Drag Manager checks if the mouse is over a
            target that’s registered in its Target Table. If no, then nop. If yes, then a possible
            target has been found, at which point the Drag Manager:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>Sends a <computeroutput>dmQueryDrop</computeroutput> message to the class object of the target
                view's model with source's model class name as the single parameter. Why the class
                object? And why that of the target view's model? The reason is that, in the general
                case, the user may drag the mouse across a large number of possible targets such as
                multiple entries in a list view. And it could well be that each item in the list
                represents a model and view instance (e.g. a list of Customers). Further, it may
                well be that none of them are instantiated (which could well involve accessing a
                data base of some sort). Now all that's required for the drag operation is a simple
                yes/no answer: can the source be dropped or not. Thus in order to avoid excessive
                and pointless processing, the model's class object is invoked. The target object
                returns a simple yes or no as to whether as drop on an instance of the target class
                is permissible.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>If the potential target returns true, then the Drag Manager set the cursor to the "drop OK"
                cursor - that is, the cursor provided by the source dialog when it told its
                superclass that it was a potential drag source.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist></listitem>
    </orderedlist></para>
  </section>
  <section id="apx6-dm-drop" xreflabel="Drop on Target">
    <title>Drop on a Target</title>
    <para>The drop is illustrated diagrammatically in the bottom half of <xref linkend="fig-apx6-02"
      />. A dialog (or a control within a dialog) sets itself as a potential drop target by supering
      a <computeroutput>dmSetAsTarget</computeroutput> message. The
        <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> superclass then sends the Drag Manager a
        <computeroutput>setTarget</computeroutput> message with three parameters: the dialog id, the
      dialog's window id, and the drop area. The Drag Manager stores this information in a table. A
      drop occurs when the user releases the left button. When this happens, the event handling
      method <computeroutput>dmOnLBup</computeroutput> in the <computeroutput>View</computeroutput>
      superclass is invoked. <computeroutput>View</computeroutput> then sends the Drag Manager a
        <computeroutput>dmDrop</computeroutput> message. This has three arguments: the dialog id,
      the key state, and the mouse position. The Drag Manager first releases the mouse and resets
      the mouse cursor. Then it sends a <computeroutput>dmDrop</computeroutput> message to the
      target view's model object, with two arguments: the model id of the source object, and the
      source dialog's id. </para>
    <para>The target object then does whatever it wishes to do. Often target's action is to send a
        <computeroutput>query</computeroutput> message to the source model in order to get its data.
      The drag-drop operation is now complete.  </para>
  </section>
  <!--  End of A6.1.  -->
</appendix>
