<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ooconsole.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooDialog User Guide XML file
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2012-2014 Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<preface id="pref-ooconsole-Preface">
<title>Preface</title>

<para>
  This book provides a reference manual to the <computeroutput>ooConsole</computeroutput> framework.
  <computeroutput>ooConsole</computeroutput> is an ooRexx native extension. It is a <emphasis
  role="italic">Windows</emphasis> only extension and gives the ooRexx programmer access to the Console API provided by
  Windows.
</para>


<xi:include href="Common_Content/Conventions.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />


<section id="syndia"><title>How to Read the Syntax Diagrams</title>
<para>
  Throughout this book, syntax is described using the structure defined below. This is similar to, but slightly
  different than, the IBM syntax diagrams used in other ooRexx reference documentation.  The author is calling these
  diagrams <emphasis role="italic">simplified railroad tracks</emphasis>. It primarily strives to limit all diagrams to
  2 lines, and does away with much of the complexity of true IBM railroad tracks. The body of text following the
  syntax diagrams, along with this clarifying text, will resolve any ambiguities in the diagrams.
</para>
<para>
  In this reference, the syntax diagrams being presented are the diagrams of the syntax for method, attribute, and routine
  invocations. The diagrams show the method, attribute, or routine name and the arguments for the invocation. For method or
  attribute invocations, the section the method or attribute is included in, and / or the text itself, make it clear as to
  which class the method belongs to. The following defines how the syntax diagrams are to be read:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
  Each syntax diagram is for a single method, attribute, or routine invocation,
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Read the syntax diagrams from left to right, from top to bottom, following the path of the line.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>&gt;&gt;--</computeroutput> symbol indicates the beginning of an invocation or call.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>--&gt;</computeroutput> symbol indicates that the invocation syntax is continued on the next line. In
  most cases continuation is avoided.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>&gt;---</computeroutput> symbol indicates that a statement is continued from the previous line.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>-&gt;&lt;</computeroutput> symbol indicates the end of a statement.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  The method, attribute, or routine name is the first token, (first word,) on the horizontal line (the main path).
  Parentheses enclose the arguments, if there are any arguments.

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--methodName()---------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Methods, attributes, or routines that do not accept arguments, stand alone on the main line.

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--attributeName--------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Required arguments appear on the horizontal line, (the main path,) wihin the parentheses.

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--methodName(--requiredArgument--)-------------><
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Optional arguments appear on a line directly below the main path.

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--methodName(--+--------------------+--)-------><
                 +--optionalArgument--+
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Commas are placed on the same line and immediately before the argument whose position relies on the comma.

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--methodName(--arg1--+-----------+--,--arg3--+-----------+--)----------------><
                       +--,--arg2--+           +--,--arg4--+
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<important><title>Important</title>
  <para>
    In ooRexx, the arguments to methods or functions are enclosed in parenthesis and each argument is separated by a comma.
    The arguments are <emphasis role="italic">positional</emphasis> and the commas are always required to properly place an
    argument in its correct position. Required arguments can not be omitted. Optional arguments can be omitted, however, any
    argument that follows an omitted argument <emphasis role="italic">must</emphasis> be in its proper position as delineated
    by the commas. If there are no arguments following an omitted argument, there is no need to include any following commas.
    But, it is not incorrect to include the following commas.
  </para>
</important>
<para>
  In the syntax diagrams in this document, arguments are represented by appropriate variable names and these variable names
  are then described in the text for the method. When arguments are optional, the default value and or behavior if the
  argument is omitted is also described in the text.
</para>
<para>
  In <emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis> cases, the text rather than the syntax diagram should be considered definitive.
</para>
<para>
  The following example shows the described syntax:
</para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--addAlias(--alias--+-------------+--+----------+--)----------><
                      +--,--target--+  +--,--exe--+
]]>
</programlisting>
<para>
  In the above example, the syntax diagram indicates that the name of the method or routine is <emphasis
  role="italic">addAlias</emphasis>. The <link linkend="mthAddAlias">location</link> of the syntax diagram in the
  body of this document would clearly indicate that it is a method of the <xref linkend="clsOOConsole"/> class. The diagram
  indicates that the first argument is required and is followed by two arguments that are optional.
</para>
<para>
  <emphasis role="bold">In addition</emphasis>, the syntax diagram indicates that <emphasis role="italic">if</emphasis> the
  second positional argument is omitted but the third positional arugment is used, there <emphasis
  role="bold">must</emphasis> be two commas preceding the <emphasis role="italic">exe</emphasis> argument.
</para>
<important><title>Important</title>
  <para>
    Although the reader may prefer to interpret the syntax diagrams in some other way than that just explained, any other
    interpretation is not correct.
  </para>
</important>
</section>


<section id="helpGettingHelp"><title>Getting Help and Submitting Feedback</title>
<para>
  The Open Object Rexx Project has a number of methods to obtain help and submit feedback for ooRexx and the
  extension packages that are part of ooRexx. These methods are listed below. For users of ooConsole, the order listed below
  is in the order that is most likely to receive prompt help or support.
</para>

<section><title>The Open Object Rexx SourceForge Site</title>
<para>
  The <ulink url="http://www.oorexx.org/">Open Object Rexx Project</ulink> utilizes
  <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/"><citetitle>SourceForge</citetitle></ulink> to house the
  <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/oorexx"><citetitle>ooRexx Project</citetitle></ulink>
  source repositories, mailing lists, and other project features. Over time it has become apparent to the ooRexx developers
  that the mailing lists are better tools for carrying on discussions concerning ooRexx and that the Forums provided by
  SourceForge are cumbersome to use. The ooRexx user is most likely to get timely replies by posting questions or comments
  to the Users Mailing List.
</para>
<para>
  Here is a list of some of the most useful facilities provided by SourceForge.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry id="helpUsersList"><term>The Users Mailing List</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    You can subscribe to the oorexx-users mailing list at <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/mailman/">
    <citetitle>ooRexx Mailing List Subscriptions</citetitle></ulink> page. This list is for discussing using ooRexx. It
    also supports a historical archive of past messages. Users of ooDialog are <emphasis role="italic">most</emphasis> likely
    to get a prompt reply to their questions, suggestions, or comments on that mailing list.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>The Announcements Mailing List</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    You can subscribe to the oorexx-announce mailing list at <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/mailman/">
    <citetitle>ooRexx Mailing List Subscriptions</citetitle></ulink> page. This list is only used to announce
    significant ooRexx project events.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry id="helpDevelList"><term>The Developer Mailing List</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    You can subscribe to the oorexx-devel mailing list at <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/mailman/">
    <citetitle>ooRexx Mailing List Subscriptions</citetitle></ulink> page. This list is for discussing ooRexx project
    development activities and future interpreter enhancements.  It also supports a historical archive of past
    messages.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>The Bug Mailing List</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    You can subscribe to the oorexx-bugs mailing list at <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/mailman/">
    <citetitle>ooRexx Mailing List Subscriptions</citetitle></ulink> page. This list is only used for
    monitoring changes to the ooRexx bug tracking system.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>Bug Reports</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    You can create a bug report at <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/bugs/"> <citetitle>ooRexx Bug
    Report</citetitle></ulink> page. Please try to provide as much information in the bug report as possible so that the
    developers can determine the problem as quickly as possible.  Sample programs that can reproduce your problem will make
    it easier to debug reported problems.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>Documentation Feedback</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    You can submit feedback for, or report errors in, the documentation at
    <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/documentation/"> <citetitle>ooRexx Documentation Report</citetitle></ulink>
    page. Please try to provide as much information in a documentation report as possible. In addition to listing the
    document and section the report concerns, direct quotes of the text will help the developers locate the text in the
    source code for the document. (Section numbers are generated when the document is produced and are not available in the
    source code itself.) Suggestions as to how to reword or fix the existing text should also be included.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>Request For Enhancement</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    You can suggest ooRexx features at the<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/feature-requests/"> <citetitle>ooRexx
    Feature Requests</citetitle></ulink> page.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>Patch Reports</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    If you create an enhancement patch for ooRexx please post the patch using the <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/patches/"> <citetitle>ooRexx Patch Report</citetitle></ulink> page. Please provide
    as much information in the patch report as possible so that the developers can evaluate the enhancement as quickly as
    possible.
  </para>
  <para>
    Please do not post bug fix patches here, instead you should open a bug report and attach the patch to it.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>The ooRexx Forums</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The ooRexx project maintains a set of forums that anyone may contribute to or monitor. They are located on the
    <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/discussion/"><citetitle>Open Object Rexx Discussion</citetitle></ulink> page.
    There are currently four forums available: Help, Developers, Open Discussion, and General Discussion. In addition, you
    can monitor the forums via email.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section><title>The Rexx Language Association Mailing List</title>
<para>
  The <ulink url="http://www.rexxla.org/"><citetitle>Rexx Language Association</citetitle></ulink> maintains a mailing
  list for its members. This mailing list is only available to RexxLA members thus you will need to
  join RexxLA in order to get on the list. The dues for RexxLA membership are small and are charged on a yearly basis.
  For details on joining RexxLA please refer to the
  <ulink url="http://rexxla.org/"><citetitle>RexxLA Home Page</citetitle></ulink> or the
  <ulink url="http://www.rexxla.org/rexxla/join.html">
  <citetitle>RexxLA Membership Application</citetitle></ulink> page.
</para>
</section>

<section><title>comp.lang.rexx Newsgroup</title>
<para>
  The <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/comp.lang.rexx/topics?hl=en">comp.lang.rexx</ulink> newsgroup is a good
  place to obtain help from many individuals within the Rexx community. You can obtain help on Open Object Rexx or on any
  number of other Rexx interpreters and tools.
</para>
</section>

</section>

<section id="relinf"><title>Related Information</title>
<para>See also:
<citetitle pubwork="book">Open Object Rexx: Reference</citetitle></para>
</section>

</preface>

