<appendix id="notices"><title id="notices.title">Notices</title>
<indexterm><primary>Notices</primary></indexterm>
<para>Any performance data contained herein was determined in a controlled environment.
Therefore, the results obtained in other operating environments may vary significantly.
Some measurements may have been made on development-level systems and there
is no guarantee that these measurements will be the same on generally available
systems. Furthermore, some measurement may have been estimated through extrapolation.
Actual results may vary. Users of this document should verify the applicable
data for their specific environment.</para>
<para>This information contains examples of data and reports used in daily business
operations. To illustrate them as completely as possible, the examples include
the names of individuals, companies, brands, and products. All of these names
are fictitious and any similarity to the names and addresses used by an actual
business enterprise is entirely coincidental.</para>

<section id="tmsm"><title>Trademarks</title>
<para>The following terms are trademarks of the IBM Corporation in the United
States, other countries, or both: </para>
<simplelist>
<member>AIX</member>
<member>IBM</member>
<member>Lotus</member>
<member>OS/2</member>
<member>S/390</member>
<member>VisualAge</member>
</simplelist>

<para>AMD is a trademark of Advance Micro Devices, Inc.</para>
<para>Intel, Intel Inside (logos), MMX and Pentium are trademarks of Intel Corporation
in the United States, other countries, or both.</para>
<para>Java and all Java-based trademarks are trademarks of Oracle,
Corporation in the Unites States, other countries, or both.</para>
<para>Linux is a trademark of Linus Torvalds in the United States, other countries,
or both.</para>
<para>Microsoft, Windows, Windows NT, and the Windows logo are trademarks of
Microsoft Corporation in the United States, other countries, or both.</para>
<para>UNIX is a registered trademark of The Open Group in the United States and
other countries.</para>
<para>Other company, product, or service names may be trademarks
or service marks of others.</para>
</section>

</appendix>
