<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "oosqlite.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooSqlite XML file.
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2012-2014 Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<preface id="oosqlite-Preface">
<title>Preface</title>

<para>
  This book describes the ooSQLite framework, which is implemented as an external library package for ooRexx. External
  library packages are often called <emphasis role="italic">extensions</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="italic">native
  extensions</emphasis>. The library package extends the capability of the Rexx interpreter by adding functionality or
  features not present in the base interpreter.
</para>
<para>
  The ooSQLite library package gives programmers access to the SQLite database engine directly from their Rexx programs.
  This book describes the Classes, Methods, and Funtions in ooSQLite that allow that access and describes how to use
  them.
</para>


<xi:include href="Common_Content/Conventions.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />


<section id="whoshoulduse"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title>
<para>
  This book is intended for Open Object Rexx programmers who are using or intend to use ooSQLite in their Rexx
  programs. The book does not teach SQL nor relational database design or management. It provides a basic introduction
  to using SQLite through the documentation of the classes and functions available in ooSQLite. In depth documentation
  of SQLite is provided by the developers of SQLite at their <ulink
  url="http://www.sqlite.org/index.html">website</ulink>, not in this book.
</para>
</section>

<section id="bookstructure"><title>How This Book is Structured</title>
<para>
  This book is primarily a reference to the classes and functions in ooSQLite. ooSQLite provides an object-orientated
  interface and a classic Rexx interface to SQLite. The book is broken into two main sections. The first section
  describes the object-orientated interface and the second section describes the classic Rexx section. Preceding the
  object-orientated section are the two chapters, <emphasis role="italic">About This Book</emphasis> and <emphasis
  role="italic">Brief Overview</emphasis>. They contain a small amount of overall information. A detailed index follows
  the classic Rexx section.
</para>
<para>
  The object-orientated section contains a reference for each class in ooSQLite. Each class reference contains a single
  section for every class, instance, and attribute method of the class. The first section in a class reference is a
  table listing every method with a brief description and a link to the detailed documentation for the method.
</para>
<para>
  Each method section starts with a <link linkend="syndia">syntax</link> diagram as a synopsis of how to invoke the
  method. Text follows describing the method, listing each argument to the method, and the return from the method. Most
  method sections have a <emphasis role="italic">remarks</emphasis> component discussing the method in more detail. Most
  method sections also have a <emphasis role="italic">details</emphasis> component pointing to the SQLite documentation
  that is most relevant to the method. To fully understand the use of any single method, the reader should also consult
  the SQLite documentation relevant to that method. Finally, many, but not all, of the method sections end with a short
  code snippet as an example of using the method.
</para>
<para>
  The classic Rexx section starts with a table that lists every function available for the classic Rexx programmer. This
  table is similar to the method table that begins each class reference. The table contains a brief description of the
  function and a link to the detailed documentation for the function. Each function is fully documented in a single
  section.
</para>
<para>
  The reference for each single function is very similar to the reference to each single method. It starts with a syntax
  diagram, describes the function, lists the arguments and return. It usually has a remarks component. The details
  component points the way to the authoritative SQLite documentation. Some, but not all function references contain an
  example.
</para>
<para>
  Each method and function reference is meant to be stand alone. All the details to use any method or function are
  included within the section for that method or function. Each method and function is listed in the index. The reader
  can look up any function or method in the index or the table of contents and go straight to the reference for the
  function or method.
</para>
<para>
  Within the reference for a single class, each method appears in alphabetical order. Likewise the reference for each
  function appears in this reference manual in alphabetical order.
</para>
</section>

<section id="relinf"><title>Related Information</title>
<para>See also:
<citetitle pubwork="book">Open Object Rexx: Reference</citetitle></para>
<para>
  There is a wealth of information on SQLite and how to use SQLite on the Web. This information is directly applicable
  to using ooSQLite. The SQLite <ulink url="http://www.sqlite.org/index.html">home</ulink> page is the authoritative
  answer to any SQLite question. In addition there is a SQLiter users mailing <ulink
  url="http://sqlite.org:8080/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/sqlite-users">list</ulink> that can be subscribed to.
</para>
</section>

<section id="syndia"><title>How to Read the Syntax Diagrams</title>
<para>
  Throughout this book, syntax is described using the structure defined below. This is similar to, but slightly
  different than, the IBM syntax diagrams used in other ooRexx reference documentation.  The author is calling these
  diagrams <emphasis role="italic">simplified railroad tracks</emphasis>. It primarily strives to limit all diagrams to
  2 lines, and does away with much of the complexity of true IBM railroad tracks. The body of text following the
  syntax diagrams will resolve any ambiguities in the diagram.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
  Read the syntax diagrams from left to right, from top to bottom, following the path of the line.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>&gt;&gt;---</computeroutput> symbol indicates the beginning of a statement.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>---&gt;</computeroutput> symbol indicates that the statement syntax is continued on the next
  line. In most cases statement continuation is avoided.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>&gt;---</computeroutput> symbol indicates that a statement is continued from the previous line.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>---&gt;&lt;</computeroutput> symbol indicates the end of a statement.
</para>
<para>
  Diagrams of syntactical units other than complete statements start with the <computeroutput>&gt;---</computeroutput>
  symbol and end with the  <computeroutput>---&gt;</computeroutput> symbol.
</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Required items appear on the horizontal line (the main path).

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>-STATEMENT--required_item------------------------------------><


]]>
</programlisting>
</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Optional items appear below the main path.

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>-STATEMENT--+---------------+--------------------------------><
              +-optional_item-+


]]>
</programlisting>
</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>
  In this reference, the syntax being presented is the syntax for method invocations and function calls. The diagrams
  show the method, or function, names and their arguments.  For method invocations, the section the method is included
  in, and / or the text itself, make it clear as to which class the method belongs to.  The arguments to the method or
  function are enclosed in parenthesis and separated by commas.  The arguments are represented by appropriate variable
  names and these variable names are then described in the text for the method.  When arguments are optional, the
  default value and or behavior if the argument is omitted is also described in the text.  In all cases, the text rather
  than the syntax diagram should be considered definitive.
</para>
<para>
  The following example shows the described syntax:
</para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

>>--rollbackHook(--callBackObj--+------------+--+-------------+--)-------------><
                                +-,-mthName--+  +-,-userData--+


]]>
</programlisting>
</section>

<section id="helpGettingHelp"><title>Getting Help and Submitting Feedback</title>
<para>The Open Object Rexx Project has a number of methods to obtain help and submit feedback for ooRexx and the
extension packages that are part of ooRexx. These methods, in no particular order of preference, are listed
below.</para>

<section><title>The Open Object Rexx SourceForge Site</title>
<para>The <ulink url="http://www.oorexx.org/">Open Object Rexx Project</ulink> utilizes
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/"><citetitle>SourceForge</citetitle></ulink>
to house the
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/oorexx"><citetitle>ooRexx Project</citetitle></ulink>
source repositories, mailing lists and other
project features. Over time it has become apparent that the Developer and User mailing lists are better tools for
carrying on discussions concerning ooRexx and that the Forums provided by SourceForge are cumbersome to use. The ooRexx
user is most likely to get timely replies from one of the mailing lists.
</para>
<para>
  Here is a list of some of the most useful facilities provided by SourceForge.
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry id="helpDevelList"><term>The Developer Mailing List</term>
<listitem><para>You can subscribe to the oorexx-devel mailing list at
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=119701">
<citetitle>ooRexx Mailing List Subscriptions</citetitle></ulink> page.
This list is for discussing ooRexx project development activities and future
interpreter enhancements.  It also supports a historical archive of past
messages.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry id="helpUsersList"><term>The Users Mailing List</term>
<listitem><para>You can subscribe to the oorexx-users mailing list at
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=119701">
<citetitle>ooRexx Mailing List Subscriptions</citetitle></ulink> page.
This list is for discussing using ooRexx.
It also supports a historical archive of past messages.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>The Announcements Mailing List</term>
<listitem><para>You can subscribe to the oorexx-announce mailing list at
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=119701">
<citetitle>ooRexx Mailing List Subscriptions</citetitle></ulink> page.
This list is only used to
announce significant ooRexx project events.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>The Bug Mailing List</term>
<listitem><para>You can subscribe to the oorexx-bugs mailing list at
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=119701">
<citetitle>ooRexx Mailing List Subscriptions</citetitle></ulink> page.
This list is only used for
monitoring changes to the ooRexx bug tracking system.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Bug Reports</term>
<listitem><para>You can create a bug report at
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=119701&amp;atid=684730">
<citetitle>ooRexx Bug Report</citetitle></ulink> page.
Please try to provide as much information in the bug report
as possible so that the developers can determine the problem as quickly as
possible.  Sample programs that can reproduce your problem will make it easier to
debug reported problems.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Documentation Feedback</term>
<listitem><para>You can submit feedback for, or report errors in, the documentation at
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=119701&amp;atid=1001880">
<citetitle>ooRexx Documentation Report</citetitle></ulink> page.
Please try to provide as much information in a documentation report as possible. In addition
to listing the document and section the report concerns, direct quotes of the text will help the
developers locate the text in the source code for the document. (Section numbers are generated
when the document is produced and are not available in the source code itself.) Suggestions as
to how to reword or fix the existing text should also be included.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Request For Enhancement</term>
<listitem><para>You can suggest ooRexx features at the
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=119701&amp;atid=684733">
<citetitle>ooRexx Feature Requests</citetitle></ulink> page.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Patch Reports</term>
<listitem><para>If you create an enhancement patch for ooRexx please
post the patch using the
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=119701&amp;atid=684732">
<citetitle>ooRexx Patch Report</citetitle></ulink> page.
Please provide as much information in the patch report
as possible so that the developers can evaluate the enhancement
as quickly as possible.</para>
<para>Please do not post bug fix patches here, instead you should open a bug report
and attach the patch to it.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>The ooRexx Forums</term>
<listitem><para>The ooRexx project maintains a set of forums that anyone
may contribute to or monitor. They are located on the
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/forum/?group_id=119701">
<citetitle>ooRexx Forums</citetitle></ulink> page.
There are currently three forums available: Help, Developers and Open
Discussion. In addition, you can monitor the forums via email.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section><title>The Rexx Language Association Mailing List</title>
<para>The <ulink url="http://www.rexxla.org/"><citetitle>Rexx Language Association</citetitle></ulink>
maintains a mailing list for its members.
This mailing list is only available to RexxLA members thus you will need to
join RexxLA in order to get on the list. The dues for RexxLA membership are
small and are charged on a yearly basis. For details on joining RexxLA please
refer to the
<ulink url="http://rexxla.org/"><citetitle>RexxLA Home Page</citetitle></ulink>
or the
<ulink url="http://www.rexxla.org/rexxla/join.html">
<citetitle>RexxLA Membership Application</citetitle></ulink> page.</para>
</section>

<section><title>comp.lang.rexx Newsgroup</title>
<para>The <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/comp.lang.rexx/topics?hl=en">comp.lang.rexx</ulink> newsgroup
is a good place to obtain help from many
individuals within the Rexx community. You can obtain help on Open Object
Rexx or on any number of other Rexx interpreters and tools.</para>
</section>

</section>

</preface>

