<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ootest.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: RxSock TCP/IP Socket Functions Reference
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2005-2025, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    # Portions Copyright (c) 2004, IBM Corporation. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->

<chapter id="chapOverview"><title>Overview of ooTest</title>
<indexterm><primary>ooTest</primary>
<secondary>overview</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
  The primary purpose of ooTest is to throughly test the ooRexx interpreter and its distribution
  pacakages.  In general, to throughly test software involves automating as much as possible of the
  testing.  The ooTest framework provides the foundation for automatically executing tests.  It currently
  contains little or no components that would aid in automating the writing of tests.
</para>
<note><title>Note</title><para>
  This document is written for the 4.0.0 and later versions of ooTest.  It makes no effort to cover the
  3.2.0 verison of ooTest, or explain any differences between the 3.2.0 and 4.0.0 versions.  There are
  differences.
</para></note>
<para>
  ooTest also contains all the tests written to date to that the ooRexx team uses to test ooRexx.  This
  makes ooTest itself more than just a framework.  It is the sum of the tests themselves, the framework
  to write the tests, and any other components used in the over all process of testing the ooRexx
  package.
</para>
<para>
  This document serves as a reference to the different components of ooTest.  It explains how to execute
  the tests, intepret the results, and gives some guidence on writing new tests.  There is very little
  involved in obtaining and settin up ooTest. Indeed there is very little set up involved in ooTest. It
  is merely a matter of placing the ooTest files on the system used to test.
</para>

<section id="getOOTest"><title>Install ooTest</title>
<indexterm><primary>installing ooTest</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>install</primary>
<secondary>ooTest</secondary></indexterm>

<para>
  Getting and installing ooTest is extremely easy.  There is no set up involved, you merely place the
  ooTest directory structure on somewhere convenient on your system.  The best method of obtaining the
  ooTest directory structure is to use a Subversion client to check out the ooTest repository.
  Subversion is widely avaliable, easy to install, and easy to use.  Directions for obtaining Subversion
  have been posted numerous times to the lists related to ooRexx.  There is a wealth of information on
  this subject on the Internet, simply use Google.
</para>
<para>
  Once you have a Subversion client, the following command will check out ooTest and place its directory
  structure in the subdirectory named <computeroutput>ooTest.4.0.0</computeroutput>. The subdirectory can
  be named anything you wish.
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
C:\>svn co https://oorexx.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/oorexx/test/trunk ooTest.4.0.0
]]>
</programlisting>
  The command is exactly the same on any operating system.
</para>
<para>
  The other way to obtain ooTest is to download one of the ooTest snapshots from the ooRexx project on
  SourceForge.  The drawback to this method is that the latest snapshot may not be current and you can
  not use the Subversion tools to keep your copy of ooTest up-to-date.  To download a snapshot go to this
  link on SourceForge:
  <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=119701&amp;package_id=251951">
  <citetitle>SourceForge.net: Open Object Rexx Files</citetitle></ulink> and download the appropriate
  file.  Then either untar or unzip the file whereever is convenient. For example:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
C:\>unzip ooTest-4.0.0-snapshot04_windows.i386.zip
]]>
</programlisting>
  Once the directory structure is placed on your system, you are ready to go. Use the driver program,
  testOORexx.rexx (<xref linkend="chapTestOORexx" />) to execute some tests. The tests should run and
  print out some statistics. This will ensure ooTest is working. The rest of this book goes into detail
  on all aspects of ooTest.
</para>
</section>

<section id="ooTestFoundation"><title>History, Foundation</title>
<indexterm><primary>ooTest</primary>
<secondary>history</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ooTest</primary>
<secondary>foundation</secondary></indexterm>

<para>
  ooTest started out as ooRexxUnit.  ooRexxUnit is a <emphasis role="italic">generic</emphasis> testing
  framework designed to serve as a unit testing framework for anyone to use to test their Rexx programs.
  It is patterned after jUnit and originally strove to emulate jUnit as closely as possible.  As a
  publicly released piece of software it was constrained by typical needs, such as providing backward
  compatibility, limiting changes that require the user to make changes to their exisiting testing
  efforts, etc..
</para>
<para>
  Over time it became apparent that the constraints of ooRexxUnit were a hinderance to the ooRexx testing
  effort.  Therefore, the ooTest framework was put in place.  ooTest sits on top of ooRexxUnit, but it is
  not designed to be a generic testing framework, does not guarentee backward compatibility, and does not
  strive to closely emulate jUnit.  The idea behind this was to leave ooRexxUnit as a generic testing
  framework for any one to use, and focus the ooTest framework on specificaly testing ooRexx.
</para>
<para>
  However, because of its history, ooTest is conceptualy similar to jUnit.  If you understand jUnit
  concepts, you will have little trouble understanding ooTest.  The main difference is that jUnit is
  primarily a unit testing framework, while ooTest is primarily an automation framework, that heavily
  supports unit testing.
</para>
<para>
  From the perspective of writing test cases, ooTest is very jUnit-like.  The terminology of ooTest is
  very similar to that of jUnit.  ooTest uses test cases, test case classes, test suites, test results,
  test runners, and asserts, just as jUnit does.  ooTest uses the same design patterns that jUnit uses.
  Hardly surprising as ooRexxUnit was modeled after jUnit.  jUnit has generated many tutorial and primer
  types of documentation on the Internet.  Google 'jUnit tutorial' or 'jUnit primer' and browse some of
  the simpler ones.  This will quickly give you a grasp of ooTest test cases.
</para>
</section>

<section id="testConcepts"><title>Testing Concepts Used in ooTest</title>
<indexterm><primary>Test</primary>
<secondary>concepts</secondary></indexterm>

<para>
  ooTest is a way of writing defined repeatable tests, collecting and storing the tests, and executing
  all or some of those tests, now and in the future.  With ooTest, all tests are to test the ooRexx
  interpreter and its distribution package.  The purpose of a test is to demonstrate that some facet of
  the interpreter works, both now and at the next point in time the test is executed.  To do this ooTest
  uses objects and the following loosely discusses these objects and how they fit together.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Test Case</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The test case is the basic concept of ooTest.  It is what the collection of defined repeatable
      tests is built upon.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Assertion</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      x.
    </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</section>

</chapter>

