<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "rxsock.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter><title>Introduction</title>
<para>RxMath is a Rexx utility package that enables you to use enhanced mathematical
functions.</para>
<para>The function names in the Rexx Mathematical Functions package are similar to
the names of their corresponding mathematical functions.</para>
<para>The precision of calculation depends on:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The value specified when the command is issued</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The numeric digits settings of the calling Rexx activity</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note><para>Precision is limited to 16 digits.</para></note>

<section><title>Using the RxMath package</title>
<para>
  The Rexx Mathematical Functions package is contained in the library <emphasis
  role="italic">rxmath</emphasis>, with the appropriate file name for the operating system.  This library
  must be loadable by the operating system using the normal procedure for the system. For instance, on Windows
  the file must be placed in a directory listed in your PATH. When installing ooRexx from any of the
  installation packages, the details of where the file is placed are handled automatically.
</para>
<para>
  Beginning with ooRexx 4.0.0, a more robust process is used to load external functions. To get access to
  the functions in the Rexx Mathematical Functions package, use a ::requires directive. For example:
</para>
<programlisting>
say 'The square root of 3 is:' RxCalcSqrt(3)

::requires 'rxmath' LIBRARY
</programlisting>
<para>
  Existing code that used the previous proces to load external functions:
</para>
<programlisting>
call rxfuncadd "MathLoadFuncs", "rxmath", "MathLoadFuncs"
</programlisting>
<para>
  does not need to be changed. However, both <computeroutput>MathLoadFuncs()</computeroutput> and
  <computeroutput>MathDropFuncs()</computeroutput> are nops in ooRexx 4.0.0 and later.
</para>
</section>

<section><title>Error Handling and Function Returns</title>
<para>
  Error 40 (Incorrect call to routine) is raised if either the wrong number of arguments or incorrect
  data is passed to a function.
</para>
<para>
  If a mathematical function fails, the function will return <emphasis role="italic">nan</emphasis>,
  <emphasis role="italic">+infinity</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="italic">-infinity</emphasis> as
  appropriate. These returns are consistent on all operating systems.
</para>
<para>
  Where an error occurs, the variable MATHERRNO is set with additional information that further defines
  the source of the error.
</para>
</section>
</chapter>
