<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooDialog Reference SGML file.
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2005-2011, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    # Portions Copyright (c) 2004, IBM Corporation. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    # Author(s):
    #      W. David Ashley <dashley@us.ibm.com>
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<chapter id="preface"><title>About This Book</title>
<para>
  This book describes the ooDialog framework, which is implemented as an external library package, and is part of the
  Open Object Rexx distribution on the <trademark class="registered">Windows</trademark> platform. It describes the
  classes in the framework and how to use the framework to program grahical user interfaces, (commonly referred to as a
  GUI,) on Windows
</para>

<section id="whoshoulduse"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title>
<para>
  This book is intended for Open Object Rexx programmers who want to design graphical user interfaces for their
  applications.
</para>
</section>

<section id="bookstructure"><title>How This Book is Structured</title>
<para>
  This book is primarily a reference that describes the classes and methods in the ooDialog framework in detail. In
  general, each chapter describes a single class and its methods. Although, in some cases similar classes that do not
  need a lot of documentaion are gathered together in a single chapter with a subsection for each class. For the most
  part, the documentation for each class will have a table, at the beginning, that lists the methods of the class, with
  a link to the detailed documentation for the method within that chapter or section.
</para>
<para>
  One slight deviation from that pattern is found in the <link linkend="chpDialogObject">dialog object</link> and <link
  linkend="chpDialogControlObject">dialog control object</link> chapters at the beginning of the book. These objects are
  composed of a number of base classes and mixin classes. These two chapters list the class methods, attributes, and
  instance methods that are a part of every dialog, or every dialog control object, respectively, without much
  distinction as to exactly which base, or mixin, class the method comes from. The method tables at the beginning of the
  chapters will contain links to the detailed documentation, which may be in another chapter.
</para>
<para>
  Chapters 1 and 2 contain general information that should be read, or re-read, with every new release. The rest of the
  book is wholly reference and the reader can navigate to the specific topic they are interested in. Chapter 1,
  <emphasis role="italic">About This Book</emphasis>, (this chapter,) is intended to give the reader a better
  understanding of how to use this reference. As the book is revised, how best to use the book may change. Chapter 2, a
  <link linkend="chapOverview">Brief Overview</link>, contains general infomation that all users of ooDialog should
  know. This content is dynamic. In particular there is a section on the <link linkend="sctCurrentRelease">current
  release</link> that will contain important information the user should be aware of in the new release. The chapter
  also contains a section on <link linkend="sctGeneralOODialog">common concepts</link> that all ooDialog programmers
  should be aware of. As new features are added, or new misconceptions come to light, this information is also likely to
  change over time.
</para>
</section>

<section id="relinf"><title>Related Information</title>
<para><citetitle>Open Object Rexx: Programming Guide</citetitle></para>
<para><citetitle>Open Object Rexx: Reference</citetitle></para>
</section>

<section id="syndia"><title>How to Read the Syntax Diagrams</title>
<para>
  Throughout this book, syntax is described using the structure defined below. This is similar to, but slightly
  different than, the IBM syntax diagrams used in other ooRexx reference documentation.  The author is calling these
  diagrams <emphasis role="italic">simplified railroad tracks</emphasis>. It primarily strives to limit all diagrams to
  2 lines, and does away with much of the complexity of true IBM railroad tracks. The body of text following the
  syntax diagrams will resolve any ambiguities in the diagram.
</para>
<note><title>Note</title><para>
  Not all syntax diagrams may be converted to the simplified railroad tracks at this time.
</para></note>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
  Read the syntax diagrams from left to right, from top to bottom, following the path of the line.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>&gt;&gt;---</computeroutput> symbol indicates the beginning of a statement.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>---&gt;</computeroutput> symbol indicates that the statement syntax is continued on the next
  line. In most cases statement continuation is avoided.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>&gt;---</computeroutput> symbol indicates that a statement is continued from the previous line.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>---&gt;&lt;</computeroutput> symbol indicates the end of a statement.
</para>
<para>
  Diagrams of syntactical units other than complete statements start with the <computeroutput>&gt;---</computeroutput>
  symbol and end with the  <computeroutput>---&gt;</computeroutput> symbol.
</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Required items appear on the horizontal line (the main path).

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>-STATEMENT--required_item------------------------------------><


]]>
</programlisting>
</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
  Optional items appear below the main path.

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>-STATEMENT--+---------------+--------------------------------><
              +-optional_item-+


]]>
</programlisting>
</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>
  In this reference, the syntax being presented is the syntax for method invocations and function calls. The diagrams
  show the method, or function, names and their arguments.  For method invocations, the section the method is included
  in, and / or the text itself, make it clear as to which class the method belongs to.  The arguments to the method or
  function are enclosed in parenthesis and seperated by commas.  The arguments are represented by appropriate variable
  names and these variable names are then described in the text for the method.  When arguments are optional, the
  default value and or behavior if the argument is omitted is also described in the text.  In all cases, the text rather
  than the syntax diagram should be considered definitive.
</para>
<para>
  The following example shows the described syntax:
</para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

>>--createFontEx(--fontName-+--------------+--+---------------+--)-------------><
                            +-,-pointSize--+  +-,-additional--+


]]>
</programlisting>
</section>

&gethelp;

</chapter>
