<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooDialog User Guide XML file.
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2011-2011, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<chapter id="chapOne"><title>In The Beginning</title>
<indexterm><primary>overview</primary></indexterm>
<para>
  The whole purpose of ooDialog is to enable ooRexx developers to provide users with 
  a GUI (graphical user interface). A GUI is a collection of windows. Each window contains a 
  number of controls, such as entry fields, push buttons, list boxes, and so forth. The user 
  keys data into controls (e.g. types into an entry field) or manipulates controls with a mouse  
  (e.g. selects an item in a listbox). Some of these actions invoke application code which in turn
  makes some change to the window, causes some other action such as data access, or both.   
</para>
<para>
  Now, there are three areas of concern in designing an ooDialog application:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Designing the appearance of the window</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Designing the desired user interactions with the window</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Designing the code that implements both appearance and interactions</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
  And there are three corresponding areas of implementation concern:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Laying out the window</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Implementing the actions requested by users of a window</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Providing the results of those actions to the user on the window.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
  This document does not pretend to be a guide to best practice in the areas of design, although 
  it tries to conform with good design principles. However, this document 
  <emphasis role="italic">does</emphasis> aim to familiarise readers with the essentials of 
  ooDialog application implementation.  
</para>
<para>  
  So, before starting the first exercise, please make sure that you have downloaded and installed the 
  latest versions of ooRexx and also ooDialog. Please also run one or more of the samples in 
  ooRexx Samples --> ooDialog to ensure that your installation is properly completed.  
</para>
<section id="sctGettingStarted"><title>Getting Started</title>
<para>
  The first exercise creates and displays a blank window with the title "Hello World!". Try it - find "Exercise01.rex" 
  in the "Sample Code\Exercise01" folder, and double-click it. You should see this:
<!--
<imagedata>
  <figure id="fig01"><title>Exercise01 Result</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Exercise01\Exercise01-Image1.jpg" scale="70">
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</imagedata>  
-->
</para>
<para>
  The Command Prompt window that appears with the "Hello World" window is irrelevant, and later we'll find out how to dispense with it. 
  But now, let's look at the "Hello World" code (excluding the comments that are in the file):  
</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>
    First, the program that does the work : 
    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      dlg = .MyDialog~new
      dlg~execute("SHOWTOP", IDI_DLG_OOREXX)
      ]]>
    </programlisting>
    The first statement creates an instance of the class <emphasis role="italic">MyDialog</emphasis>, and assigns the instance to the 
    variable <emphasis role="italic">dlg</emphasis> (the <emphasis role="italic">MyDialog</emphasis> class is defined in the third part of the code). 
    The second statement invokes the <emphasis role="italic">execute</emphasis> method of <emphasis role="italic">MyDialog</emphasis>, and it is this 
    that displays the window.
    </para>
    <para>
    Note that the usual naming conventions are observed: upper camel case for classes (e.g. <computeroutput>MyDialog</computeroutput>and lower camel case for 
    variables (including of course instance variables - e.g. <computeroutput>dlg</computeroutput>).    
    </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>
    Second, the directive to ooRexx to use ooDialog:    
    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      ::requires "ooDialog.cls"
      ]]>
    </programlisting>
    This one directive allows all the classes defined by ooDialog (including <emphasis role="italic">UserDialog</emphasis>) to be accessible to our program. 
    If this statement is absent, then the following error appears on the initiating comand prompt:  
    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
      16 *-* ::class 'MyDialog' subclass UserDialog
      Error 98 running ... Exercise01\Exercise01.rex line 16: Execution error 
      Error 98.909:  Class "USERDIALOG" not found
      ]]>
    </programlisting>
    Note that it's <computeroutput>UserDialog</computeroutput> (see next bullet) that's not found. 
    This is because the <computeroutput>::requires ooDialog.cls</computeroutput> statement not only says we're using ooDialog, but also provides 
    access to all the classes provided <emphasis role="italic">by</emphasis> ooDialog. Later, we'll see a further use  
    for the <computeroutput>::requires</computeroutput> directive.  
  </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>
    Finally, there's the definition of the class <emphasis role="italic">MyDialog</emphasis>: 
    <![CDATA[
    ::class MyDialog subclass UserDialog		
    ::method init
      forward class (super) continue	 
      self~create(30, 30, 257, 123, "Hello World", "CENTER")
    ]]>
    The first line defines a class called <computeroutput>MyDialog</computeroutput> as a subclass of 
    the ooDialog-provided class <computeroutput>UserDialog</computeroutput>
    <footnote><para>See Chapter 7 of the ooDialog Reference for full details.</para></footnote>
    Among other things, <emphasis role="italic">UserDialog</emphasis> enables the programmer to define the window layout in code. 
    This can get cumbersome in more advanced dialogs, and later we'll meet a simpler way of defining a more realistic window layout.
    </para>
    <para>
    The second line defines the <emphasis role="italic">init</emphasis> method, and the third line calls the superclass which does 
    the heavy work of creating the window.
    <footnote><para>See Chapter 3 of the ooDialog Reference manual.</para></footnote>
    This is supplemented by the last line, where the <computeroutput>create</computeroutput> message is sent to 
    <computeroutput>self</computeroutput> and hence to <computeroutput>UserDialog</computeroutput>. This method defines the "template" to 
    be used - that is, the layout of the window - in this case the position and size of the "Hello World" window, as well as the text to 
    be dispayed in the window's title bar.<footnote><para>See Chapter 7 of the Windows ooDialog Reference.</para></footnote>
    </para>
    <para>Finally, this instance of the <computeroutput>MyDialog</computeroutput> class having been set up properly, the window is 
    actually surfaced (made visible) by the <emphasis role="italic">execute</emphasis> message (handled by MyDialog's superclass)
    sent by the second statement in the first part of the program (see above).  
    </para>    
   </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
  
</section>

<section id="someID"><title>Visible Bahaviour</title>
<para>
  Text.
</para>
</section>

<section id="someOtherID"><title>Some Other Title</title>
<para>
  Text.
</para>
</section>


</chapter>
