<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section>
	<title>Document Conventions</title>
	 <para>
		This manual uses several conventions to highlight certain words and phrases and draw attention to specific pieces of information.
	</para>
	 <section>
		<title>Typographic Conventions</title>
		 <para>
			Typographic conventions are used to call attention to specific words and phrases. These conventions, and the circumstances they apply to, are as follows.
		</para>

		 <para>
			<literal>Mono-spaced Bold</literal> is used to highlight literal strings, class names, or inline code examples.  For example:
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				The <classname>Class</classname> class comparison methods return &true; or &false;, the result of performing the comparison operation.
			</para>
			<para>
				This method is exactly equivalent to <code>subWord(</code><emphasis role="italic">n</emphasis><code>, 1)</code>.
			</para>
		</blockquote>

		 <para>
			<methodname>Mono-spaced Normal</methodname> denotes method names or source code in programlistings set off as separate examples.
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				This method has no effect on the action of any <methodname>hasEntry</methodname>, <methodname>hasIndex</methodname>, <methodname>items</methodname>, <methodname>remove</methodname>, or <methodname>supplier</methodname> message sent to the collection.
			</para>
			<para>
				<programlisting>
-- reverse an array
a = .Array~of("one", "two", "three", "four", "five")

-- five, four, three, two, one
aReverse = .CircularQueue~new(a~size)~appendAll(a)~makeArray("lifo")
</programlisting>
			</para>
		</blockquote>

		 <para>
			<emphasis role="italic">Proportional Italic</emphasis> is used for method and function variables and arguments.
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				A supplier loop specifies one or two control variables, <emphasis role="italic">index</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="italic">item</emphasis>, which receive a different value on each repetition of the loop.
			</para>
			<para>
				Returns a string of length <emphasis role="italic">length</emphasis> with <emphasis role="italic">string</emphasis> centered in it and with <emphasis role="italic">pad</emphasis> characters added as necessary to make up length.
			</para>
		</blockquote>
	</section>

	 <section>
		<title>Notes and Warnings</title>
		 <para>
			Finally, we use three visual styles to draw attention to information that might otherwise be overlooked.
		</para>

		 <note>
			<title>Note</title>
			 <para>
				Notes are tips, shortcuts or alternative approaches to the task at hand. Ignoring a note should have no negative consequences, but you might miss out on a trick that makes your life easier.
			</para>
		</note>

		 <important>
			<title>Important</title>
			 <para>
				Important boxes detail things that are easily missed, like mandatory initialization. Ignoring a box labeled 'Important' will not cause data loss but may cause irritation and frustration.
			</para>
		</important>

		 <warning>
			<title>Warning</title>
			 <para>
				Warnings should not be ignored. Ignoring warnings will most likely cause data loss.
			</para>
		</warning>

	</section>

</section>


