<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section id="helpGettingHelp"><title>Getting Help and Submitting Feedback</title>
<para>The Open Object Rexx Project has a number of methods to obtain help and submit feedback for ooRexx and the
extension packages that are part of ooRexx. These methods, in no particular order of preference, are listed
below.</para>

<section><title>The Open Object Rexx SourceForge Site</title>
<para>Open Object Rexx utilizes SourceForge to house its source repositories,
mailing lists and other project features at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/projects/oorexx"></ulink>.
ooRexx uses the Developer and User mailing lists at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/mailman"></ulink>
for discussions concerning ooRexx.
The ooRexx user is most likely to get timely replies from one of these mailing lists.
</para>
<para>
Here is a list of some of the most useful facilities provided by SourceForge.
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry id="helpDevelList"><term>The Developer Mailing List</term>
<listitem><para>Subscribe to the oorexx-devel mailing list at
<ulink url="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/oorexx-devel"></ulink>
to discuss ooRexx project development activities and future interpreter enhancements.
You can find its archive of past messages at
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum_name=oorexx-devel"></ulink>.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry id="helpUsersList"><term>The Users Mailing List</term>
<listitem><para>Subscribe to the oorexx-users mailing list at
<ulink url="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/oorexx-users"></ulink>
to discuss how to use ooRexx.
It also supports a historical archive of past messages.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>The Announcements Mailing List</term>
<listitem><para>Subscribe to the oorexx-announce mailing list at
<ulink url="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/oorexx-announce"></ulink>
to receive announcments of significant ooRexx project events.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>The Bug Mailing List</term>
<listitem><para>Subscribe to the oorexx-bugs mailing list at
<ulink url="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/oorexx-bugs"></ulink>
to monitor changes in the ooRexx bug tracking system.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Bug Reports</term>
<listitem><para>You can view ooRexx bug reports at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/bugs"></ulink>.
To be able to create new bug reports, you will need to first register for a
SourceForge userid at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/user/registration"></ulink>.
When reporting a bug, please try to provide as much information as possible
to help developers determine the cause of the issue.
Sample program code that can reproduce your problem will make it easier to
debug reported problems.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Documentation Feedback</term>
<listitem><para>You can submit feedback for, or report errors in, the documentation at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/documentation"></ulink>.
Please try to provide as much information in a documentation report as possible. In addition
to listing the document and section the report concerns, direct quotes of the text will help the
developers locate the text in the source code for the document. (Section numbers are generated
when the document is produced and are not available in the source code itself.) Suggestions as
to how to reword or fix the existing text should also be included.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Request For Enhancement</term>
<listitem><para>You can new suggest ooRexx features or enhancements at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/feature-requests"></ulink>.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Patch Reports</term>
<listitem><para>If you create an enhancement patch for ooRexx please
post the patch at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/patches"></ulink>.
Please provide as much information in the patch report
as possible so that the developers can evaluate the enhancement
as quickly as possible.</para>
<para>Please do not post bug fix patches here, instead you should open a bug report at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/bugs"></ulink>
and attach the patch to it.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>The ooRexx Forums</term>
<listitem><para>The ooRexx project maintains a set of forums that anyone
may contribute to or monitor. They are located at
<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/p/oorexx/discussion"></ulink>.
There are currently three forums available: Help, Developers and Open
Discussion. In addition, you can monitor the forums via email.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section><title>The Rexx Language Association Mailing List</title>

<para>The Rexx Language Association maintains a forum at
<ulink url="https://groups.io/g/rexxla-members/topics"></ulink>.
<!-- according to https://rexxla.github.io/ there is currently no archive:
  2020-07-05 Nabble RexxLA forum defunct
  The owner of the Nabble fora has decided to shut it down gradually. Before the
  forum was deleted, we have saved the messages. RexxLA will announce a new forum
  shortly, to interact to our mailing list over the Web.
  <ulink url="http://rexx-language-association-forum.44760.x6.nabble.com"></ulink>.
-->
</para>
</section>

<!-- groups.google.com will be read-only starting with February 22, 2024
<section><title>comp.lang.rexx Newsgroup</title>
<para>The comp.lang.rexx newsgroup at
<ulink url="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.lang.rexx"></ulink>
is a good place to obtain help from many individuals within the Rexx community.
You can obtain help on Open Object Rexx and other Rexx interpreters and tools.</para>
</section>
-->

</section>
