<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "rexxpg.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: Programming Guide XML file.
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2005-2022, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    # Portions Copyright (c) 2004, IBM Corporation. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<chapter id="meet"><title>Meet Open Object Rexx (ooRexx)</title>
<para>Rexx is a versatile, free-format language. Its simplicity makes it a good first
language for beginners. For more experienced users and computer professionals,
Rexx offers powerful functions and the ability to issue commands to several
environments.</para>

<section id="dossier"><title>The Main Attractions</title>
<indexterm><primary>Rexx</primary>
<secondary>features</secondary></indexterm>
<para>The following aspects of Rexx round out its versatility and functions.</para>

<section id="oop"><title>Object-Oriented Programming</title>
<para>Object-oriented extensions have been added to traditional Rexx, but its
existing functions and instructions have not changed. The Open Object Rexx interpreter
is an enhanced version of its predecessor with support for:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Classes, objects, and methods</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Messaging and polymorphism</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Inheritance and multiple inheritance</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>Rexx supplies the user with a base set of built-in classes providing
many useful functions.
Open Object Rexx is fully
compatible with earlier versions of Rexx that were not object-oriented.</para>
</section>

<section id="english"><title>An English-Like Language</title>
<para>To make Rexx easier to learn and use, many of its instructions are meaningful
English words. Rexx instructions are common words such as SAY,
PULL, IF...THEN...ELSE,
DO...END, and EXIT.</para>
</section>

<section id="crossplat"><title>Cross-Platform Versatility</title>
<para>Versions of ooRexx are now available for a wide variety
of platforms, and the programs you create with ooRexx will run on any
of these.
There are 32-bit and 64-bit versions that can exploit larger address spaces.
</para>
</section>

<section id="fewrule"><title>Fewer Rules</title>
<para>Rexx has relatively few rules about format. A single instruction can span
many lines, and you can include several instructions on a single line. Instructions
need not begin in a particular column and can be typed in uppercase, lowercase,
or mixed case. You can skip spaces in a line or entire lines. There is no
line numbering.</para>
</section>

<section id="interp"><title>Interpreted, Not Compiled</title>
<para>Rexx is an interpreted language. When a Rexx program runs, its language
processor reads each statement from the source file and runs it, one statement
at a time. Languages that are not interpreted must be compiled into object
code before they can be run.</para>
</section>

<section id="builtin"><title>Built-In Classes and Functions</title>
<para>Rexx has built-in classes and functions that perform various processing,
searching, and comparison operations for text and numbers and provide formatting
capabilities and arithmetic calculations.</para>
</section>

<section id="typeles"><title>Typeless Variables</title>
<indexterm><primary>typeless</primary></indexterm>
<para>Rexx regards all data
as objects of various kinds. Variables can hold any kind of object, so you
need not declare variables as strings or numbers.</para>
</section>

<section id="string"><title>String Handling</title>
<indexterm><primary>strings</primary></indexterm>
<para>Rexx includes capabilities for manipulating
character strings. This allows programs to read and separate characters, numbers,
and mixed input. Rexx performs arithmetic operations on any string that represents
a valid number, including those in exponential formats.</para>
</section>

<section id="clear"><title>Clear Error Messages and Powerful Debugging</title>
<para>Rexx displays messages with meaningful explanations when a Rexx program
encounters an error. In addition, the TRACE instruction provides a powerful
debugging tool.</para>
</section>

<section id="devtool"><title>Impressive Development Tools</title>
<para>The ooRexx places many powerful tools at
your disposal. These include
a Rexx API to other languages like C/C++ or Cobol,
OLE/ActiveX support, a mathematical functions package.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="rexxos2"><title>Rexx and the Operating System</title>
<indexterm><primary>Rexx</primary>
<secondary>and Windows</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Rexx</primary>
<secondary>and Unix</secondary></indexterm>
<para>The most important role Rexx plays is as a programming
language for Windows and Unix-based systems. A Rexx program can serve as a
script for the operating system. Using
Rexx, you can reduce long, complex, or repetitious tasks to a single command
or program.</para>
</section>

<section id="teaser"><title>A Classic Language Gets Classier</title>
<indexterm><primary>classes</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Rexx</primary>
<secondary>and object-oriented extensions</secondary></indexterm>
<para>Object-oriented extensions have been added to traditional Rexx without
changing its existing functions and instructions. So you can continue to use
Rexx's procedural instructions, and incorporate objects as you become
more comfortable with the technology. In general, your current Rexx programs
will work without change.
</para>
<indexterm><primary>objects</primary></indexterm>
<para>In object-oriented technology,
<emphasis role="italic">objects</emphasis> are used in programs to model the
real world.  Similar objects
are grouped into <emphasis role="italic">classes</emphasis>,
and the classes themselves
are arranged in hierarchies.</para>
<para>As an object-oriented programmer, you solve problems by identifying and
classifying objects related to the problem. Then you determine what actions
or behaviors are required of those objects. Finally, you write the instructions
to generate the classes, create the objects, and implement the actions. Your
main program consists of instructions that send messages to objects.</para>

<indexterm><primary>instances</primary></indexterm>
<para>A billing application, for example,
might have an Invoice class and a
Receipt class. These two classes might be
members of a Forms class. Individual invoices are
<emphasis role="italic">instances</emphasis> of the Invoice class.</para>

<figure><title>Objects in a Billing Application</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="images/BillingApplication.svg" align="center" scale="70" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<indexterm><primary>messages</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>methods</primary></indexterm>
<para>Each instance contains all the data associated with it (such as customer
name or descriptions and prices of items purchased). To get at the data, you
write instructions that send messages to the objects.
These messages activate coded actions called methods.
For an invoice object, you might need CREATE, DISPLAY,
PRINT, UPDATE, and
ERASE methods.</para>

<section id="torexx"><title>From Traditional Rexx to Open Object Rexx</title>
<indexterm><primary>Rexx</primary>
<secondary>traditional</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>strings</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>objects</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>instances</primary></indexterm>

<para>In traditional (classic) Rexx, all data was stored as strings.
The strings represented character data as well as numeric data.
From an object-oriented perspective, traditional Rexx had just one kind of object:
the string. In object-oriented terminology, each string variable is an
<emphasis role="italic">object</emphasis> that is a
reference to an instance of the String class.</para>

<indexterm><primary>messages</primary></indexterm>
<para>With
ooRexx, variables can now reference objects other than strings. In addition
to the String class, Rexx includes classes for creating arrays, queues,
streams, and many other useful objects. Additionally, you can create your own
classes that can interoperate seamlessly with the language built-in classes.
Objects in these Rexx classes
are manipulated by methods instead of traditional
functions. To activate a method, you just send a message to the object.</para>
<para>For example, instead of using the SUBSTR function on a string
variable Name, you send a SUBSTR
message to the string object. In classic
Rexx, you would do the following: </para>

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
s=substr(name,2,3)
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>In Open Object Rexx, the equivalent would be: </para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
s=name~substr(2,3)
]]>
</programlisting>

<indexterm><primary>~ (tilde, or twiddle)</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>tilde (~)</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>twiddle (~)</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>message-send operator (~)</primary></indexterm>
<para>The tilde
(<literal>~</literal>) character is the Rexx message send operator,
called <emphasis role="italic">twiddle</emphasis>.  The object receiving the message
is to the left of the twiddle. The message sent is to the right. In this example,
the Name object is sent the SUBSTR message. The numbers in parentheses <emphasis role="italic">(2,3)</emphasis>
are arguments sent as part of the message. The SUBSTR method is run for the
Name object, and the result is assigned to the
<emphasis role="italic">s</emphasis> string object.
Conceptually, you are "asking" the String object referred to by variable NAME to
give you its substring starting at character 2 for 3 characters.  Many String
operations are available as both class methods and built-in functions, but the
String class also provides many method enhancements for which there are no corresponding
built-in functions.
</para>

<indexterm><primary>string</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>stem</primary></indexterm>
<para>For
classes other than String (such as Array or
Queue), methods are provided, but not equivalent
built-in functions. For example, suppose you want to use a Rexx Array object instead
of the traditional string-based
stem variables (such as <emphasis role="italic">text.1</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic">text.2</emphasis>).
To create an array object of five elements, you would send a NEW message to
the Array class as follows: </para>

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
myarray=.array~new(5)
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>A new instance of the Array class is created and reference
to it is stored in the variable <literal>myarray</literal>.
A period and the class name identify the class, <literal>.Array</literal>.  The period tells the
interpreter to look in the Rexx environment for a class named "ARRAY".
The <literal>myarray</literal> Array object has five
elements, but the array itself is currently empty.  Items can be added using methods
defined by the Array class.</para>

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
myarray[1] = "Rick"
myarray[2] = "David"
myarray[3] = "Mark"

say myarray[1] myarray[2] myarray[3]
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>The Array class implements many more methods.  See the ooRexx reference for
details on what additional methods are provided.</para>
<para>By adding object technology
to its repertoire of traditional programming techniques, Rexx has evolved
into an object-oriented language, like Smalltalk. Rexx accommodates
the programming techniques of traditional Rexx while adding new ones. With
ooRexx, you can use the new technology as much or as little as you like,
at whatever pace you like. You can mix classic and object techniques. You
can ease into the object world gradually, building on the Rexx skills and
knowledge you already have.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="which"><title>The Object Advantage</title>
<para>If you are unsure about whether to employ Rexx's object-oriented features,
here are some tips to help you decide.</para>
<para>Object-oriented technology reinforces good programming practices,
such as hiding your data from code that does not use it (encapsulation and
polymorphism), partitioning your program in small, manageable units (classification
and data abstraction), reusing code wherever possible and changing it in one
place (inheritance and functional decomposition).</para>
<para>Other advantages often associated with object technology are: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Simplified design through modeling with objects</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Greater code reuse</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Rapid prototyping</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The higher quality of proven components</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Easier and reduced maintenance</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Cost-savings potential</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Increased adaptability and scalability</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>With ooRexx, you get the user-friendliness of Rexx in an
object-oriented environment.</para>
<para>ooRexx provides a Sockets API for Rexx.
So you can script Rexx clients and servers, and run them in the Internet.</para>
<para>ooRexx also provides access to FTP commands by means of
its RxFtp package, and the use of mathematical functions by means of its
RxMath utility package. The Sockets, FTP, and mathematical functions packages
are each supplied with separate, full documentation.</para>
</section>

<section id="next"><title>The Next Step</title>
<para>If you already know traditional Rexx and want to
go straight to the basic concepts of object-oriented programming, continue
with <xref linkend="concept" />.</para>
<para>If you are unfamiliar with traditional Rexx, continue
to read <xref linkend="tour" />.</para>
</section>
</chapter>
