<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "oodguide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooDialog User Guide XML file
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2013-2022, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->

<!-- Chapter01 - Introduction				  	  v01-00 03Jan13

     Changes:
     v01-00 03Jan13: First version.
-->

<chapter id="chap01"><title>About This Book</title>
<para>This book provides a general user's guide to the ooDialog framework, and is a companion book
    to the <emphasis role="italic">ooDialog Reference</emphasis>. The ooDialog framework is part of
    the Open Object Rexx distribution on the <trademark class="registered">Windows</trademark>
    platform. The <emphasis role="italic">User Guide</emphasis> discusses the general ideas needed
    to use the framework to its best advantage. </para>

<section id="whoshoulduse"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title>
<para>This book is intended for Open Object Rexx programmers who want to design graphical user
      interfaces for their applications using ooDialog. It is intended to paint a broader picture of
      how to use ooDialog than the a purely reference manual can. Readers will gain a better
      understanding of the general concepts used in the ooDialog framework. </para>
<para>In addition to ooDialog concepts, some discussion of how the underlying Windows dialogs and
      controls behave and are normally programmed is included. The will give the reader some idea of
      what can and can not be done using ooDialog. Knowing some of the inherent capabilities and
      restrictions of the operating system allows ooRexx programmers to better design their
      programs. </para>
</section>

<section id="bookstructure"><title>How This Book is Structured</title>
<para>This book takes the reader through a series of exercises, each exercise building on the
      previous one. The final exercise will complete a simple Sales Order Management application.
      The intent is not to provide a realistic application, but rather to illustrate the use of the
      main ooDialog features while building a working if simplistic application. While not
      production-strength, this sample application will include a number of different dialogs,
      together with, in later chapters, a sample model-view framework of the kind often used to
      provide the application programmer with greater development simplicity. </para>
<para>In the course of these exercises, various key ooDialog concepts are discussed. However, this
      book is not, and is not intended to be, a technical reference for ooDialog. Rather it is an
      introduction to ooDialog. Its intent is merely to familiarize the reader with the basics. The
      reader is assumed to be reasonably familiar with the object-orientation concepts, and also
      with programming using ooRexx. </para>
<para>Completed code for each exercise is available from the
        <computeroutput>samples</computeroutput> sub-directory of the ooRexx installation directory.
      Specifically, the code for the exercises will be in
        <computeroutput>samples\oodialog\userGuide\exercises</computeroutput>. Note that exercise
      numbers are aligned with chapter numbers. Thus the first exercise, introduced in Chapter 2, is
      found in the folder <computeroutput>Exercise02</computeroutput>. </para>
</section>
</chapter>
