<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "readme.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: Release Notes XML File
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2005-2024, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    # Portions Copyright (c) 2004, IBM Corporation. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->

<section><title>Windows Requirements, Installation and Configuration</title>

<section><title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
  Approximately 52 MB free disk space is needed for a complete installation.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  12 MB free disk space for the core interpreter.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  25 MB free disk space for online documentation.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  15 MB free disk space for all samples.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  0.5 MB free disk space for the API headers and libraries.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  Any hardware capable of running the supported Windows operating systems is sufficient.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section><title>Software Requirements</title>
<para>
  On Windows, the ooRexx development team is committed to supporting all active versions of Windows. That is, versions of
  Windows that Microsoft has not declared end of life. For ooRexx version 5.0.0, the officially supported version of Window
  are Windows Vista through Windows 10. The team will not <emphasis role="italic">purposively</emphasis> make changes to
  prevent ooRexx from running on versions of Windows that have reached end of life. However, the team is more interested in
  supporting newer versions of Windows than they are in supporting out of date operating systems. Versions of Windows that
  are no longer supported by Microsoft, are officially not supported by ooRexx.
</para>
<para>
  The following lists the versions of Windows that ooRexx 5.0.0 has been consistently tested on by the development team:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Windows 10</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
  The following lists the version of Windows that the development team is committed to supporting. However, ooRexx 5.0.0 has
  not been well tested by the development team on these versions of Windows. Testing has been done by committed users of
  ooRexx.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Windows Vista</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Windows 7</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Windows 8</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Windows 8.1</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section><title>Installation and Configuration Information</title>

<section id="sectPreInstallation"><title>Windows Pre-Installation Notes</title>
<para>
  Open Object Rexx cannot coexist with IBM Object REXX. If IBM Object REXX is installed on the system
  you must first uninstall it.
</para>
<para>
  If a previous version of ooRexx is installed, you <emphasis role="italic">should</emphasis> uninstall
  it. If two different versions of ooRexx are installed on the same system, the results are not
  predictable and the interpreter will <emphasis role="italic">not</emphasis> work correctly. You could
  install over the top of the existing installation, but that is not recommended and is not supported.
</para>
<para>
  A previous version of ooRexx can be uninstalled (<xref linkend="sectWindowsUninstall" />) before
  starting the new installation. However, the uninstall does not have to be done as a separate step. When
  the installation program is started it will detect a previous version of ooRexx and offer to uninstall
  it at that time.
</para>

<warning><title>Warning</title>
<para>
  If a previous Windows install exists and is not the same addressing mode (32 or 64) as the version of ooRexx about to be
  installed, there are potential problems when the uninstaller is launched from the installer automatically. In this case it
  is <emphasis role="bold">strongly</emphasis> advised that the uninstallation program be run first to completely uninstall
  the current version of ooRexx, and then the new installer be run.
</para>
</warning>

<para>
  ooRexx should be installed by a user with administrator rights. On Vista and later this is a requirement.
  There are several installation
  steps that can only be performed with administrator rights. They are:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>
  The subdirectory that ooRexx is installed into is added to the System PATH environment variable.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  The environment variable REXX_HOME is set for all users.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  The file type (ftype) <computeroutput>REXXScript</computeroutput> is defined for the interpreter
  executable and the file extension <computeroutput>.rex</computeroutput> is associated (assoc) with the
  <computeroutput>REXXScript</computeroutput> file type.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  The file extension <computeroutput>.rex</computeroutput> is added to the System PATHEXT environment
  variable.
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
<note><para>
  On Vista when a user starts the installation program, the user is prompted for an administrator
  password to continue. It is not necessary to actually be logged in as administrator when the
  installation is started.
</para></note>
<para>
  It is important that if ooRexx is installed by a user with administrator rights, that ooRexx is
  uninstalled by a user with administrator rights. Otherwise, the installation steps described above,
  including removal of rxapi as a service, will not be undone when ooRexx is uninstalled.
</para>
<para>
  ooRexx is compiled both as 32-bit application and as a native 64-bit application. The native 64-bit
  application can not be installed on a 32-bit version of Windows. Either the 32-bit or the 64-bit ooRexx
  can be installed on a 64-bit version of Windows. However, to take full advantage of both the operating
  system and ooRexx, the user should install the 64-bit version of ooRexx on a 64-bit version of Windows.
  The installation programs for the two types of ooRexx are clearly labelled:
  <computeroutput>ooRexx-5.0.0.windows.x86_32.exe</computeroutput> and
  <computeroutput>ooRexx-5.0.0.windows.x86_64.exe</computeroutput>.
</para>
</section>

<section><title>Running the Installation Program on Windows</title>
<para>
  Before starting the installation, review the pre-installation (<xref
  linkend="sectPreInstallation" />) notes if you have not already done so.
</para>
<para>
  The ooRexx installation program is a typical Windows installation program. Download the installation
  program for your operating system. From Windows Explorer double-click the appropriate installation
  package: <computeroutput>ooRexx-5.0.0.windows.x86_32.exe</computeroutput> or
  <computeroutput>ooRexx-5.0.0.windows.x86_64.exe</computeroutput>. Follow the prompts in the installation dialog.
  Naturally, the program can also be run from a console window by typing the executable name at the
  command prompt.
</para>
<note><para>
  If a previous version of ooRexx is installed and the rxapi process is running, the user will be
  prompted to halt the process. The process <emphasis role="italic">must</emphasis> be halted to properly
  install the new version. If necessary, (because a Rexx program is running in the background and you are
  worried about possible data loss,) cancel the installation and take the appropriate steps to halt
  the process cleanly.  If, on the other hand, you somehow trick the installation program to continue
  without halting the rxapi process, you will most likely end up with a corrupt installation of ooRexx.
</para></note>
<para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Unattended installation</emphasis>. The Windows installation program can be run
  from the command line with no user input. This is done by using the <computeroutput>/S</computeroutput>
  option. Note that in this mode default values are used for all options other than the installation
  directory. This mode can be used to script automatic installs or multiple installs on different
  machines. From a script, or from the command line, enter the installation program name followed by the
  <computeroutput>/S</computeroutput> parameter, and the <computeroutput>/D</computeroutput> parameter if
  the default installation directory should be changed:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>/S : Silent mode</term>
<listitem><para>
  This will install ooRexx without any user intervention using default values for all options.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>/D : Default directory</term>
<listitem><para>
  The default installation directory, (C:\Program Files\ooRexx), can be changed using this switch. This
  must be the last parameter used in the command line and must not contain any quotes, even if the path
  contains spaces. For example:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
ooRexx-5.0.0.windows.x86_64.exe /S /D=C:\Program Files\Interpreters\ooRexx
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section id="sectWindowsUninstall"><title>Windows Uninstall Information</title>
<para>
  Select "Programs and Features" from the Control Panel, then select "Open Object Rexx" and select "Remove".
</para>
<para>
  Alternatively, the ooRexx installation places a menu item in the program folder that can be used to
  uninstall. Select "Start->All Programs->Open Object Rexx->Uninstall ooRexx". This is
  functionally equivalent to using "Add Remove Programs".
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section><title>Running Open Object Rexx as a Child Process of a Service on Windows</title>
<para>
  <computeroutput>rxapi</computeroutput> in its role as the memory manager for ooRexx can share out some
  resources among all the ooRexx processes to enable global functions, system exits, subcommand handlers,
  and global queues. If you start ooRexx from a service, two or more processes might run under different
  user accounts. Therefore it is required that the memory manager is not protected and can be accessed by
  every user. This means that ooRexx global data is system global and unsecured.
</para>
<para>
  Note that starting ooRexx from a service is different than installing
  <computeroutput>rxapi</computeroutput> as a service.
</para>
<para>
  If you want ooRexx to be started from a service, ooRexx must be installed as a common program or you
  must modify the system path manually to include the directory where ooRexx has been installed.
</para>
<para>
  If you are writing a service that calls RexxStart(), ensure that the SERVICE_INTERACTIVE_PROCESS flag
  is set for your service. To prevent access violations, use a NULL security descriptor and assign it to
  your service process.
</para>
</section>

<section><title>Open Object Rexx and Other Rexx Interpreters</title>
<para>
  If you have other Rexx interpreters installed, you may have to set the PATH manually because ooRexx and
  the other Rexx interpreters may both use the name "rexx" for invoking the interpreter.
  Interpreter error messages that begin with "Rexx:" indicate that another Rexx interpreter
  was called instead of ooRexx. You can verify which Rexx interpreter is running either by the form of
  the error messages, by running <computeroutput>rexxtry.rex</computeroutput> and executing SAY VERSION,
  or by invoking <computeroutput>rexx -v</computeroutput>, which then should display information about
  the Rexx interpreter that is invoked. If no information is displayed, it is not ooRexx. If you don't
  want the other Rexx interpreter to be invoked, you should remove it from the PATH, delete it, or rename
  <computeroutput>rexx.exe</computeroutput> in the installation directory to
  <computeroutput>orx.exe</computeroutput> and use <computeroutput>orx</computeroutput> to invoke the
  interpreter.
</para>
</section>

<section><title>Exploring Open Object Rexx</title>
<para>
  Once you have installed the ooRexx files you can run Rexx scripts by issuing the command
  <computeroutput>rexx</computeroutput> followed by the name of your Rexx script at the command prompt.
  In addition, if you installed ooRexx as recommended, a file type has been associated with the
  <computeroutput>.rex</computeroutput> extension which allows you to just type the name of your script,
  without the extension, to run it. For example, if your program was named
  <computeroutput>addressBook.rex</computeroutput>, the file association will allow you to execute the
  program as follows:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
C:\work.ooRexx>addressBook
]]>
</programlisting>
  An execution of the program might look like this:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
C:\work.ooRexx>addressBook
ooRexx Address Lookup, version 1.1.0
  Look up address for: gatch

Tom Gatch
3245 Westfield Dr
Mission Bay CA 92110

  Look up another address? [y/n] n

C:\work.ooRexx>
]]>
</programlisting>
  To interactively try Object Rexx statements, enter <computeroutput>rexx rexxtry.rex</computeroutput> on
  the command line. Enter <computeroutput>exit</computeroutput> to end the program.
</para>
<para>
  To help you explore programming in Open Object Rexx, the following generic sample programs are
  provided:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>ccreply.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>concurrent program using REPLY
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>complex.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>complex number class
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>drives.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>demonstrates the usage of Sys functions
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>factor.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>factorial program
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>greply.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>concurrent program using WAIT and NOWAIT
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>guess.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>a guessing game
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>ktguard.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>concurrent program using START and GUARD
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>makestring.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>demonstrated the usage of the makestring method
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>month.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>displays a calendar for the month of January
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>philfork.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>program that demonstrates Open Object Rexx concurrency
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>pipe.cls</varname></term>
<listitem><para>a library of pipeline classes
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>properties.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>shows usage of the .Properties class and some Sys functions
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>qdate.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>date query program
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>qtime.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>time query program
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>rexxcps.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>measures Rexx performance
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>scclient.rex scserver.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>a client / server demonstration using the .Socket class from socket.cls
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>semcls.cls</varname></term>
<listitem><para>semaphore class
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>sfclient.rex sfserver.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>a client / server demonstration using the external rxsock library
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>stack.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>program that uses a stack class
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>usecomp.cls</varname></term>
<listitem><para>an implementation of a complex number class (see note below)
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>usepipe.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>program that uses the pipeline implementation (see note below)
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<note><para>
  To run these programs, you must either add the <computeroutput>samples</computeroutput> directory to
  the PATH or execute them directly from the <computeroutput>samples</computeroutput> directory.
</para></note>

<para>
  To help you explore using the Windows <computeroutput>WinSystm.cls</computeroutput>, the following
  sample programs are provided:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>deskicon.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>AddDesktopIcon method of the WindowsProgramManager class
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>desktop.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>uses the WindowsProgramManager class
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>displayAnyMenu.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  Displays the menu hierarchy for a window that the user picks. The example uses a mixture of ooDialog
  and WinSystm.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>displayWindowTree.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  Allows the user to pick an open top-level window and then displays the window hierarchy for that window.
  The program uses both ooDialog and WinSystm classes.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>eventlog.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>uses the WindowsEventLog class
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>getTheWindow.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  This example shows how to find a window without using the exact window title.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>menuCalc.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  Uses the MenuObject class to display the menu hierarchy of the Windows Calculator application.  The
  menu hierarchy for both the Calculator's standard view and its scientific view are printed to the
  console.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>menuNotepad.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  Uses the MenuObject class to displays the hierarchy of the Notepad menu.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>quickCalc.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  Demonstrates how to control an application programmatically using the winsystm classes.  Does some
  simple calculations using the Windows Calculator application. This program is similar to usewmgr.rex
  but more simple to better show what is going on.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>quickShowAllMenus.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  Uses the windowsSystem.frm package to print out a menu outline of every open window that has a menu.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>registry.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>uses the WindowsRegistry class
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>usewmgr.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>program that uses the WindowsManager class
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>windowsSystem.frm</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  A collection of public routines and classes to help work with the winsystm.cls package. This is an
  example of how to extract common function into a package, and then use the package to help in writing
  similar programs.  A number of the sample programs that use winsystm.cls make use of this framework.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><varname>writeWithNotepad.rex</varname></term>
<listitem><para>
  Uses classes in winsystm.cls to automate the Windows Notepad application. This is a subset of the
  usewmgr.rex program designed to be a little easier to understand.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>
  The directory <computeroutput>samples\ole\</computeroutput> and its subdirectories contain a number of
  samples for the ooRexx OLE / ActiveX interface. The sample programs contain comments to help with
  learning to use the OLEObject class.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>samples\oodialog</computeroutput> and it subdirectories contain a relatively large
  number of example programs that demonstrate the use of OODialog. A subset of these examples can be
  launched from the ooRexx Program folder in the Start Menu. "Start->All Programs->Open Object
  Rexx->ooRexx Samples->ooDialog"
</para>
<para>
  There are several examples provided to help with programming external function libraries using the
  ooRexx native API. These samples are located under the <computeroutput>samples\api</computeroutput>
  directory, along with two read me files:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>sample\api\readme.txt</computeroutput></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>sample\api\callrxnt</computeroutput></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>sample\api\callrxwn</computeroutput></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>sample\api\rexxexit</computeroutput></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>sample\api\wpipe</computeroutput></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>sample\api\wpipe\readme.txt</computeroutput></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
  Several of the API samples can be launched from the ooRexx Program folder in the Start Menu.
  "Start->All Programs->Open Object Rexx->ooRexx Samples->API"
</para>
</section>
</section>
