<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "oodialog.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooDialog Reference XML file.
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2012-2025, Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<chapter id="clsToolTip" xreflabel="ToolTip"><title>ToolTip Controls</title>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary></indexterm>
<para>
  Tooltip controls are pop-up windows that display text. Typically the text describes a <emphasis
  role="italic">tool</emphasis>. A <emphasis role="italic">tool</emphasis> is either a window or an application defined area
  within a window. Conceptually, a ToolTip is a dialog control that contains tools. Each ToolTip can contain any number of
  <emphasis role="italic">tools</emphasis>. A ToolTip with no added tool will never display text. In ooDialog, the tools
  added to a ToolTip are usually other dialog controls.
</para>
<para>
  ToolTips are hidden most of the time. They appear automatically, or pop up, when the user pauses the mouse pointer over a
  tool. The ToolTip appears near the pointer and disappears when the user clicks a mouse button or moves the pointer away
  from the tool.
</para>
<para>
  ToolTip controls can display single or multiple lines of text. They can have square or rounded corners. They might or might
  not have a stem that points to the tools like a cartoon balloon. ToolTip text can be stationary or can move with the mouse
  pointer, these are called tracking ToolTips. Stationary text can be displayed adjacent to a tool or it can be displayed
  over a tool, which is referred to as in-place ToolTips. Standard ToolTips are stationary, display a single line of text,
  have square corners, and have no stem pointing to the tool.
</para>
<para>
  The <computeroutput>ToolTip</computeroutput> class provides methods to work with and manipulate the underlying Windows
  ToolTip dialog control which it represents. It is a concrete subclass of the dialog control <link
  linkend="chpDialogControlObject">object</link> and therefore has all methods of the dialog control object.
</para>
<para>
  The following classes, and methods from other classes, are needed, or are useful, when working with ToolTip controls:
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">ToolInfo Class</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <link linkend="clsToolInfo">ToolInfo</link> class represents the information a ToolTip control uses to manage the
    <emphasis role="italic">tools</emphasis> it contains. The attributes of a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput>
    object represent the information specific to a single tool within a ToolTip. Many of the methods of the
    <computeroutput>ToolTip</computeroutput> class require a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object as an argument,
    or return information using a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Creation:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Unlike most other types of dialog controls, a ToolTip can not be added to a dialog <link
    linkend="ovvDialogTemplate">template</link>. ToolTips are created dynamically using the <link
    linkend="tmthCreateToolTip">createToolTip</link> method. ToolTips can only be created after the underlying Windows dialog
    exists. Therefore, ToolTips can not be created in the <xref linkend="mthDefineDialog"/> method of the <link
    linkend="clsUserDialog">UserDialog</link> class.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Instantiation:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Use the <link linkend="tmthNewToolTip">newToolTip</link> method of the <link linkend="chpDialogObject">dialog</link>
    object to retrieve a Rexx ToolTip object.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Event Notification</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    To connect the <link linkend="ovvEvents">event</link> notifications sent by the underlying ToolTip control to a method in
    the Rexx dialog object use the <link linkend="mthConnectToolTipEvent">connectToolTipEvent</link> method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>


<section id="sctToolIdentification"><title>Tool Identification</title>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>tool identification</secondary></indexterm>

<para>
  Each ToolTip can contain more than one <emphasis role="italic">tool</emphasis>. Because of this, the ToolTip control
  needs a way of uniquely identifying each individual tool. In the operating system, each tool is identified using a
  combination of a window <link linkend="defHandle">handle</link> and an ID. The ID however, can be either another window
  handle or a unique number. When the ID is a number, the number is similar to a <xref linkend="defResourceId"/>.
</para>
<para>
  For the operating system, the first part of the 2-part identifier is the handle of the window that the ToolTip will send
  notifications to. The second part of the identifier can be a second window handle, if the ToolTip is going to subclass that
  window, or an unique number if the ToolTip is not going to subclass the tool. This may seem somewhat complicated to the
  Rexx programmer, especially if the programmer has little experience with the underlying details of programming dialog
  controls.
</para>
<para>
  The ooDialog framework attempts to simplify this somewhat by allowing the Rexx programmer to identify an unique tool in
  several different ways. For the most common use of ToolTips, identifying a tool is simple and can be done with one Rexx
  object. However, ooDialog also supplies the means needed to identify a tool when more advanced use of ToolTips is desired.
</para>
<para>
  This documentation refers to a tool identifier as a <emphasis role="italic">Rexx object combination</emphasis>. This can be
  a combination of two Rexx objects, but quite often only one object is needed to identify a tool.
  <computeroutput>ToolTip</computeroutput> methods that require a tool to be identified, have a required argument, a <emphasis
  role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> argument, followed by a second optional argument a <emphasis
  role="italic">toolID</emphasis> argument. The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> argument is usually argument 1,
  followed by the <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> argument. However, in some cases the <emphasis
  role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> argument may be argument 2 followed by the <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> as
  argument 3.
</para>
<para>
  The combination of the two arguments, <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis
  role="italic">toolID</emphasis>, is always handled in the same way, which is as follows:
</para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term>if <emphasis role="italic">hwndTool</emphasis> == a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    A <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object always uniquely identifies a tool. When the <emphasis
    role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> argument is a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object that is sufficient and
    the second <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> argument is ignored.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>if <emphasis role="italic">hwndTool</emphasis> \== a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> is omitted</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    It is very common that a ToolTip tool is a dialog control. For example quite often ToolTips are used for push buttons,
    so that some label can be displayed when the user hovers the mouser over the button. ooDialog makes it easy for the
    Rexx programmer to identify this type of tool by using just the dialog control object.  When the <emphasis
    role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> argument is not a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object, and the <emphasis
    role="italic">toolID</emphasis> is omitted, then the <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> argument must be a
    dialog control object. This dialog control object is the tool identifier. The ooDialog framework deduces the proper
    values to identify the tool to the operating system.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>if <emphasis role="italic">hwndTool</emphasis> \== a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> is not omitted</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This combination of identifying objects is needed when some more advanced uses of ToolTips are desired. It allows the
    programmer to specify the exact values that should be passed on to the operarting system to identify the tool.  For this
    combination, <emphasis role="italic">hwndTool</emphasis> can be either a dialog object, or a dialog control object. When
    <emphasis role="italic">hwndTool</emphasis> is a dialog object, then <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> must be
    either a dialog control object or an unique whole number. The first part of the 2-part operating system ID for the tool
    is set to the window handle of the Rexx object, the dialog window handle or the dialog control window handle.
  </para>
  <para>
    The <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> argument can be either a dialog control, or an unique non-negative whole
    number. If the <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> argument is a dialog, then <emphasis
    role="italic">toolID</emphasis> can be a dialog control or a number. However, if <emphasis
    role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> is a dialog control, the <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> must be a number.
    The second part of the 2-part operating system identifier is set to the window handle of the dialog control, if <emphasis
    role="italic">toolID</emphasis> is a dialog control. Otherwise the second part is set to the number specified. Note that
    numbers can be specified using <link linkend="defSymbolicId">symbolic</link> IDs just as other types of resource IDs are.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</section>  <!-- End Tool Identification Section -->

<section id="sctMethodsToolTip"><title>Method Table</title>
<para>
  The following table provides links to the documentation for the primary methods and attributes used in working
  with ToolTip objects, including the pertinent methods from other classes:
</para>
<table id="tblToolTipMethods" frame="all">
<title>Important ToolTip Methods</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colwidth="3*" /><colspec colwidth="8*" />
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Method</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Useful</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Classes</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="clsToolInfo">ToolInfo</link></entry>
<entry>A <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object is used to supply tool information to, or receive tool information from, the ToolTip control.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Useful</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">External Methods</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="tmthCreateToolTip">createToolTip</link></entry>
<entry>Creates the underlying Windows ToolTip control and returns an instantiated Rexx ToolTip object.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="tmthConnectToolTipEvent">connectToolTipEvent</link></entry>
<entry>Connects tool tip event notifications to a method in the Rexx dialog object</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="tmthNewToolTip">newToolTip</link></entry>
<entry>Returns the Rexx <computeroutput>ToolTip</computeroutput> object for the tool tip control with the specified ID.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Instance Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Instance Methods</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthActivate"/></entry>
<entry>Activates or deactivates this ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthAddTool"/></entry>
<entry>Adds a tool to this ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthAddToolEx"/></entry>
<entry>Adds the tool, specified by a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object, to this ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthAddToolRect"/></entry>
<entry>Adds a tool that uses a rectangular area in the dialog as its trigger point.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthAdjustRect"/></entry>
<entry>Calculates a ToolTip control's text display rectangle from its window rectangle, or the ToolTip window rectangle needed to display a specified text display rectangle.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthDelTool"/></entry>
<entry>Removes the specified tool from this ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthEnumTools"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves a <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object for the tool at the specified index.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetBubbleSize"/></entry>
<entry>Returns the width and height, as a <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object, of this ToolTip control.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetCurrentToolInfo"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves a <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object whose attributes represent the current tool in this tool tip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetDelayTime"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves one of the 3 delay times currently set for this ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetMargin"/></entry>
<entry>Returns a rectangle that describes the margins of the ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetMaxTipWidth"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves the maximum width for this ToolTip window.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetTextClsToolTip"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves the text information this ToolTip control maintains about the specified tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetTipBkColor"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves the background color for this ToolTip's window.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetTipTextColor"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves the text color fot this ToolTip's window.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetTitle"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves information concerning the title and icon of this ToolTip control.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetToolCount"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves the number of tools this ToolTip contains.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthGetToolInfo"/></entry>
<entry>Retrieves the information, as a <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object, that this tool tip control maintains about the specified tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthHasCurrentTool"/></entry>
<entry>Tests if this ToolTip has a current tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthHitTestInfoClsToolTip"/></entry>
<entry>Tests a point to determine whether it is within the bounding rectangle of a tool within the window specified and, if it is, retrieves information about the tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthManageAtypicalTool"/></entry>
<entry>Initiates the management of a ToolTip tool that is a dialog control.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthNewToolRect"/></entry>
<entry>Sets a new bounding rectangle for a tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthPop"/></entry>
<entry>Removes, hides, this ToolTip's display window.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthPopup"/></entry>
<entry>Causes this ToolTip to display at the coordinates of the last mouse message.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSetDelayTime"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the initial, pop-up, and reshow durations for this ToolTip control.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSetMargin"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the top, left, bottom, and right margins for this ToolTip window. A margin is the distance, in pixels, between the ToolTip window border and the text contained within the ToolTip window.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSetMaxTipWidth"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the maximum width, in pixels, for this ToolTip window.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSetTipBkColor"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the background color for this ToolTip window.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSetTipTextColor"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the text color for this ToolTip window.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSetTitleClsToolTip"/></entry>
<entry>Adds a title string and optionally an icon image to this ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSetToolInfo"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the information that this ToolTip control maintains for a tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthSetWindowThemeClsToolTip"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the visual style of a ToolTip control.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthTrackActivate"/></entry>
<entry>Activates or deactivates a tracking ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the position of a tracking ToolTip.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthUpdateClsToolTip"/></entry>
<entry>Forces the current tool to be redrawn.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><xref linkend="mthUpdateTipText"/></entry>
<entry>Sets the ToolTip text for a tool.</entry>
</row>
</tbody></tgroup>
</table>
</section>


<section id="tmthConnectToolTipEvent"><title>connectToolTipEvent (dialog object method)</title>
<para>
  To connect event notifications from an tool tip control use the <link
  linkend="mthConnectToolTipEvent">connectToolTipEvent</link>() method of the <link
  linkend="chpDialogObject">dialog</link> object. The basic syntax is:

<programlisting> <![CDATA[
>>--connectToolTipEvent(--id--,--event--+-----------+--+-------------+--)------><
                                        +-,-mthName-+  +-,-willReply-+
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>  <!-- End connectToolTipEvent() [EventNotification method] -->


<section id="tmthCreateToolTip"><title>createToolTip (dialog object method)</title>
<para>
  To create the underlying Windows ToolTip control use the <link linkend="mthCreateToolTip">createToolTip</link> method of
  the <link linkend="chpDialogObject">dialog</link> object. This method also returns the instantiated Rexx object that
  represents the created tool tip control. The basic syntax is:

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--createToolTip(--id--+----------+--)-------------><
                        +-,-style--+
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>  <!-- End createToolTipt() [PlainBaseDialog method] -->


<section id="tmthNewToolTip"><title>newToolTip (dialog object method)</title>
<para>
  ToolTip objects can not be instantiated by the programmer from Rexx code using the normal <emphasis
  role="italic">new</emphasis> method. Rather a ToolTip object is obtained either by using the <xref
  linkend="mthCreateToolTip"/> method or the <link linkend="mthNewToolTip">newToolTip</link> method of the dialog <link
  linkend="chpDialogObject">object</link>. The syntax for the <emphasis role="italic">newToolTip</emphasis> is:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>-newToolTip(--id--)---------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>  <!-- End newToolTip() [PlainBaseDialog method] -->


<section id="mthActivate" xreflabel="activate"><title>activate</title>
<indexterm><primary>activate</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>activate</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--activate(--+------------+--)-----------------><
               +--activate--+

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Activates or deactivates this ToolTip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single optional argument is:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term>activate [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      If true, activates this tool it, if false, deactivate this tool tip. The default if the argument is omitted is true.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    A ToolTip control can be either active or inactive. When it is active, the ToolTip text appears when the mouse pointer is
    on a tool. When it is inactive, the ToolTip text does not appear, even if the pointer is on a tool.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::activate() -->


<section id="mthAddTool" xreflabel="addTool"><title>addTool</title>
<indexterm><primary>addTool</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>addTool</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--addTool(--tool--+---------+--+---------+--+------------+--)----------------><
                    +-,-text--+  +-,-flags-+  +-,-userData-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Adds a tool to this ToolTip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>tool [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The dialog control that defines the tool being added.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>text [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Text for the tool. If omitted, or the empty string, or the string: TEXTCALLBACK, then the tool tip sends the <xref
        linkend="kywToolTipNEEDTEXT"/> notification and the program supplies the text.
      </para>
      <para>
        The length of the text must be less than 1024 characters, which includes any possible end of line (0x0D0A) sequences.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>flags [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A list of 0 or more of the following keywords separated by spaces, case is not significant. If this argument is
        omitted, the flags are set to IDISHWND SUBCLASS:
      </para>
      <para>
        <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
          <member>ABSOLUTE   </member>
          <member>CENTERTIP  </member>
          <member>IDISHWND   </member>
          <member>PARSELINKS </member>
          <member>RTLREADING </member>
          <member>SUBCLASS   </member>
          <member>TRACK      </member>
          <member>TRANSPARENT</member>
        </simplelist>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry><term>ABSOLUTE</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Positions the ToolTip window at the exact same coordinates specified by the <xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/>
            method. Without this flag the ToolTip control chooses where to display the ToolTip window based on the
            coordinates specified, which places the ToolTip close to the tool. This flag must be used with the TRACK flag.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>CENTERTIP</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Centers the ToolTip window below the tool specified by the <emphasis role="italic">tool</emphasis> argument.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>IDISHWND</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Indicates that the ID part of the tool <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification</link> is the window
            handle to the tool. If this flag is not set, the ID part is the tool's identification number. For the <emphasis
            role="italic">addTool</emphasis> method, the ooDialog framework always sets this flag, it does not need to be
            specified by the programmer. The window <link linkend="defHandle">handle</link> of the <emphasis
            role="italic">tool</emphasis> argument is always the ID part of the tool identification.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry id="kywToolTipPARSELINKS" xreflabel="PARSELINKS"><term>PARSELINKS</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Requires Common Control <xref linkend="ovvComctl32"/> version 6.0 or later.
          </para>
          <para>
            Indicates that links in the ToolTip text should be parsed.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>RTLREADING</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Indicates that the ToolTip text will be displayed in the opposite direction to the text in the parent window.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>SUBCLASS</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Indicates that the ToolTip control should subclass the tool's window to intercept messages, such as WM_MOUSEMOVE.
            If this flag is not set, the <xref linkend="mthManageAtypicalTool"/> method must be used so the mouse messages
            are forwarded to the ToolTip control. For the simple case that the <emphasis role="italic">addTool</emphasis>
            method is designed for, the <emphasis role="italic">manageAtypicalTool</emphasis> method will not work. The
            ooDialog framwork always sets this flag during the <emphasis role="italic">addTool</emphasis> method, the
            programmer does not need to include this flag.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>TRACK</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
             Positions the ToolTip window next to the tool to which it corresponds and moves the window according to
             coordinates supplied by the <xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/> method. The programmer must activate this
             type of tool using the <xref linkend="mthTrackActivate"/> method.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>TRANSPARENT</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Causes the ToolTip control to forward mouse event messages to the parent window. This is limited to mouse events
            that occur within the bounds of the ToolTip window.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>userData [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A user data value to be associated with the tool. This can be any Rexx object the programmer wants. Note that the
        value is associated with the tool, not the tool tip.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns true on success, false on error.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <emphasis role="italic">addTool</emphasis> method is intended to be a convenient method for use in the most common
    case of adding a tool.  The case where the tool is a simple dialog control. Use the <xref linkend="mthAddToolRect"/> or
    the <xref linkend="mthAddToolEx"/> methods to add a tool with characteristics that need to be more explicitly defined.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example creates a ToolTip and then adds a tool to it. The tool is defined using a push button dialog control and
    the text for the tool is specified at the time the tool is added:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  pbTest = self~newPushButton(IDC_PB_TEST)
  count  = 0
  ...

  ttTest = self~createToolTip(IDC_TT_TEST)
  ttTest~addTool(pbTest, "Push the Test button to start the regression testing.")

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::addTool() -->


<section id="mthAddToolEx" xreflabel="addToolEx"><title>addToolEx</title>
<indexterm><primary>addToolEx</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>addToolEx</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--addToolEx(--tool--)--------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Adds the specified tool to this ToolTip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>tool [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/>  object that defines the tool being added.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns true on success, false on error.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    There are a number of different attributes that can be set when adding a tool to a tool tip. The <emphasis
    role="italic">addToolEx</emphasis> method is designed to let the programmer specify any valid combination of attributes
    allowed by the operating system. To do this, it requires the specifier of the tool to be a
    <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object. The programmer is responsible for setting the tool attributes as he
    wishes.
  </para>
  <para>
    For the simple case of adding a tool that is a dialog control, the <xref linkend="mthAddTool"/> is a more convenient
    method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example creates a ToolTip and then adds a tool that will supply customized tool tips for a tree-view:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  tv = self~newTreeView(IDC_TREE)
  rect = tv~clientRect

  tt = self~createToolTip(IDC_TT)

  toolInfo = .ToolInfo~new(tv, ID_TREE_TOOL, '', 'TRANSPARENT', rect)
  tt~addToolEx(toolInfo)

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::addToolEx() -->


<section id="mthAddToolRect" xreflabel="addToolRect"><title>addToolRect</title>
<indexterm><primary>addToolRect</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>addToolRect</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--addToolRect(--dlg-,-id-,-rect--+--------+-+---------+-+------------+--)----><
                                   +-,-txt--+ +-,-flags-+ +-,-userData-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Adds a tool that uses a rectangular area in the dialog as its trigger point.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>dlg [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The dialog <link linkend="chpDialogObject">object</link> that contains the rectangular area specified by the
        <emphasis role="italic">rect</emphasis> argument.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>id [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        An unique, non-negative, whole number that identifies the tool being added. May be numeric or <xref
        linkend="defSymbolicId"/>.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>rect [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsRect"/> object that specifies the bounding rectangle coordinates of the tool. The coordinates are
        in client <link linkend="defScreenCoordinates">coordinates</link> of the dialog identified by the <emphasis
        role="italic">dlg</emphasis> argument.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>txt [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Text for the tool. If omitted, or the empty string, or the string: TEXTCALLBACK, then the ToolTip sends the <xref
        linkend="kywToolTipNEEDTEXT"/> notification and the program supplies the text.
      </para>
      <para>
        The length of the text must be less than 1024 characters, which includes any possible end of line (0x0D0A) sequences.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>flags [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A list of 0 or more of the following keywords separated by spaces, case is not significant. If this argument is
        omitted, the flags are set to SUBCLASS:
      </para>
      <para>
        <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
          <member>ABSOLUTE   </member>
          <member>CENTERTIP  </member>
          <member>IDISHWND   </member>
          <member>PARSELINKS </member>
          <member>RTLREADING </member>
          <member>SUBCLASS   </member>
          <member>TRACK      </member>
          <member>TRANSPARENT</member>
        </simplelist>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry><term>ABSOLUTE</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Positions the ToolTip window at the exact same coordinates specified by the <xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/>
            method. Without this flag the ToolTip control chooses where to display the ToolTip window based on the
            coordinates specified, which places the ToolTip close to the tool. This flag must be used with the TRACK flag.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>CENTERTIP</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Centers the ToolTip window below the tool specified by the <emphasis role="italic">tool</emphasis> argument.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>IDISHWND</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Indicates that the ID part of the tool <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification</link> is the window
            handle to the tool. This flag can not be used for the <emphasis role="italic">addToolRect</emphasis> method. If
            it is present, the ooDialog framework removes it.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>PARSELINKS</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Requires Common Control <xref linkend="ovvComctl32"/> version 6.0 or later.
          </para>
          <para>
            Indicates that links in the ToolTip text should be parsed.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>RTLREADING</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Indicates that the ToolTip text will be displayed in the opposite direction to the text in the parent window.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>SUBCLASS</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Indicates that the ToolTip control should subclass the tool's window to intercept messages, such as WM_MOUSEMOVE.
            If this flag is not set, some means must be used so that the mouse messages are forwarded to the ToolTip control.
            For the use case that the <emphasis role="italic">addToolRect</emphasis> method is designed for, this flag
            should always be set. The ooDialog framwork always sets this flag during the <emphasis
            role="italic">addToolRect</emphasis> method, the programmer does not need to include this flag.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>TRACK</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
             Positions the ToolTip window next to the tool to which it corresponds and moves the window according to
             coordinates supplied by the <xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/> method. The programmer must activate this
             type of tool using the <xref linkend="mthTrackActivate"/> method.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>TRANSPARENT</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Causes the ToolTip control to forward mouse event messages to the parent window. This is limited to mouse events
            that occur within the bounds of the ToolTip window.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>userData [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A user data value to be associated with the tool. This can be any Rexx object the programmer wants. Note that the
        value is associated with the tool, not the tool tip.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns true on success, false on error.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example was created solely as a demonstration of how ToolTips work, it has no real practical value. It displays
    ToolTips as the mouse moves over a dialog:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  tt = self~createToolTip(IDC_TT_MAIN)

  clRect = self~clientRect
  hMidpoint = trunc((clRect~right - clRect~left) / 2) + clRect~left
  vMidpoint = trunc((clRect~bottom - clRect~top) / 2) + clRect~top

  clRect1 = .Rect~new(clRect~left, clRect~top, hMidpoint, vMidpoint)
  clRect2 = .Rect~new(hMidpoint + 1, clRect~top, clRect~right, vMidpoint + 1)
  clRect3 = .Rect~new(clRect~left, vMidpoint + 1, hMidpoint + 1, clRect~bottom)
  clRect4 = .Rect~new(hMidpoint + 1, vMidpoint + 1, clRect~right, clRect~bottom)

  text1 = 'Over main dialog, top left quadrant'
  text2 = 'Over main dialog, top right quadrant'
  text3 = 'Over main dialog, bottom left quadrant'
  text4 = 'Over main dialog, bottom right quadrant'

  ret = tt~addToolRect(self, IDTOOL_DLG_RECT1, clRect1, text1, 'TRANSPARENT')
  ret = tt~addToolRect(self, IDTOOL_DLG_RECT2, clRect2, text2, 'TRANSPARENT')
  ret = tt~addToolRect(self, IDTOOL_DLG_RECT3, clRect3, text3, 'TRANSPARENT')
  ret = tt~addToolRect(self, IDTOOL_DLG_RECT4, clRect4, text4, 'TRANSPARENT')

  self~connectToolTipEvent(IDC_TT_MAIN, 'SHOW', onShow)
]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::addToolRect() -->


<section id="mthAdjustRect" xreflabel="adjustRect"><title>adjustRect</title>
<indexterm><primary>adjustRect</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>adjustRect</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--adjustRect(--rect--+-----------+--)----------><
                       +-,-larger--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Calculates a ToolTip control's text display rectangle from its window rectangle, or the ToolTip window rectangle needed to
  display a specified text display rectangle.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>rect [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsRect"/> object used to specify the rectangle to adjust. On a successful return, the coordinates
        in the rectangle will be adjusted as specified by the <emphasis role="italic">larger</emphasis> argument.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>larger [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        True or false to specify how the rectangle is adjusted. If omitted, the default is false.
      </para>
      <para>
        If true, <emphasis role="italic">rect</emphasis> is used to specify a text-display rectangle and it is updated to
        contain the corresponding window rectangle. On return the rectangle is <emphasis role="italic">larger</emphasis> in
        this case. If false, <emphasis role="italic">rect</emphasis> is used to specify a window rectangle and it is updated
        to the corresponding text display rectangle. On return, the rectangle is <emphasis role="italic">not</emphasis>
        larger, (it is smaller,) in this case.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns true if the rectangle was adjusted correctly, and returns false if an error occurred.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method is particularly useful when a ToolTip control is used to display the full text of a string that is truncated.
    It is commonly used with list-view and tree-view controls. Typically send this method would be used in response to a
    <xref linkend="kywToolTipSHOW"/> SHOW event notification so that the ToolTip control properly can be positioned properly.
  </para>
  <para>
    The ToolTip's window rectangle is somewhat larger than the text display rectangle that bounds the ToolTip string. The
    window origin is also offset up and to the left from the origin of the text display rectangle. To position the text
    display rectangle, the programmer must calculate the corresponding window rectangle and use that rectangle to position
    the ToolTip. The <emphasis role="italic">adjustRect</emphasis> method handles this calculation for the programmer.
  </para>
  <para>
    If <emphasis role="italic">larger</emphasis> is set to true, <emphasis role="italic">adjustRect</emphasis> takes the size
    and position of the desired ToolTip text display rectangle, and passes back the size and position of the ToolTip window
    needed to display the text in the specified position. If <emphasis role="italic">larger</emphasis> is set to false, the
    programmer can specify a ToolTip window rectangle and the <emphasis role="italic">adjustRect</emphasis> method will
    return the size and position of its text rectangle.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::adjustRect() -->


<section id="mthDelTool" xreflabel="delTool"><title>delTool</title>
<indexterm><primary>delTool</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>delTool</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--delTool(--toolHwnd--+----------+--)----------><
                        +-,-toolID-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Removes the specified tool from this ToolTip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolHwnd [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>toolID [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">Tool Identification</link> section explains exactly how the Rexx object
    combination is used to specify the tool to be deleted.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example shows a tool being added to a ToolTip and then at some later point in the application being deleted.
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  pbTest = self~newPushButton(IDC_PB_TEST)
  count  = 0
  ...

  ttTest = self~createToolTip(IDC_TT_TEST)
  ttTest~addTool(pbTest, "Push the Test button to start the regression testing.")

  ...

  ttTest~delTool(pbTest)


]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::delTool() -->


<section id="mthEnumTools" xreflabel="enumTools"><title>enumTools</title>
<indexterm><primary>enumTools</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>enumTools</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--enumTools(--+---------+--)-------------------><
                +--index--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves a <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object for the tool at the specified index.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>index</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The one-based index of the tool to retrieve. If omitted, <emphasis role="italic">index</emphasis> defaults to 1.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the tool, as a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object, at the index specified, or the
    <computeroutput>.nil</computeroutput> object if there is no tool at the index.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The Microsoft documentation says nothing about what, if any, order the tools contained in a ToolTip are in.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example <emphasis role="italic">enumerates</emphasis> the tools in a ToolTip:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  do i = 1 to toolTip~getToolCount
    toolInfo = toolTip~enumTools(i)
    say 'Tool info  hwnd:    ' toolInfo~rexxHwnd
    say 'Tool info  id:      ' toolInfo~rexxID
    say 'Tool info  text:    ' toolInfo~text
    say 'Tool info  flags:   ' toolInfo~flags
    say 'Tool info  rect:    ' toolInfo~rect
    say 'Tool info  userData:' toolInfo~userData
    say 'Tool info  resource:' toolInfo~resource
    say
  end
]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::enumTools() -->


<section id="mthGetBubbleSize" xreflabel="getBubbleSize"><title>getBubbleSize</title>
<indexterm><primary>getBubbleSize</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getBubbleSize</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getBubbleSize(--toolHwnd--+----------+--)----><
                              +-,-toolID-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns the width and height, as a <xref linkend="clsSize"/> object, of this ToolTip control.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolHwnd [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>toolID [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    A <computeroutput>Size</computeroutput> object specifying the width and height of this tool tip control.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">Tool Identification</link> section explains exactly how the Rexx object
    combination is used to specify the tool to be deleted.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getBubbleSize() -->


<section id="mthGetCurrentToolInfo" xreflabel="getCurrentToolInfo"><title>getCurrentToolInfo</title>
<indexterm><primary>getCurrentToolInfo</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getCurrentToolInfo</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getCurrentToolInfo---------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves a <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object whose attributes represent the current tool in this tool tip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    There are no arguments for this method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the current tool as a <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/>  object, if one exists, or
    the <computeroutput>.nil</computeroutput> object if there is not a current tool.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  <para>
    Sets the <link linkend="dotSystemErrorCode">.SystemErrorCode</link> variable.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getCurrentToolInfo() -->


<section id="mthGetDelayTime" xreflabel="getDelayTime"><title>getDelayTime</title>
<indexterm><primary>getDelayTime</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getDelayTime</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getDelayTime(--+---------+--)----------------><
                   +--which--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves one of the 3 delay times currently set for this ToolTip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>which [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Exactly one of the following keywords, case is not significant. This specifies which of the 3 possible delay times to
        retrieve. The default if omitted is AUTOPOP:
      </para>
      <para>
        <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
          <member>AUTOPOP   </member>
          <member>INITIAL    </member>
          <member>RESHOW   </member>
        </simplelist>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry><term>AUTOPOP</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            The amount of time the ToolTip window remains visible if the pointer is stationary within a tool's bounding
            rectangle.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>INITIAL</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            The amount of time the pointer must remain stationary within a tool's bounding rectangle before the ToolTip
            window appears.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>RESHOW</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            The amount of time it takes for subsequent ToolTip windows to appear as the pointer moves from one tool to
            another.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The specified delay time in milliseconds.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getDelayTime() -->


<section id="mthGetMargin" xreflabel="getMargin"><title>getMargin</title>
<indexterm><primary>getMargin</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getMargin</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getMargin------------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns a rectangle that describes the margins of the ToolTip
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method has no arguments.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    A <xref linkend="clsRect"/> object whose attributes specify the margins of the ToolTip.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The attributes of the returned rectangle do not define a bounding rectangle. For the purpose of this method, the
    attributes are interpreted as follows:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">top:</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Distance between top border and top of ToolTip text, in pixels.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">left:</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Distance between left border and left end of ToolTip text, in pixels.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">bottom:</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Distance between bottom border and bottom of ToolTip text, in pixels.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">right:</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Distance between right border and right end of ToolTip text, in pixels.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getMargin() -->


<section id="mthGetMaxTipWidth" xreflabel="getMaxTipWidth"><title>getMaxTipWidth</title>
<indexterm><primary>getMaxTipWidth</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getMaxTipWidth</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getMaxTipWidth-------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves the maximum width for this ToolTip window.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method has no arguments.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a whole number value that represents the maximum ToolTip width, in pixels. If no maximum width was set
    previously, this method returns -1.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The maximum ToolTip width value does not indicate a ToolTip window's actual width. Rather, if a ToolTip string exceeds
    the maximum width, the control breaks the text into multiple lines, using spaces or newline characters to determine line
    breaks. If the text cannot be segmented into multiple lines, it will be displayed on a single line. The length of this
    line may exceed the maximum ToolTip width.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getMaxTipWidth() -->


<section id="mthGetTextClsToolTip" xreflabel="getText"><title>getText</title>
<indexterm><primary>getText</primary><secondary>ToolTip class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getText</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getText(--toolHwnd--+----------+--)----------><
                        +-,-toolID-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves the text information this ToolTip control maintains about the specified tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolHwnd [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>toolID [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The text string for the specified tool
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">Tool Identification</link> section explains exactly how the Rexx object
    combination is used to specify the tool to get the text for.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example example prints to the screen the text for a tool tip where the tool is a rectangular area in a dialog:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

      say 'Text for the tool tip:' tt~getText(self, IDTOOL_DLG_RECT1)

/* Output might be:

Text for the tool tip: Over main dialog, top left quadrant

*/
]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getText() -->


<section id="mthGetTipBkColor" xreflabel="getTipBkColor"><title>getTipBkColor</title>
<indexterm><primary>getTipBkColor</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getTipBkColor</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getTipBkColor--------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves the background color for this ToolTip window.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    There are no arguments for this method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a <xref linkend="defColorRef"/> value that represents the background color of this ToolTip window.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getTipBkColor() -->


<section id="mthGetTipTextColor" xreflabel="getTipTextColor"><title>getTipTextColor</title>
<indexterm><primary>getTipTextColor</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getTipTextColor</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getTipTextColor------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves the text color fot this ToolTip window.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method does not have any arguments.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a <xref linkend="defColorRef"/> value that represents the background color of this ToolTip window.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getTipTextColor() -->


<section id="mthGetTitle" xreflabel="getTitle"><title>getTitle</title>
<indexterm><primary>getTitle</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getTitle</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getTitle-------------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves information concerning the title and icon of this ToolTip control.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method takes no arguments.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a <computeroutput>.Directory</computeroutput> object whose indexes contain the title and icon information for
    this ToolTip. Indexes are:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term>TITLE</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      The title text.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>ICON</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      The ICON index will be the <xref linkend="clsImage"/> object used for the icon of this ToolTip, or one of the following
      keywords if a system image is used for the icon:
    </para>
    <para>
      <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
        <member>NONE        </member>
        <member>ERROR       </member>
        <member>ERRORLARGE  </member>
        <member>INFO        </member>
        <member>INFOLARGE   </member>
        <member>WARNING     </member>
        <member>WARNINGLARGE</member>
      </simplelist>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>NONE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          No icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>ERROR</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Error icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>ERRORLARGE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Large warning icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>INFO</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Info icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>INFOLARGE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Large info icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>WARNING</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Warning icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>WARNINGLARGE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Large warning icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>ISKEYWORD</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      True if the ICON index is a keyword, false if it is an <computeroutput>Image</computeroutput> object.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The underlying Windows API for <emphasis role="italic">getTitle</emphasis> appears to be rather idiosyncratic.
  </para>
  <para>
    In testing, when setting the icon to an actual icon image, getting the icon always returns the INFOLARGE keyword, rather
    than the icon image. In addition, when setting the icon to any of the LARGE keyword values, getting the icon always
    returns the non-large keyword. This anomaly is mentioned in several places on the web. The following table shows this
    behaviour:

  <table id="tblGetTitleReturns" frame="all"> <title>getTitle Anomalies</title>
  <tgroup cols="2">
  <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
  <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
  <thead>
  <row>
  <entry>Actual Icon Value</entry>
  <entry>getTitle() returns</entry>
  </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <row>
  <entry>hIcon</entry>
  <entry>INFOLARGE</entry>
  </row>
  <row>
  <entry>INFOLARGE</entry>
  <entry>INFO</entry>
  </row>
  <row>
  <entry>WARNINGLARGE</entry>
  <entry>WARNING</entry>
  </row>
  <row>
  <entry>ERRORLARGE</entry>
  <entry>ERROR</entry>
  </row>
  </tbody></tgroup>
  </table>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getTitle() -->


<section id="mthGetToolCount" xreflabel="getToolCount"><title>getToolCount</title>
<indexterm><primary>getToolCount</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getToolCount</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getToolCount---------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves the number of tools this ToolTip contains.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    There are no arguments for this method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the number of tools in the ToolTip.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <emphasis role="italic">getToolCount</emphasis> method in conjunction with the <xref linkend="mthEnumTools"/> method
    is useful in enumerating the tools of the ToolTip.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example prints out information for each tool in the ToolTip:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  do i = 1 to tt~getToolCount
    toolInfo = tt~enumTools(i)
    say 'Tool info  hwnd:    ' toolInfo~rexxHwnd
    say 'Tool info  id:      ' toolInfo~rexxID
    say 'Tool info  text:    ' toolInfo~text
    say 'Tool info  flags:   ' toolInfo~flags
    say 'Tool info  rect:    ' toolInfo~rect
    say 'Tool info  userData:' toolInfo~userData
    say 'Tool info  resource:' toolInfo~resource
    say
  end
]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getToolCount() -->


<section id="mthGetToolInfo" xreflabel="getToolInfo"><title>getToolInfo</title>
<indexterm><primary>getToolInfo</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>getToolInfo</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--getToolInfo(--toolHwnd--+----------+--)------><
                            +-,-toolID-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Retrieves the information, as a <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object, that this tool tip control maintains about the
  specified tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolHwnd [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>toolID [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object whose attributes reflect the information that this ToolTip
    maintains about the specified tool. On error, the <computeroutput>.nil</computeroutput> object is returned.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">Tool Identification</link> section explains exactly how the Rexx object
    combination is used to specify the tool to be deleted.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::getToolInfo() -->


<section id="mthHasCurrentTool" xreflabel="hasCurrentTool"><title>hasCurrentTool</title>
<indexterm><primary>hasCurrentTool</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>hasCurrentTool</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--hasCurrentTool-------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Tests if this ToolTip has a current tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method has no arguments.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns true if there is a current tool, false if there is not.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    In essence, this convenience method tests if the <xref linkend="mthGetCurrentToolInfo"/> method will return a
    <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object or the <computeroutput>.nil</computeroutput> object.
  </para> </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::hasCurrentTool() -->


<section id="mthHitTestInfoClsToolTip" xreflabel="hitTestInfo"><title>hitTestInfo</title>
<indexterm><primary>hitTestInfo</primary><secondary>ToolTip class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>hitTest</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
Form 1:

>>--hitTestInfo(--toolInfo--,--point--)----------><

Form 2:

>>--hitTestInfo(--toolInfo--,--x,--y--)----------><

Generic form:

>>--hitTestInfo(--toolInfo--,--ptToTest--)-------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Tests a point to determine whether it is within the bounding rectangle of a tool within the window specified and, if it
  is, retrieves information about the tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolInfo [required in / out]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object whose <xref linkend="atrRexxHwnd"/> attribute specifies which tool window to
        test.
      </para>
      <para>
        If the point tested is within a tool of the tool window, the retrieved tool information is returned in this object.
        The tool info object should be instantiated using the <xref linkend="mthForHitTest"/> class method.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>ptToTest [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The point to test. The point is specifed in client <link linkend="defScreenCoordinates">coordinates</link> of the
        window specified by the <emphasis role="italic">toolInfo</emphasis> argument.
      </para>
      <para>
        As indicated by the syntax diagram, the point to test can be specified in two ways. Either as one argument, a <xref
        linkend="clsPoint"/> object, or as two arguments, the x coordinate of the point followed by the y coordinate of the
        point.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    True if the point being tested is within the window specified, otherwise false.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example gets the current cursor position and then hit tests that position for a push button tool:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  mouse = .Mouse~new(self)
  pos = mouse~getCursorPos
  pbTest~screen2client(pos)

  hitTool = .ToolInfo~forHitTest(pbTest)

  say 'Using' pos
  if ttTest~hitTestInfo(hitTool, pos) then do
    say 'Got hit'
    say 'Tool info  hwnd:    ' hitTool~rexxHwnd
    say 'Tool info  id:      ' hitTool~rexxID
    say 'Tool info  text:    ' hitTool~text
    say 'Tool info  flags:   ' hitTool~flags
    say 'Tool info  rect:    ' hitTool~rect
    say 'Tool info  userData:' hitTool~userData
    say 'Tool info  resource:' hitTool~resource
    say
  end
  else do
    say 'NO hit'
    say 'Tool info  hwnd:    ' hitTool~rexxHwnd
  end

/* Output could be for instance:

Got hit
Tool info  hwnd:     a SimpleDialog
Tool info  id:       a Button
Tool info  text:     Press Test to execute the regression suite
Tool info  flags:    IDISHWND SUBCLASS
Tool info  rect:     a Rect (0, 0, 0, 0)
Tool info  userData: The NIL object
Tool info  resource: The NIL object

*/
]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::hitTestInfo() -->


<section id="mthManageAtypicalTool" xreflabel="manageAtypicalTool"><title>manageAtypicalTool</title>
<indexterm><primary>manageAtypicalTool</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>manageAtypicalTool</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--manageAtypicalTool(--toolObj--+-----------+--+-----------+--)--------------><
                                  +-,-events--+  +-,-methods-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Initiates the management of a ToolTip tool that is a dialog control. This is for a tool that is not the typical tool used
  in ooDialog. See the remarks section for details.
</para>
<para>
  The <emphasis role="italic">manageAtypicalTool</emphasis> initiates a process that monitors every window <link
  linkend="ovvWindowMessages">message</link> sent to the <emphasis role="italic">toolObj</emphasis>, (which is a dialog
  control.) This allows the process to relay all mouse messages to the tool and to intercept all event notifications sent by
  the ToolTip to the <emphasis role="italic">toolObj</emphasis>. Why this is necessary is explained in more detail in the
  remarks section.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolObj [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The tool dialog control to be managed.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>events [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        An array of keywords for the ToolTip events that should invoke a method in the Rexx dialog.  The array can not be
        sparse. Each index in the array should contain the keyword for a ToolTip event. If an event keyword is present at an
        index, then that event is connected to a method in the Rexx dialog. Case is not significant in the keywords. The
        valid keywords are:
      </para>
      <para>
        <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
          <member>RELAY    </member>
          <member>NEEDTEXT </member>
          <member>SHOW     </member>
          <member>POP      </member>
          <member>LINKCLICK</member>
          <member>NORELAY  </member>
        </simplelist>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry><term>RELAY</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Causes the monitoring process to invoke the connected method in the Rexx dialog for every mouse message sent to
            the dialog control. The method is invoked <emphasis role="italic">before</emphasis> the monitoring process relays
            the message to the ToolTip. By default the method invoked for this keyword is <emphasis
            role="italic">onRelay</emphasis>.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>NEEDTEXT</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Causes the monitoring process to intercept the <xref linkend="kywToolTipNEEDTEXT"/> event notification sent to
            the dialog control, and invoke the connected method in the Rexx dialog. The notifcation is prevented from going
            to the dialog control. By default the method invoked for this keyword is <emphasis
            role="italic">onNeedText</emphasis>.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>SHOW</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Causes the monitoring process to intercept the <xref linkend="kywToolTipSHOW"/> event notification sent to the
            dialog control, and invoke the connected method in the Rexx dialog. The notifcation is prevented from going to
            the dialog control. By default the method invoked for this keyword is <emphasis role="italic">onShow</emphasis>.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>POP</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Causes the monitoring process to intercept the <xref linkend="kywToolTipPOP"/> event notification sent to the
            dialog control and invoke the connected method in the Rexx dialog. The notifcation is prevented from going to
            the dialog control. By default the method invoked for this keyword is <emphasis
            role="italic">onPop</emphasis>.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>LINKCLICK</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Causes the monitoring process to intercept the <xref linkend="kywToolTipLINKCLICK"/> event notification sent to
            the dialog control and invoke the connected method in the Rexx dialog. The notifcation is prevented from going to
            the dialog control. By default the method invoked for this keyword is <emphasis
            role="italic">onLinkClick</emphasis>.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>NORELAY</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Prevents the monitoring process from automatically forwarding the mouse messages to the ToolTip. There is no
            method connection associated with this keyword.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>methods [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        An array of alternative method names for each connected event. If the default method name is not suitable, for whatever
        reason, then the programmer can supply her own name in the <emphasis role="italic">methods</emphasis> array. The
        alternative method name must be at the same index in the <emphasis role="italic">methods</emphasis> array as the
        event keyword's index in the <emphasis role="italic">events</emphasis> array.
      </para>
      <para>
        E.g., if the keyword SHOW is present at index 2 in the <emphasis role="italic">events</emphasis> array and the
        programmer wants to over-ride the default method name of <emphasis role="italic">onShow</emphasis>, then this can be
        done by putting the alternative method name at index 2 in the <emphasis role="italic">methods</emphasis> array. There
        is no requirement to put any name at index 1. That is, the <emphasis role="italic">methods</emphasis> array can be
        sparse.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns true on success, false on error.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The ooDialog framework provides the <emphasis role="italic">manageAtypicalTool</emphasis> method to allow more advanced
    usage of ToolTips. For a ToolTip to work properly, it needs two things. One, it needs to be aware of every mouse message
    sent to the window that is the tool. Two, it needs to send event notifications to the owner window of the tool.
  </para>
  <para>
    In the typical use case in ooDialog, the window that the ToolTip sends the notifications to is the dialog, (where they
    are handled by the Rexx dialog through the event connections.) When the SUBCLASS flag is used for the tool, the ToolTip
    sets up its own internal process to monitor all the mouse messages sent to the tool window. In this typical use case,
    there is no need for the <emphasis role="italic">manageAtypicalTool</emphasis> method.
  </para>
  <para>
    However there are two basic situations that are not the typical use case. The first is when the SUBCLASS flag can not be
    used. In this situation there needs to be some way to <emphasis role="italic">relay</emphasis> the mouse messages to the
    ToolTip. The problem with mouse messages is that they are sent to the window the mouse is over. If the mouse messages are
    sent to the dialog window, ooDialog would have no problem. It could intercept the mouse messages through event
    connections and then relay the message to the ToolTip. However, when the mouse is over a dialog control, the dialog
    window has no knowledge of the mouse messages.
  </para>
  <para>
    The other situation is when the dialog window is not sent the ToolTip event notifications. If the event notifications are
    sent to a dialog control, then there is no way to handle the events through connected methods in the Rexx dialog. Both of
    these situations can arise when more advanced usage of ToolTips is tried. A common reason why the SUBCLASS flag can not
    be used is because the application needs to take some action <emphasis role="italic">before</emphasis> the ToolTip is
    aware of the mouse message. A common reason why the ToolTip event notifications can not be sent to the dialog window is
    that the ToolTip was created by and is owned by a dialog control.
  </para>
  <para>
    There are two example programs provided with the ooDialog distribution that explore the use of the <emphasis
    role="italic">manageAtypicalTool</emphasis> method in these two situations. They are in the
    <computeroutput>samples\controls\ToolTip</computeroutput> subdirectories. One program is the
    <computeroutput>manageControlTool.rex</computeroutput> example. The other is the
    <computeroutput>customPositionToolTip.rex</computeroutput> example.
  </para>
  <para>
    Note that when the <emphasis role="italic">manageAtypicalTool</emphasis> method starts the monitoring process, it
    <emphasis role="italic">always</emphasis> forwards all mouse messages to the ToolTip, even if both optional arguments are
    ommitted. This is not always desirable. To prevent this, use the NORELAY keyword.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Requires Common Control <xref linkend="ovvComctl32"/> version 6.0 or later.
  </para>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example sets up a customized ToolTip for a tree-view control. The <emphasis
    role="italic">manageAtypicalTool</emphasis> method is used because the customization requires that the application takes
    action before the mouse move messages are seen by the ToolTip. The RELAY keyword invokes the <emphasis
    role="italic">onRelay</emphasis> method in the dialog for every mouse move message. The application examines the mouse
    messages and determines what action to take. When the method returns, the mouse messages are relayed to the ToolTip.
  </para>
  <para>
    Note that the third optional argument is an array with no values at index 1 and index 2. The <emphasis
    role="italic">onShowToolTip</emphasis> value at index 3 is the alternative method name to invoke for the SHOW event:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  tv = self~newTreeView(IDC_TREE)
  rect = tv~clientRect

  tt = self~createToolTip(IDC_TT)

  toolInfo = .ToolInfo~new(tv, 10, '', 'TRANSPARENT', rect)
  tt~addToolEx(toolInfo)

  ...

  tt~manageAtypicalTool(tv, .array~of('RELAY', 'NEEDTEXT', 'SHOW'), .array~of( , , 'onShowToolTip'))

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::manageAtypicalTool() -->


<section id="mthNewToolRect" xreflabel="newToolRect"><title>newToolRect</title>
<indexterm><primary>newToolRect</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>newToolRect</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--newToolRect(--rect-,-toolHwnd--+----------+--)--------------><
                                   +-,-toolID-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets a new bounding rectangle for a tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>rect [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsRect"/> object that specifies the new bounding rectangle of the tool.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>toolHwnd [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>toolID [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">Tool Identification</link> section explains exactly how the Rexx object
    combination is used to specify the tool the new bounding rectangle is assigned to.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::newToolRect() -->


<section id="mthPop" xreflabel="pop"><title>pop</title>
<indexterm><primary>pop</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>pop</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--pop------------------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Removes, hides, this ToolTip's display window.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method has no arguments.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::pop() -->


<section id="mthPopUpClsToolTip" xreflabel="popUp"><title>popUp</title>
<indexterm><primary>popUp</primary><secondary>ToolTip class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>popUp</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--popUp----------------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Causes this ToolTip to display at the coordinates of the last mouse message.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    There are no arguments for this method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Requires Common Control <xref linkend="ovvComctl32"/> version 6.0 or later.
  </para>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::popUp() -->


<section id="mthSetDelayTime" xreflabel="setDelayTime"><title>setDelayTime</title>
<indexterm><primary>setDelayTime</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>setDelayTime</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--setDelayTime(--+---------+--+---------+--)---><
                   +--which--+  +-,-time--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the initial, pop-up, and reshow durations for this ToolTip control.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>which [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Exactly one of the following keywords, case is not significant. This specifies which of the 3, or all of the 3,
        possible delay times to set. The default if omitted is AUTOMATIC:
      </para>
      <para>
        <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
          <member>AUTOPOP  </member>
          <member>INITIAL  </member>
          <member>RESHOW   </member>
          <member>AUTOMATIC</member>
        </simplelist>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry><term>AUTOPOP</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            The amount of time the ToolTip window remains visible if the pointer is stationary within a tool's bounding
            rectangle.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>INITIAL</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            The amount of time the pointer must remain stationary within a tool's bounding rectangle before the ToolTip
            window appears.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>RESHOW</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            The amount of time it takes for subsequent ToolTip windows to appear as the pointer moves from one tool to
            another.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>AUTOMATIC</term>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Sets all 3 delay times to their default proportions. The autopop time will be ten times the initial time and the
            reshow time will be one fifth the initial time. When using this keyword, use a positive value for <emphasis
            role="italic">time</emphasis> to specify the initial time, in milliseconds.  Use a negative <emphasis
            role="italic">time</emphasis> to return all three delay times to their default values. This is the default if the
            <emphasis role="italic">which</emphasis> argument is omitted.
          </para>
          </listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>time [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The time, in milliseconds to set the specified delay time to. A negative time sets the specified time back to its
        default value. If this argument is omitted, the default is -1.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::setDelayTime() -->


<section id="mthSetMargin" xreflabel="setMargin"><title>setMargin</title>
<indexterm><primary>setMargin</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>setMargin</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--setMargin(--margins--)-----------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the top, left, bottom, and right margins for a ToolTip window. A margin is the distance, in pixels, between the
  ToolTip window border and the text contained within the ToolTip window.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>margins [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsRect"/> object that specifies the margins.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The attributes of the returned rectangle do not define a bounding rectangle. For the purpose of this method, the
    attributes are interpreted as follows:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">top:</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Distance between top border and top of ToolTip text, in pixels.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">left:</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Distance between left border and left end of ToolTip text, in pixels.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">bottom:</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Distance between bottom border and bottom of ToolTip text, in pixels.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">right:</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Distance between right border and right end of ToolTip text, in pixels.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example sets the margins for a ToolTip to 2 pixels on the sides and 4 pixels on the top and bottom:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  margins = .Rect~new(2, 4, 2, 4)
  toolTip~setMargins(margins)

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::setMargin() -->


<section id="mthSetMaxTipWidth" xreflabel="setMaxTipWidth"><title>setMaxTipWidth</title>
<indexterm><primary>setMaxTipWidth</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>setMaxTipWidth</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--setMaxTipWidth(--max--)---------------------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the maximum width, in pixels, for this ToolTip window.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>max [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The maximum width for the ToolTip, or -1 to allow any width.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the previous maximum width for this ToolTip.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The maximum width value does not indicate a ToolTip window's actual width. Rather, if a ToolTip string exceeds the
     maximum width, the control breaks the text into multiple lines, using spaces to determine line breaks. If the text
     cannot be segmented into multiple lines, it is displayed on a single line, which may exceed the maximum ToolTip width.
  </para>
  <para>
    For instance, if the maximum width is set to 20 and there is a word within the text that is longer than 20, the word is
    not broken in two. It is displayed on a single line, causing that line to be longer than 20.
  </para>
  <para>
    The text can contain embedded new line characters and the ToolTip will break the text at the new line indicator.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example creates a tool for a push button with a relatively long string for the tool's text. It then gets the size
    for a portion of the text in pixels and sets the max tip width to the width of the portion. This causes the ToolTip to
    create a multi-line display window:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  tt = self~createToolTip(IDC_TT_MAIN)

  text = "Push the 'Test' button to run the current regression test for ooRexx..."
  tt~addTool(self~newPushButton(IDC_PB_TEST), text)

  s = self~getTextSizePX("Push the 'Test' button")
  tt~setMaxTipWidth(s~width)

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::setMaxTipWidth() -->


<section id="mthSetTipBkColor" xreflabel="setTipBkColor"><title>setTipBkColor</title>
<indexterm><primary>setTipBkColor</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>setTipBkColor</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--setTipBkColor(--color--)---------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the background color for this ToolTip window.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>color [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The new color for the background of the ToolTip window. The color is expressed as a <xref linkend="defColorRef"/>
        value.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method is included for completeness. As is the case for most dialog controls that have set color methods, the dialog
    control ignores a color change if visual themes are in effect. Most systems on XP and later have visual themes on by
    default.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::setTipBkColor() -->


<section id="mthSetTipTextColor" xreflabel="setTipTextColor"><title>setTipTextColor</title>
<indexterm><primary>setTipTextColor</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>setTipTextColor</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--setTipTextColor(--color--)---------------------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the text color for this ToolTip window.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>color [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The new color for the text of the ToolTip window. The color is expressed as a <xref linkend="defColorRef"/> value.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method is included for completeness. As is the case for most dialog controls that have set color methods, the dialog
    control ignores a color change if visual themes are in effect. Most systems on XP and later have visual themes on by
    default.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::setTipTextColor() -->


<section id="mthSetTitleClsToolTip" xreflabel="setTitle"><title>setTitle</title>
<indexterm><primary>setTitle</primary><secondary>ToolTip class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>setTitle</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--setTitle(--title--+---------+--)-------------><
                      +-,-icon--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Adds a title string and optionally an icon image to this ToolTip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>title [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The title for this ToolTip.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>icon [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Either an icon <xref linkend="clsImage"/> object, or one of the following keywords to use a system icon. Case is not
        significant in the keywords. The default if the keyword is omitted is NONE:
      </para>
      <para>
        <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
          <member>NONE</member>
          <member>ERROR</member>
          <member>ERRORLARGE</member>
          <member>INFO</member>
          <member>INFOLARGE</member>
          <member>WARNING</member>
          <member>WARNINGLARGE</member>
        </simplelist>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>NONE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          No icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>ERROR</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Error icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>ERRORLARGE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Large warning icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>INFO</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Info icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>INFOLARGE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Large info icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>WARNING</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Warning icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>WARNINGLARGE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Large warning icon.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    True on success, false on error.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <emphasis role="italic">title</emphasis> string can not be longer than 99 characters. If an <xref
    linkend="clsImage"/> object is used, the image must actually be an icon. The operating system will not display a bitmap
    when an icon is called for.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example creates a balloon ToolTip with a title and an icon;
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  icon = .Image~getImage("musicNote.ico", .Image~toID(IMAGE_ICON), .size~new(16, 16))

  tt = self~createToolTip(IDC_TT_BALLOON, 'BALLOON CLOSE')
  tt~setTitle("Important Message", icon)

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::setTitle() -->


<section id="mthSetToolInfo" xreflabel="setToolInfo"><title>setToolInfo</title>
<indexterm><primary>setToolInfo</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>setToolInfo</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--setToolInfo(--toolInfo--)--------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the information that this ToolTip control maintains for a tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolInfo [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object whose attributes specify the information this ToolTip should use for a tool.
        See the remarks.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Some internal properties of a tool are established when the tool is created, and are not recomputed by the ToolTip when
    the <emphasis role="italic">setToolInfo</emphasis> method is invoked.  If a <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput>
    object is simply instantiated, its attributes assigned values, and is then passed to the ToolTip control through the
    <emphasis role="italic">setToolInfo</emphasis> method, these properties may be lost.
  </para>
  <para>
    Instead, the programmer should first request the tool's current <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object by using
    the <xref linkend="mthGetToolInfo"/> method. Then, modify the attributes of this object as needed and pass it back to
    the ToolTip control using the <emphasis role="italic">setToolInfo</emphasis> method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example modifies the text, bounding rectangle, and flags of a tool:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  toolInfo = ttEsc~getToolInfo(self~newPushButton(IDCANCEL))

  toolInfo~text  = "Only push the cancel button if you want, or need, to end the dialog"
  toolInfo~rect  = .Rect~new(3, 2, 44, 11)
  toolInfo~flags = toolInfo~flags 'CENTERTIP'

  ttEsc~setToolInfo(toolInfo)

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::setToolInfo() -->


<section id="mthSetWindowThemeClsToolTip" xreflabel="setWindowTheme"><title>setWindowTheme</title>
<indexterm><primary>setWindowTheme</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>setWindowTheme</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--setWindowTheme(--style--)--------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the visual style of a ToolTip control.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>style [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A string specifying the visual style.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This method over-rides the <xref linkend="clsDialogControl"/>  classs <xref
    linkend="mthSetWindowThemeClsDialogControl"/> method because the implementation for a tool tip is different than for the
    general dialog control case.
  </para>
  <para>
    This method is included for completeness. The Windows <xref linkend="defWindowsDoc"/> is very sparse on this topic. It
    simply says a string specifying the style, but doesn't say what styles are available. Currently, the ooDialog developers
    are not certain what string to use to get this method to work.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Requires Common Control <xref linkend="ovvComctl32"/> version 6.0 or later.
  </para>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::setWindowTheme() -->


<section id="mthTrackActivate" xreflabel="trackActivate"><title>trackActivate</title>
<indexterm><primary>trackActivate</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>trackActivate</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--trackActivate(--toolHwnd--+----------+--+-------------+--)--><
                              +-,-toolID-+  +-,-activate--+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Activates or deactivates a tracking ToolTip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolHwnd [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>toolID [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to be deleted.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>activate</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Must be true or false, use true to activate the ToolTip, false to deactivate it. If omitted, the default is true.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">Tool Identification</link> section explains exactly how the Rexx object
    combination is used to specify the tool to be deleted.
  </para>
  <para>
    Tracking ToolTips must be manually activated and deactivated by using the <emphasis
    role="italic">trackActivate</emphasis> method. Activation or deactivation also shows or hides the ToolTip, respectively.
  </para>
  <para>
     While a tracking ToolTip is active, the application must specify the location of the ToolTip by invoking the
     <xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/> method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::trackActivate() -->


<section id="mthTrackPosition" xreflabel="trackPosition"><title>trackPosition</title>
<indexterm><primary>trackPosition</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>trackPosition</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
Form 1:

>>--trackPosition(--point--)---------------------><

Form 2:

>>--trackPosition(--x,--y--)---------------------><

Generic form:

>>--trackPosition(--pt--)------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the position of a tracking ToolTip.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>pt [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The (x, y) coordinates of the position to set. As the syntax diagram indicates, the coordinates can be specified
        either as a single <xref linkend="clsPoint"/> object, or as two arguments, a separate x and a y coordinate.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Tracking ToolTips change position on the screen dynamically.  While a tracking ToolTip is active, the application must
    specify the location of the ToolTip by invoking the <emphasis role="italic">trackPosition</emphasis> method.
  </para>
  <para>
    The ToolTip control chooses where to display the ToolTip window based on the coordinates provided through the <emphasis
    role="italic">trackPosition</emphasis> method. This causes the ToolTip window to appear beside the tool to which it
    corresponds. To have ToolTip windows displayed at specific coordinates, include the ABSOLUTE keyword in the <emphasis
    role="italic">flags</emphasis> argument when adding the tool through the <xref linkend="mthAddTool"/>, <xref
    linkend="mthAddToolEx"/>, or <xref linkend="mthAddToolRect"/> methods.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::trackPosition() -->


<section id="mthUpdateClsToolTip" xreflabel="update"><title>update</title>
<indexterm><primary>update</primary><secondary>ToolTip class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>update</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--update---------------------------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Forces the current tool to be redrawn.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    There are no arguments for this method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::update() -->


<section id="mthUpdateTipText" xreflabel="updateTipText"><title>updateTipText</title>
<indexterm><primary>updateTipText</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolTip class</primary><secondary>updateTipText</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--updateTipText(--toolInfo--)------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Sets the ToolTip text for a tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolInfo [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        A <xref linkend="clsToolInfo"/> object that specifies the tool and the text for the update.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns 0, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The best way to use this method is to instantiate a new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object through the
    <xref linkend="mthForID"/> method and then set the <emphasis role="italic">text</emphasis> attribute of the object
    to the new text desired.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example updates the text for a tool:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  toolInfo = .ToolInfo~forID(self~newPushButton(IDCANCEL))
  toolInfo~text  = "Only push the cancel button if you want, or need, to end the dialog"

  toolTip~updateTipText(toolInfo)
]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolTip::updateTipText() -->


<section id="clsToolInfo" xreflabel="ToolInfo"><title>ToolInfo Class</title>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary></indexterm>
<para>
  A <emphasis role="italic">ToolInfo</emphasis> object contains information about a tool in a <xref linkend="clsToolTip"/>
  control. The attributes of the <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object reflect the information that defines a
  specific tool in the ToolTip control.
</para>
<para>
  <emphasis role="italic">ToolInfo</emphasis> objects are used in some of the methods of the
  <computeroutput>ToolTip</computeroutput> class to provide information to the ToolTip control, and / or, to receive
  information from the ToolTip control.
</para>

<section id="sctMethodsToolInfo"><title>Method Table</title>
<para>
  The following table lists the class and instance methods of the <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> class:

<table id="tblMethodsToolInfo" frame="all"> <title>ToolInfo Class Method Reference</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Method</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Class Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Class Methods</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="mthForHitTest">forHitTest</link></entry>
<entry>Returns a new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object to be used in the <xref linkend="mthHitTestInfoClsToolTip"/> method.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="mthForID">forID</link></entry>
<entry>Returns a new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object to be used for tool <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification.</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="mthNewClsToolInfo">new</link></entry>
<entry>Instantiates a new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Attribute Methods</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Attribute Methods</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="atrFlags">flags</link></entry>
<entry>Reflects the flags that define the style and options of the tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="atrRect">rect</link></entry>
<entry>Reflects the bounding rectangle coordinates of the tool when the tool is an application-defined rectangular area within a window's client area.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="atrResource">resource</link></entry>
<entry>Reserved for future enhancement.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="atrRexxHwnd">rexxHwnd</link></entry>
<entry>Reflects the Rexx object from which the first part of the 2-part system <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification</link> for a tool is derived.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="atrRexxID">rexxID</link></entry>
<entry>Reflects the Rexx object from which the second part of the 2-part system <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification</link> for a tool is derived.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="atrTextClsToolTip">text</link></entry>
<entry>Reflects the text set for the tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><link linkend="atrUserDataClsToolTip">userData</link></entry>
<entry>Reflects the application-defined user data value for the tool.</entry>
</row>
</tbody></tgroup>
</table>
</para>
</section>


<section id="mthForHitTest" xreflabel="forHitTest"><title>forHitTest (Class Method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>forHitTest</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>forHitTest</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--forHitTest(--hwndObj--)----------------------><
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns a new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object to be used in the <xref linkend="mthHitTestInfoClsToolTip"/>
  method.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The single argument is:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>hwndObj [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The Rexx tool or Rexx object that contains a tool that is going to be hit tested. For example, if the tool to be
        tested is a rectangular area, <emphasis role="italic">hwndObj</emphasis> should be the Rexx object that represents
        the window containing the rectangle. If the tool is a dialog control, then <emphasis role="italic">hwndObj</emphasis>
        should be the Rexx object that represents the dialog control.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a newly instantiated <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object designed to be used as the argument to the
    <emphasis role="italic">hitTest</emphasis> method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object is especially constructed to be of use in the <xref
    linkend="mthHitTestInfoClsToolTip"/> method. To be explicit, the <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object returned is
    initialized to an empty state and the normal tool identifiers are not set.  The returned
    <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object is not suitable to be used in any other methods that required a
    <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object, except the <emphasis role="italic">hitTest</emphasis> method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example comes from an application that has a number of rectangular tools in a dialog.  An arbitrary point is hit
    tested and if the hit succeeds, the filled in tool information is printed to the screen:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  hitTool = .ToolInfo~forHitTest(self)

  say 'Using' pos

  if tt~hitTest(hitTool, pos) then do
    say 'Got hit'
    say 'Tool info  hwnd:    ' hitTool~rexxHwnd
    say 'Tool info  id:      ' hitTool~rexxID
    say 'Tool info  text:    ' hitTool~text
    say 'Tool info  flags:   ' hitTool~flags
    say 'Tool info  rect:    ' hitTool~rect
    say 'Tool info  userData:' hitTool~userData
    say 'Tool info  resource:' hitTool~resource
    say
  end
  else do
    say 'NO hit'
  end

/*  Output might be for instance:

Using a Point (220, 101)
Got hit
Tool info  hwnd:     a SimpleDialog
Tool info  id:       777
Tool info  text:     Over main dialog, bottom right quadrant
Tool info  flags:    SUBCLASS TRANSPARENT
Tool info  rect:     a Rect (194, 101, 386, 200)
Tool info  userData: The NIL object
Tool info  resource: The NIL object

*/

/* Output from a miss:

Using a Point (220, 301)
NO hit

*/

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::forHitTest() -->


<section id="mthForID" xreflabel="forID"><title>forID (Class Method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>forID</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>forID</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--forID(--toolHwnd--+----------+--)------------><
                      +-,-toolID-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Returns a new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object to be used for tool <link
  linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification.</link>
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>toolHwnd [required]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> a tool to the operating system.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>toolID [optional]</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
        object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to the operaring system.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a newly instantiated <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object that can be used to identify a specific
    tool contained within a ToolTip.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Many of the <computeroutput>ToolTip</computeroutput> methods require that the tool the method pertains to be identified.
    The <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object returned from <emphasis role="italic">forID</emphasis> is useful for
    those method. In addition, some methods return information by filling in the attributes of a
    <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object that specifies a tool. This is another good use of the <emphasis
    role="italic">forID</emphasis> method.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example instantiates a new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object using the <emphasis
    role="italic">forID</emphasis> method and then uses the object to change the ToolTip text for a push button tool:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  toolInfo = .ToolInfo~forID(self~newPushButton(IDC_PB_TEST))
  toolInfo~text = "Push the 'Test' button when you are ready to begin the test suite for the final release."

  toolTip~setMaxTipWidth(140)
  toolTip~updateTipText(toolInfo)
]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::forID() -->

<section id="mthNewClsToolInfo"><title>new (Class Method)</title>
<indexterm><primary>new</primary><secondary>ToolInfo class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>new</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--new(-toolHwnd-+----------+-+-------+-+--------+-+-----+-+---------+-+-------+-)--><
                  +-,-toolID-+ +-,-txt-+ +-,-flgs-+ +-,-r-+ +-,-uData-+ +-,-rsv-+
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Instantiates a new <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Arguments:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The arguments are:
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term>toolHwnd [required]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
      object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> a tool to the operating system.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>toolID [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      The <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis> arguments are the Rexx
      object combination that <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identify</link> the tool to the operaring system.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>txt [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Text for the tool. If omitted, or the empty string, or the string: TEXTCALLBACK, then the ToolTip sends the <xref
      linkend="kywToolTipNEEDTEXT"/> notification and the program supplies the text.
    </para>
    <para>
      The length of the text must be less than 1024 characters, which includes any possible end of line (0x0D0A) sequences.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>flags [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      A list of 0 or more of the following keywords separated by spaces, case is not significant.
    </para>
    <para>
      <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
        <member>ABSOLUTE   </member>
        <member>CENTERTIP  </member>
        <member>IDISHWND   </member>
        <member>PARSELINKS </member>
        <member>RTLREADING </member>
        <member>SUBCLASS   </member>
        <member>TRACK      </member>
        <member>TRANSPARENT</member>
      </simplelist>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>ABSOLUTE</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Positions the ToolTip window at the exact same coordinates specified by the <xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/>
          method. Without this flag the ToolTip control chooses where to display the ToolTip window based on the
          coordinates specified, which places the ToolTip close to the tool. This flag must be used with the TRACK flag.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>CENTERTIP</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Centers the ToolTip window below the tool.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>IDISHWND</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Indicates that the ID part of the tool <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification</link> is the window
          handle to the tool. In general, the ooDialog framework will set this flag correctly by using knowledge it gains
          from parsing the <emphasis role="italic">toolHwnd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">toolID</emphasis>
          arguments. If the flag is required, the framework will set it, if the flag should not be used, the framework will
          remove it if it is set.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>PARSELINKS</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Requires Common Control <xref linkend="ovvComctl32"/> version 6.0 or later.
        </para>
        <para>
          Indicates that links in the ToolTip text should be parsed.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>RTLREADING</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Indicates that the ToolTip text will be displayed in the opposite direction to the text in the parent window.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>SUBCLASS</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Indicates that the ToolTip control should subclass the tool's window to intercept messages, such as WM_MOUSEMOVE.
          If this flag is not set, some means must be used so that the mouse messages are forwarded to the ToolTip control,
          for instance by using the <xref linkend="mthManageAtypicalTool"/> method.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>TRACK</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
           Positions the ToolTip window next to the tool to which it corresponds and moves the window according to
           coordinates supplied by the <xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/> method. The programmer must activate this
           type of tool using the <xref linkend="mthTrackActivate"/> method.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>TRANSPARENT</term>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          Causes the ToolTip control to forward mouse event messages to the parent window. This is limited to mouse events
          that occur within the bounds of the ToolTip window.
        </para>
        </listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>r [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      A <xref linkend="clsRect"/> object that specifies the bounding rectangle coordinates of the tool. The coordinates are
      in client <link linkend="defScreenCoordinates">coordinates</link> of the tool.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>uData [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      A user data value to be associated with the tool. This can be any Rexx object the programmer wants. Note that the
      value is associated with the tool, not the tool tip.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>rsv [optional]</term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      Reserved for future enhancement. This argument is completely ignored in the current implmentation of ooDialog. Future
      versions may be enhance to use this argument to specify a <xref linkend="clsResourceImage"/> object containing binary
      resources for the tool.
    </para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Return value:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a newly instantiated <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Except for the IDISHWND flag, the returned <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object is constructed exactly as the
    programmer specifies. This makes the object ideal for use in the <xref linkend="mthAddToolEx"/> method for those cases
    where the convenience <xref linkend="mthAddTool"/> and <xref linkend="mthAddToolRect"/> methods are not suitable.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect arguments are detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This example uses the <emphasis role="italic">new</emphasis> method to instantiate a
    <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object for an implementation of custom ToolTips for a <xref
    linkend="clsTreeView"/>:

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[

  tv = self~newTreeView(IDC_TREE)
  ret = tv~setItemHeight(20)
  tt = self~createToolTip(IDC_TT)

  rect = tv~clientRect

  toolInfo = .ToolInfo~new(tv, ID_TOOL_TV, '', 'TRANSPARENT', rect, helperObj)
  tt~addToolEx(toolInfo)

  tt~setMaxTipWidth(250)

  self~populateTree(tv)
  tt~manageAtypicalTool(tv, .array~of('RELAY', 'NEEDTEXT', 'SHOW'))

]]>
</programlisting>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::new() -->

<section id="atrFlags" xreflabel="flags"><title>flags (Attribute)</title>
<indexterm><primary>flags</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>flags</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--flags-----------------------------------------------------><

>>--flags = varName-------------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Reflects the flags that define the style and options of the tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">flags get:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns a string of 0 or more keywords separated by a single space that specify the flags set for this tool. If no flags
    are set, the empty string is returned. See the remarks for the keyword values and meanings.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">flags set:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Sets the flags for this tool to those specified by a string of 0 or more space separated keywords. Case is not
    significant. See the remarks for the possible keywords and their meaning.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The following keywords specify the individual flags that define the style and options for a ToolTip tool. The keywords
    are case insensitive.
  </para>
  <para>
    <simplelist type='vert' columns='3'>
      <member>ABSOLUTE   </member>
      <member>CENTERTIP  </member>
      <member>IDISHWND   </member>
      <member>PARSELINKS </member>
      <member>RTLREADING </member>
      <member>SUBCLASS   </member>
      <member>TRACK      </member>
      <member>TRANSPARENT</member>
    </simplelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>ABSOLUTE</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Indicates that the ToolTip should position its window at the exact same coordinates specified by the <xref
        linkend="mthTrackPosition"/> method. Without this flag the ToolTip control chooses where to display the ToolTip
        window based on the coordinates specified, which places the ToolTip close to the tool. This flag must be used with
        the TRACK flag.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>CENTERTIP</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Indicates that the ToolTip should centers its window below the tool.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>IDISHWND</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Indicates that the ID part of the tool <link linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification</link> is the window
        handle if the tool. If the programmer sets the <emphasis role="italic">flags</emphasis> attribute, it becomes the
        programmer's responsibility to set this flag correctly. Failure to do so will result in unpredictable behaviour.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>PARSELINKS</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Requires Common Control <xref linkend="ovvComctl32"/> version 6.0 or later.
      </para>
      <para>
        Indicates that links in the ToolTip text should be parsed.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>RTLREADING</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Indicates that the ToolTip text will be displayed in the opposite direction to the text in the parent window.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>SUBCLASS</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Indicates that the ToolTip control should subclass the tool's window to intercept messages, such as WM_MOUSEMOVE.
        If this flag is not set, some means must be used so that the mouse messages are forwarded to the ToolTip control.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>TRACK</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Indicates that the ToolTip should position its window next to the tool to which it corresponds and move the window
        according to coordinates supplied by the <xref linkend="mthTrackPosition"/> method. The programmer must activate this
        type of tool using the <xref linkend="mthTrackActivate"/> method.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>TRANSPARENT</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Causes the ToolTip control to forward mouse event messages to the parent window. This is limited to mouse events
        that occur within the bounds of the ToolTip window.
      </para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::flags() [attribute]  -->


<section id="atrRect" xreflabel="rect"><title>rect (Attribute)</title>
<indexterm><primary>rect</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>rect</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--rect-----------------------------------------------------><

>>--rect = varName-------------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Reflects the bounding rectangle coordinates of the tool when the tool is an application-defined rectangular area within a
  window's client area.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">rect get:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the bounding rectangle as a <xref linkend="clsRect"/> object.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">rect set:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Assign a <computeroutput>Rect</computeroutput> object to the <emphasis role="italic">rect</emphasis> attribute to define
    the tool as a rectangular area within a window.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    When the tool is not an application-defined rectangular area, the value of the <emphasis role="italic">rect</emphasis>
    attribute is a <computeroutput>rect</computeroutput> object whose coordinates are all 0. When the <emphasis
    role="italic">flags</emphasis> attribute includes the IDISHWND keyword, the <emphasis role="italic">rect</emphasis>
    attriubte is ignored by the ToolTip.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::rect() [attribute]  -->


<section id="atrResource" xreflabel="resource"><title>resource (Attribute)</title>
<indexterm><primary>resource</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>resource</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--resource-----------------------------------------------------><

>>--resource = varName-------------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Reserved for future enhancement.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">resource get:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the <computeroutput>.nil</computeroutput> object, always.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">resource set:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This attribute can not be set.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    If the <xref linkend="clsResourceImage"/> class is enhanced to work with string resources (a good possibility) then this
    attribute will be the <computeroutput>ResourceImage</computeroutput> that contains the string resource to use for the
    text of the tool.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::resource() [attribute]  -->


<section id="atrRexxHwnd" xreflabel="rexxHwnd"><title>rexxHwnd (Attribute)</title>
<indexterm><primary>rexxHwnd</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>rexxHwnd</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--rexxHwnd-----------------------------------------------------><

>>--rexxHwnd = varName-------------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Reflects the Rexx object from which the first part of the 2-part system <link
  linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification</link> for a tool is derived.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">rexxHwnd get:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the Rexx object that is used as part of the basis for the tool identification. This will always be either a
    dialog object or a dialog control object.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">rexxHwnd set:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The Rexx programmer can not set this attribute. It is set by the ooDialog framework when the
    <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object is instantiated and can not be changed after that.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::rexxHwnd() [attribute]  -->


<section id="atrRexxID" xreflabel="rexxID"><title>rexxID (Attribute)</title>
<indexterm><primary>rexxID</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>rexxID</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--rexxID-----------------------------------------------------><

>>--rexxID = varName-------------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Reflects the Rexx object from which the second part of the 2-part system <link
  linkend="sctToolIdentification">identification</link> for a tool is derived.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">rexxID get:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the Rexx object used as the ID portion of the tool identifier. This will always be either a dialog control object
    or a non-negative whole number. (Recall that in ooRexx all numbers are objects.)
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">rexxID set:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The Rexx programmer can not set this attribute. It is set by the ooDialog framework when the
    <computeroutput>ToolInfo</computeroutput> object is instantiated and can not be changed after that
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::rexxID() [attribute]  -->


<section id="atrTextClsToolTip" xreflabel="text"><title>text (Attribute)</title>
<indexterm><primary>text</primary><secondary>ToolInfo class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>text</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--text-----------------------------------------------------><

>>--text = varName-------------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Reflects the text set for the tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">text get:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the text for the tool, the empty string if the text is not set, or the string <emphasis
    role="italic">TextCallBack</emphasis> if the tool is set to use the call back feature. See the remarks for details on the
    call back feature.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">text set:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Assign this attribute the text string the ToolTip should display in its window for this tool. To set the ToolTip to use
    its call back feature, either assign the string <emphasis role="italic">TEXTCALLBACK</emphasis>, case is not significant,
    or assign the empty string.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Remarks:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
   The ToolTip provides a call back feature that can be used rather than setting a static text string for the tool. With this
   feature, the ToolTip sends the <xref linkend="kywToolTipNEEDTEXT"/> notification and the program supplies the text
   supplies the text for the tool by responding to the notification. To use this feature, the programmer should set the
   <emphasis role="italic">text</emphasis> attribute to either the string, <emphasis role="italic">TextCallBack</emphasis> ro
   the empty string.
  </para>
  <para>
    The length of the text must be less than 1024 characters, which includes any possible end of line (0x0D0A) sequences. Do
    not set the <emphasis role="italic">text</emphasis> attriubte to a string longer than 1023 characters.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::text() [attribute]  -->


<section id="atrUserDataClsToolTip" xreflabel="userData"><title>userData (Attribute)</title>
<indexterm><primary>userData</primary><secondary>ToolInfo class</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ToolInfo class</primary><secondary>userData</secondary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
>>--userData-----------------------------------------------------><

>>--userData = varName-------------------------------------------><

]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
  Reflects the application-defined user data value for the tool.
</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">userData get:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Returns the user data set for the tool, or the <computeroutput>.nil</computeroutput> object is no user data has been
    assigned.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">userData set:</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The programmer can assign a user data value to the tool. This can be any Rexx object desired.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Raises syntax errors when incorrect usage is detected.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>  <!-- End ToolInfo::userData() [attribute]  -->

</section> <!-- End ToolInfo Class -->


</chapter>  <!-- End ToolTip class -->
