<!--#########################################################################
    #
    # Description: Open Object Rexx: ooDialog Reference SGML file.
    #
    # Copyright (c) 2012-2012 Rexx Language Association. All rights reserved.
    #
    # This program and the accompanying materials are made available under
    # the terms of the Common Public License v1.0 which accompanies this
    # distribution. A copy is also available at the following address:
    # http://www.oorexx.org/license.html
    #
    # Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
    # without modification, are permitted provided that the following
    # conditions are met:
    #
    # Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    # Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    # notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
    # the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    #
    # Neither the name of Rexx Language Association nor the names
    # of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
    # derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
    #
    # THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    # "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
    # LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
    # FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
    # OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
    # SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    # TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA,
    # OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
    # OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    # NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    # SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    #
    #########################################################################
-->
<chapter id="chapOverview"><title>Brief Overview</title>
<indexterm><primary>overview</primary></indexterm>
<para>
  ooSQLite is a
</para>
<para>
</para>

<section id="sctGettingStarted"><title>Getting Started</title>
<para>
  Text
</para>
<para>
  Text
  In addition the <link
  linkend="helpGettingHelp">getting help </link> section of this reference lists a number of resources for the
  programmer with questions about ooSQLite.
</para>
</section>

<section id="sctTermDefs"><title>Definition of Terms</title>
<para>
  A collection of definitions and explanations for terms used in the ooSQLite documentation. These terms may not be
  familiar to the average Rexx programmer.
</para>

<section id="defSomeTerm"><title>SomeTerm</title>
<para>
  Text
</para>
</section>


</section> <!-- End: Definition of Terms -->

<section id="sctGeneralOOSQLite"><title>Common Concepts</title>
<para>
  Some common concepts in ooSQLite text text
</para>

<section id="ovvSomeConcept"><title>SomeConcept</title>
<para>
  PROVIDE TEXT
</para>
</section>


</section> <!-- End: Common Concepts -->


<section id="sctSomeSection"><title>SomeSection</title>
<para>
  text
</para>
<para>
  IBM announced and released several successive versions of Object Rexx for Windows over the following years. For
  instance, Object REXX for Windows V2R1 was announced March 2001.  In May 2004, IBM announced its intention to
  contribute the source code for Object Rexx to RexxLA, and the ooRexx project was born. It took the best part of a year
  to work out the details and for the ooRexx developers to get the first version of ooRexx built and released. ooRexx
  3.0, the first ooRexx release, took place on March 25th 2005.
</para>
<para>
  From that point, the ooRexx team began regularly releasing new versions of ooRexx, up through the release of ooRexx
  3.2.0 on November 5, 2007. After the release of 3.2.0, the ooRexx team concentrated on refactoring the interpreter and
  on adding a new set of native APIs used to write extensions to the ooRexx interpreter.  The new APIs allowed the
  passing ooRexx objects to the routines and methods used in extensions.  Previously, only strings could be passed to
  external libraries. The refactored ooRexx interpreter and the new native APIs were introduced in ooRexx 4.0.0,
  released in August 2009.
</para>
<para>
  Up until that release in the middle of 2009, ooDialog remained virtually unchanged. The evolution of the Windows
  operating system had passed it by. ooDialog was designed for Windows 3.1, or at the latest Windows 95. It still
  referred to dialog controls such as the list-view as "new" controls. Despite the fact that the list-view control had
  been in use for over a decade. Some controls were considered "advanced" in ooDialog, while in Windows itself they were
  considered old news.
</para>
<para>
  Much of the design of ooDialog was based on constraints that existed in Windows 3.1 and Windows 95 that no longer
  existed in modern operating systems. For instance, the reason for having three separate ooDialog class files,
  <computeroutput>OODPLAIN.CLS, OODIALOG.CLS, and OODWIN32.CLS</computeroutput>, and for providing the simpler
  <computeroutput>PlainUserDialog</computeroutput> class was to have a smaller package that required less system
  resources for ordinary user interfaces like the standard dialogs.  That reason is not as valid in modern times as it
  was when ooDialog was being developed to run on Windows 3.1. Many of the programming techniques in the ooDialog
  implementation were also outdated. The conversion of dialog units to pixels and vice versa in ooDialog is a good
  example. While the technique must have worked in very early versions of Windows, it is completely wrong in Windows XP
  and later.
</para>
<para>
  The release of the new C++ native APIs in ooRexx 4.0.0 allowed much richer extensions to the Rexx interpreter to be
  written. Extensions could be implemented that had access to the actual objects instantiated within the
  interpreter. During the release of ooRexx 4.0.0, the internal work was started to convert ooDialog to use the C++
  APIs. This work lead to the complete refactoring of the ooDialog code, and the effort to bring ooDialog up to the
  level of Windows Vista and Windows 7 got started. New dialog controls were added along with new dialog objects and
  methods. However, this work was done in the internal development source tree and was not ready for the 4.0.0, 4.0.1,
  and 4.1.0 releases of ooRexx. Although ooDialog in those releases had some improvements and enhancements, they were
  minor.
</para>
<para>
  ooRexx 4.1.0 was released in December 2010. At that time, the internal work to convert ooDialog to the C++ APIs and
  the refactoring of the ooDialog source code was complete, but the refactored ooDialog was not ready for release,
  primarily because the documentation was not complete. The ooDialog distributed with ooRexx 4.1.0 was essentially the
  same as the ooDialog distributed with ooRexx 4.0.0, with bug fixes and some small enhancements. A small bug fix
  version of ooRexx 4.1.1 was released in March 2012. The ooDialog distributed in 4.1.1 is identical to the 4.1.0
  ooDialog.
</para>
<para>
  When the work of getting ooRexx 4.1.0 out the door was finished, some observations about ooDialog were made. One was
  that previously no real versioning of ooDialog was done. The second was that each of the ooDialogs shipped with ooRexx
  4.0.0, 4.0.1, and 4.1.0 only required an ooRexx 4.0.0 interpreter to work, while the refactored ooDialog in the
  internal development source tree required an ooRexx 4.1.0 interpreter. The third observation was that, since ooDialog
  is an extension to the Rexx interpreter, there is no reason why it could not be distributed independently of the
  ooRexx interpreter. Finally, it had been observed from some comments made in bugs opened up against ooDialog, that
  there were a few people who seemed to prefer to remain with an ooDialog that was designed for Windows 95, in essence
  an ooDialog unchanged from the ooDialog shipped with ooRexx 3.2.0.
</para>
<para>
  This lead to the decision to define a more formal versioning scheme for ooDialog and also to implement a means to
  distribute ooDialog independently of the ooRexx distribution. The version string of ooDialog had already been defined
  to be the version string of the ooRexx interpreter ooDialog was built under. A second part of the ooDialog version was
  to be the ooDialog level. This is similar to the language level of the Rexx interpreter. The initial ooDialog levels
  are listed in this table:
</para>
<table id="tblOODialogLevels" frame="all" pgwide='1'>
<title>ooDialog Levels</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec align='left' colwidth='1*'>
<colspec align='left' colwidth='1*'>
<colspec align='left' colwidth='6*'>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Level</entry>
<entry>Required Interpreter</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>3.2.0</entry>
<entry>4.0.0</entry>
<entry>ooDialog implementation using Rexx classic external routines.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>4.1.0</entry>
<entry>4.0.0</entry>
<entry>ooDialog as shipped with ooRexx 4.0.0 with all bug fixes through ooRexx 4.1.1.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>4.2.0</entry>
<entry>4.1.0</entry>
<entry>Refactored ooDialog completely implemented with the C++ native API.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Level 3.2.0</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The ooDialog code at level 3.2.0 is frozen. Since the implementing code uses the classic external routines and the
    code itself is unchanged from the ooDialog shipped with ooRexx 3.2.0, ooDialog programs should behave
    exactly as they did under the ooDialog shipped with ooRexx 3.2.0. No fixes, enhancements, or changes will be made to
    the code.
  </para>
  <para>
    It is available as a separate download from SourceForge using the <emphasis role="italic">Switch ooDialog</emphasis>
    technology for users who would like to replace their installed ooDialog with a 3.2.0 level ooDialog. It requires
    that the installed ooRexx is 4.0.0 or later. Although the code is frozen, if a user can demonstrate an ooDialog
    program behaves differently using a 3.2.0 level ooDialog than it did under an actual ooRexx 3.2.0 installation, a
    fix will be considered.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Level 4.1.0</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    ooDialog at level 4.1.0 is the ooDialog that shipped with ooRexx 4.0.0, plus all bug fixes and changes up through
    ooRexx 4.1.1. It is also provided as a separate download on SourceForge and also requires the installed ooRexx be
    4.0.0 or later. This code is frozen, no changes will be made to the code. Bugs found in this code will be fixed in
    upcoming releases of ooDialog.
  </para>
  <para>
    It allows users that have not upgraded their ooRexx from 4.0.0 or 4.0.1 to pick up the bug fixes in ooDialog
    included in the ooRexx distributions up through ooRexx 4.1.1. However, its primary purpose is for users who may be
    unhappy with the future direction of ooDialog. It will provide a way for users to upgrade to future versions of
    ooRexx and yet retain an unchanged ooDialog.
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term><emphasis role="bold">Level 4.2.0</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    This is the actively maintained ooDialog level. The level will be incremented in the future as circumstances
    dictate. It requires an installed ooRexx of 4.1.0 or later. New versions of ooDialog at the 4.2.0 level will be
    released as they become ready. It is available as a separate download from SourceForge and will also be the
    ooDialog level shipped with future versions of ooRexx, (versions past ooRexx 4.1.1.)
  </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</section>


</chapter>
