<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "rxsock.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter><title>Installation</title>
<indexterm><primary>RxFtp installation</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>installation, RxFtp</primary></indexterm>
<para>The RxFtp package is contained in the file
<emphasis role="italic">rxftp.cls</emphasis>. This file must be placed in
a directory listed in your PATH. To get access to the class and methods in the RxFtp
package you must include a ::REQUIRES directive in any Object Rexx script that
uses the class:
<indexterm><primary>::REQUIRES directive, RxFtp</primary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
     .
     .
     .
::requires "rxftp.cls"
</programlisting></para>

<para>You instantiate an instance of the class using the normal Object Rexx
conventions.
<programlisting>
myftpobj = .rxftp~new
</programlisting></para>
<para>Each instance of the class completely encapsulates a connection to an
FTP server. This means that you can  instantiate multiples instance of the class
and have multiple open connections to FTP servers simultaneously.</para>

<section><title>Notes on Using RxFtp</title>
<indexterm><primary>RxFtp notes</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>notes, RxFtp</primary></indexterm>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>
The FtpProxy method does not exist in the RxFtp class.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Firewalls can prevent many of the RxFtp methods from working
properly. Active and passive mode transfers can both be restricted by the use
of firewalls. This especially applies to active mode transfers when the client
is running a firewall locally (like WindowsXP SP2 or any modern Linux
distribution).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Each instance of the RxFtp class you
 instantiate has its own connection to an FTP server. Thus
you can  instantiate multiple instance of this class and
connect to multiple FTP servers simultaneously. Also, each
instance can be reused - the FtpLogoff method reinitializes
the instance and a following FtpSetUser method can establish
a new connection to an FTP server.
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</chapter>
